<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
〓n intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivarta SzuKI takayasu 1.The aim of This paper. continuous verification of the hypothesis as has been already illustrated in a series of previous studies,) the suvarnapra bhsutra of golelight, suv,)one of the Mahayana buddhist scriptures which has collected and demonstrated various doctrines and rites of both mundane anc supermundane levels, and has long had wide influence over the way of thinking and living of asans, seems to have been underestimated in some cases by the modern scholarly world with remarks such as " the suv is a mere miscellaneous medlley of doctrines and rites" or " the features appearing in the suv represent either a token of the assimilation of buddhism into hinduism or a token of the depravity of Buddhistn." ln relation to this, the present author focusing attention on the complicated struc-ture of the suv and on the description in the caturmaharoia-parivarta,) has, partly upported by some archeological results,4)already proposed the following hypothesis 〓 one of the intentions of the compilers of the swv &lt;The hypothesis) owing to the account of the suv which has, through thc scveral stages of its formation, collected and demonstrated various doctrines and rites of both mundane and supermundane levels already expounded in the treatises either of mahayana. of non-Mahayana, or of non-buddhism e., of hinduism) before, the compilers and the proponents of the suy became more able to lead their daily religious livcs, including their practice of various rites and their attainment of various religious merits, in accordance with "the teaching of the suv," that is, "the teaching of [mahayanal buddhism." we can therefore interpret thc features appearing in the suv not as a tokcn of "thc assimilation of Buddhism into hinduism" or "the depravity of buddhism," but as an attempt of buddhists to survive in the indian religious world by cmphasizing the value, the usefulness, and the completcncss of [Mahayana] buddhism to the proponents under circumstanccs where hin-  〓 intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhusa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivart . suzuk1)円 duism had become more and more dominant over buddhism during and after the gupte period). Moreover, if one of the intentions of the compilers of the suy lies in this attemp1 by collecting as many doctrines and rites as possible, however mundane or supermundane thcy might be, from the stage of the formation of the suvcl to that of the suvc3 consistent ly, we might be able to suppose that the intention of the compilers has remained unchangec a11 through the stages of the formation of the suv. furthermore, it might turn out that the Suv is not "a merc miscellaneous medlley of doctrines and rites," but a collcction of therr which is intrinsic to the value of the suv. This paper continuously verifies this hypothesis by examining the drdha. parivarta chapter on the earth-goddess drdha; chapter l85)of the sup), which is the fourth chapter in "the Five chapters on the various gods and Goddesses."6) 〓.a brief survey of the drdha-parivarta (chapter on the earth-goddess drdha; chapte 18) we will begin with a brief survey of the drdha-parivarta by dividing it approxi mately into five sections (from 〓l to〓5). 〓l:The earth-goddess drdha(堅牢地神)makes an address in the presence of the Lord sakyamuni as follows: when thc suv is being expounded, the earth-goddess drdha, together with her rctinue, will become stronger and more powerful. In their bodies therc will be produced great power, fortitude, and strength. having gone up to the seat of the law with invisible body, she will lean with her head upon the soles of the feet of the monks, nuns, laymcn and lay-women who are preaching the suv. after having been satisfied with the nectar juice of the Suv and having obtained great brilliance and strength, she will causc to increase thc savor of thc carth and make the earth stronger so that the various fruits and crops will be strong. cr, more tasty and grcater. a11 those beings that are dependent upon the earth will find increase and become great. having becomc great, they will enjoy the various cnjoyments and plcasures on earth such as various foods, drinks, and nourishment, these and similar varieties of blessings existing on the earth and dependent upon the earth. for this reason. a11 beings should show gratitude to her by means of listening to respectfully, honoring, and worshipping the suv. by the hearing of the suy they will have escaped from cvil states such as hell and will have gained rebirth among gods and men in future time. wherever the various beings in various regions on the earth tcll onc another even a  〓n intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa xpressed and intimated in the drha-parivarta  Suzuki single chapter or a single birth-story, even the namc of a single bodhisattva or tatha gata, even a four-verse stanza or a single versc, or even the mere name of the suv, a1 those regions of thc earth will becomc stronger and more moist. the various savors of the earth will increase for a11 the beings in those regions of the earth. a11 those beings will be blessed and will have great wealth and enjoyment. They will be devoted to liberality danadhimuktani ca bhavisyanti). they will have faith in the Threc jcwcls of buddhism (trisu ratnesv abhiprasannani bhavisyanti). (See emmerick [19965-56d) 〓2the lord Sakyamuni tells the earth-goddess drdha the merits of hearing and honoring the suv: whatever beings may hear even a single verse from the suv, they will transmigrate from this world of men and will be reborn among the groups of gods. whatever beings may honor the suy by adorning their houses and covering them with even a single umbrella or a flag, those adorned houses will become divine palaces made of the seven jewels. and when those beings transmigrate fronr this world of men, they will be reborn in those divine palaces seven times and will1 experience inconceivable divine blessings. (See Emmerick [199-571) 〓3:the earth-goddess drdha makes a vow to protect the preachers of the suy: She will dwell in those regions of the earth where the preachers of the suv have sa1 upon the seat of the law, and with invisible body she will lean her head upon the soles of the feet of them so that the suv, for the welfare of a11 beings, may long go forth in this world, so that beings may hear the suv, so that they may in future time experience inconceivable divine and human pleasures (anagate 'thuany. acintyan. divyamanusyakani sukhami pratyanubhaveyuh), so that they may meet tathagatas (tatha-ratasamavadhanagatas ca bhaveyuh), so that they may in future time awaken to su-preme and perfect enlightenment (anagate 'ahvany anuttaram samyaksambodhim abhisambudheran), and so that a11 the woes of hells and so on may be wholly cut off (sarvanaraka-tiryagyoni-yamalokaduhkhani catyantena samucchinnani bhaveyur).(See Emmerick [1996571) The first Chinese version suvcl rendered by dharmaksema(曇無識)in the 5th entury(412-421),the second chinese version suvc2 combined by bao-gui(寶貴)in 597,the Sanskrit text suvs, and the smaller tibetan version suvm conclude chapter 18with the end of this section. 〓4: This 〓4 and the next 〓5 only exist in the larger tibetan version suyt2 and the 〓  〓 lntention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhosa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivarta . Suzuk1)2 third chinese version suvc3 rendered by yi-ing(義淨)in the year73. The earth-goddess drdha states that she holds a spell (snags, * mantra; gzuns snags kdcharam ) which can bring about the welfare and blessing to a11 the divine and humar beings, and she gives instructions how to employ it involving the worship of those images sku gzugs, * pratima) and stupas (mchod rten, * stupa or caitya7)in which the relics i bsrel, *sarira or dhatu ) of the buddha are deposited. Then she adds instructions in another two spells that enable the beings to meet her and to be blessed by her. after these instructions she concludes her address insisting that her power of protection and blessing originates in the three jewels of buddhismsnis rgyas dkon mchog dn chos dkon mchog d dge un dkon mchog,*buddharatna-dharmaratng. samgharatna). 〓the lord offers congratulations to the earth-goddess drdha who protects the Suv together with its preachers, and prophesies that she will obtain inconceivable merits by her act of protection. The structure of chapter i8can be tabled as follows Table l. The structure of the drdha-parivart chapter l8) we can see from table l that the content of the drdha-parivarta was enlarged through the two stages of formation. Chapter18 scc2),suvs, suyr (the first stage)〓ur2, suvc3 the seconc and last stage)  〓 intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa xpressed and lntimated in the drdha-parivart. Suzuk1) 3. the intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa expressed and intimatec in the drdha-parivarta Having taken a brief overview, let us now return to the successive verificationo the above-mentioned hypothesis by examining this drdha-parivarta, paying careful attention not to overlook the intention of the compilers of the suv expressed and intiinated in this chapter. First, almost a11 of the religious merits this chapter 8 refers to are not the ones peculiar to buddhism but nothing other than those merits which are mundane anc popular in india. the merits of hearing and honoring the suv are, for example, tc increase the savor of the earth, to make this circle of the earth moist with the mois savor of the earth, to make the earth stronger so that the various plants and trees will grow stronger, to make a11 the various fruits and crops grow stronger, more fra-grant, more tasty and greater so that those beings who have enjoyed those various drinks and foods will increase their longevity, strength, commplexion, and senses, tc have great wealth and enioyment, to escape from hell, the region of animals and the world of ghosts, and in future time to gain rebirth among gods and men. in contrast. only a few of the supermundane merits regarded as intrinsic to buddhism are listed. The minority exceptions in this Chapter 18 should be at the most to meet tathagatas and to awakenin future timne to supreme and perfect enlightenment. This tendency remains unchanged in the second and last stage since the merits attained by mploying the several spells are such as to obtain prosperity, health, and longevity, mnd to be protected against enemies Second, suggested by the description in〓l, there is high possibility that the hearers or the proponents of this chapter the compilers of the suv had expected are hose who were engaged in agriculture. to take somne examples that reinforce this assumption, the beings who should be blessed by the earth-goddess drdha are described as "those beings who are dependent upon the earth sattvani prthivi-samnisritani, suvs,as those beings who "will perform the various numerous hundreds of thousands of activities o earth nanavidhani prthivigatany anekon nanavidhani karyasatasahasrani karisyanti, suvs12-14, and as those beings who "will do acts that have to be done with power (balakaraniyami karmani karisyanti, suvs 123.1)on top of that, belief in "the earth-goddess" or " the spirit of the earth" that  〓 intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhosa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivarta (T. Suzukl)(6 brings about fertility is in general a very common one any time and anywhers among farmers. There seems thus considerable validity for this assumption Agricultural areas in India are said to have been very concerned about conven tionalities, and the same is true of religious tradition, that is, in agricultural areas ir India hinduism has been predominant over buddhism. if one of the intentions of the compilers of the suv, as proposed in the hypothesis, lies in an attempt to survive in the religious world of India by emphasizing the value and the usefulness of [Mahayana] buddhism to these proponents, this chapter i8chapter on the Earth  oddess drdha) may have been compiled for emphasizing the value and the useful- 1ess of the swv to those farmers in india who might have not been buddhists at that time. this attempt was therefore, as it were, "to open up a new market." as well a the characteristics pointed out above that almost a11 of the religious merits this Chapter 18 refers to are not peculiar to buddhism but popular and mundane, a de scription inuggesting that those people who should employ the spell for the welfare and blessing do not necessarily need to be buddhists,8) may also serve t strengthen this assummption and consequently the hypothesis. Third, in spite of the lack of laying stress of the merits intrinsic to buddhism, the value of the three jewels (ie. the value of buddhism) is much emphasized and enhanced both in the first stage and in the second and last stage. what draw ou1 ittention here are the contexts in which the descriptions on the Three jewels ppear. in(in the first stage) the description appears in the context that the beings will have faith in the Three jewels and will be devoted to offering, since they have become blessed and had great wealth and enjoyment through the power of the earth-goddess drdha who was encouraged by one of the buddhist sutras named suv9) And in the sccond stage) the description appears in the context that those beings who employ the several spells taught by the earth-goddess drdha will be blessed and protected since she is always watched over by the three jewels so that ihe can grant the beings blessing and protection.10)it must be also noted that in these contexts chapter 18 refers to the Three jewels, that is, buddhist monks and nuns as well as the buddha and the law. From these descriptions in the particular contexts, we ca comprehend the inten-tion of the compilers of the suv as follows. "since the beings will be blessed, will  〓 intention of the compilers of the suparnaprabhasa expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivarta T. suzuk) have great wealth and enjoyment, and will be protected by the power of the earth-goddess drdha who is encouraged by one of the buddhist scriptures named Suy and is always watched over by the Three jewels of buddhism, it is highly expected that they will be willing to make a lot of offerings to the buddhal1)or buddhist monasteries, not to the hindu gods or brahmins." As has been pointed out in Suzuki [2], buddhist monks and nuns who have transmitted the law of the buddha and practiced for the supreme enlightenment. cannot accomplish their duty without any assistance, especially financial assistance of lay people. thus the hypothesis proposed by the present author appears quite reasonable, that one of the intentions of the compilers of the suy lies in their attempt to survive in the religious world of india by emphasizing the value and the usefulness of lmahayanal buddhism to the proponents, by consistently collecting nany doctrines and rites a11 through the stage of the formation. 4.atentative conclusion lt is tentatively concluded here, from what has been said above, that with the compilation of chapter 18 referring to those religious merits which are mundane and popular in india, the compilers of the suv must have attempted to emphasize the value and the usefulness of the suv to the proponents, especially to those farmers in india who mmight have not been buddhists at that time, and also attempted to attain financial aid from the proponents for the sake of accomplishing their transmittion of the law and religious practice for the supreme enlightenment. we can therefore say that the validity of the hypothesis has been strengthened through the examination in this paper. however, its verification still needs to be studied in further research. )suzuki, t. [199] the mahameghasutra as a origin of an interpolated part of the present suvarnaprabhasa, jjournal of indicnd buddhist studies 8945-1), tokyo, pp 〓8-30Suzuki, t 3]stupa worship and dharma evaluation in thc suvarnapra-bhasa, journal of indian ad buddhist studies (-2),tokyo, pp.3-3; suzuki, 〓.[4]rites and buddhismperspective from the sarasvati-parivarta in the suvarnaprabhasa, journal of indian ad buddhist studies 102-2),tokyo, pp.121, suzuki, t. [ the unchanged intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa:  〓 intention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivaria (t. suzuk1)(71) a Examination through the verification of the hypothcsis on "the independencc of [Mahayana] buddhism," journal of indian ad buddhist studies 1(3-2),tokyo, pp. 〓0-26,suzuki, t.[2the primary introduction of the rites for good fortune into the suvarnaprabas described in the sri-parivarta, journal of indicn ad buddhist studies 1(4-3), tokyo,206,pp.42-50,and Suzuki [998a,1998c,1999,2005a anc 2b]i japanese. Suv suvarnaprabhasa or suvarn/-pr- jbhasottamasutrendraroja. 2)&lt;texts and abbreviations Suvcl『金光明經』四卷,曇無識譯.t. no.663 suvs suvarnabhasottamasutra, ed. J. nobel, leipzig,1937 suvt 'phgs p gser 'od dp mdo sde'i d poi rgyalps bya ba theg p chen po'i mdo,ary-suvarnaprabhasottamasutrendraroia-hama-mahoyana-sutra, tr.un known. p no.17 suvc2『合部金光明經』八卷,寶貴合粹.t. no.664. Suvr2 phags p gser 'od dmp mdo sde'i d po'i rgyl pzs bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo, ary-varnaprabhosottamasutrendraroia-nama-mnahayana-sutra, tr. jina. mitra, silendrabodhi and Ye ses sde. p no.175. Suvc3『金光明最勝王經』十卷,義淨譯.t. No.665 suvr suvarnaprabhasottamasutra, ed. J. nobel, leiden, 1944 (<ref><canon>T</canon>. <w>taisho tripitaka</w></ref>,p peking kanjur ) 3)"whatever mundane and supermundane (laukikalokottara) treatises have gone fort in the whole of Jambudvipa, by which these beings will be blessed, a11 those have beer revealed, expounded, and set forth here in the excellcnt suv, king of sutras, which is superior and more outstanding, by the lord, the tathagata, the arhat, the fully cnlight-ned one." (suvs 97-98.) see suzuki [200and2]. 4)the report that the first inscription supposed to belong to Mahayana can date back to no earlier than the 5-bth century c.e. might suggest that Mahayana buddhism had pecame popular or known after that period. see suzuki [2004]. 5)堅牢地神品第十八.the way of numbering the chapters in this paper follows the wa) in the suvc, 6)the present author calls the five successive chapters consisting of the caturmaha-raia-parivarta (see suzuki [0),the sarasvati-parivarta (see suzuki [2004]), the sri-parivarta (see suzuki [d), the drdha-parivarta, and the saminaya-parivarta, ethe fivc chapters on the various Gods and Goddesses," which tell the various merits granted to the proponents of the suv by the various gods and goddesses. 7)制底(suvc34c28).This, however, does not follow that the original Sanskrit word for mchod rten here is caitya since there are several cases where"制底"in the suvc3 corresponds to stupa in the suvs (suvc4l9 and suvs 1; u349 and suvs 159.8. suvc34a1 and suvs., and so on)  〓 lntention of the compilers of the suvarnaprabhasa Expressed and intimated in the drdha-parivart . suzuki 〓)pyspasiba pudmr , t)ogllazggssnss hbzils pas 8)skyes pa'am bud med dam〓khor bzi po gan la la ig gis. gzuns snags 'di bzlas pas spyan dran bar 'gyur te (Swv-15). 若有男子女人及諸四衆,(中略)即可誦此請召之呪.(suvlal). since a11 the budchists can be representcd by " buddhist monks, nuns, laymen, and lay women'khor bii po,四衆),"it may follow that " menkyes pa,男子)"and "women d med,女人)" here refer to non-buddhists 9)yatra yatra bhadanta bhagavams tani nanavidhani sattvani nanavidhesu prthivipradesesu imany evamrupani nanavidhani sutrantahetuni parasparenarocayeran samsravayeran va kathasambandham va kurviran/ sarve te bhadanta bhagavan prthivipradesa ojasvitaras ca bhavisyanti snigdhataras ca bhavisyanti/ sarvesan sattvanam tesu tesu prthivipradesesu nanavidhani prthivirasani sarvopakaranani bhuyisthataram utpatsyante vivardhayisyante vaipulyatan gamisyanti/ sarvani tani sattvani sukhitani bhavisyanti/ mahadhanani mahabhogani ca danadhimuktani ca bhavisyanti/ trisu ratnesv abhiprasannani bhavisy. nti//Suvs11) 10)sems mi g-yen bar snags 'di bzlas na/ bsam pa thams cad 'grub par 'gyur te/ bdag gi tshig 'di mi slu bar ni sans rgyas dkon mchog dan/ chos dkon mchog dan/ dge 'dun dkon mchog rnams bdag la mnon du gzigs sin dgons par gsolur4-) 若有至心誦此呪者,所求必遂.我不妄語.我以仏法僧宝,而為要契,証知是実. (sucl19-21) 11)since the buddha Sakyamuni has already entered into his perfect pcacefulness (parinipvrta), these offcrings are to be made to those stupas or images of the buddha hat represent the buddha and are recognized as none other than the buddha himself. (Kev words)金光明経堅牢地神品,金光明経の編纂意図,〔大乗〕仏教の生き残り策とし ての金光明経,インド〔大乗〕仏教の実像理解. (professor, Yamaguchi prefectural university, d.litt.)  
</root>
