<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The vimalakirtinirdesa's Narration on the amrta distribution and its Exploitation by the pus chutai jing's Authors Elsa lEGiTTIMO Introductory notes The present paper discusses the means employed by the authors of the pus chutai jing for conferring an altered message regarding events and motives that occur in the vimalakirtinirdesa. it further includes a comparative study on the asta-vimoksa conceptin relation to food or drink. whereas the vimalakirtinirdesa, the key topic of this year's congress of the Japanese association of indian and buddhist studies, is still at the crest of its fame the pus chutoi ji The sutra heldby the bodhisattva within the womb菩薩處胎經)1) belongs to a once influential and now forgotten genre of buddhist literature.2) just before entering nirvana the buddha recalls in this sutra the very first exposition he held in his mother's womb and creates a great womb palace for his auditors. acer-tain parallelism exists with vimalakirti's empty house or sick-room that accommo dates a huge assembly. i. The tathagata's food gift and the creation of golden-colored bodhisattva(s) The vimalakirtinirdesa's chapter nine, the "nirmitabhojananayanaparivarta" ("the chapter on the created/fictive food's provision",)focuses on the amria (sweet dew甘露) given by sugandhakuta tathagata to the golden-colored fictive bodhisattva sent to the sarvagandhasugandha universe by vimalakirti. The main heroes of this play are vimalakirti, his fictive bodhisattva who brings back the precious food, and Sugandhakuta tathagata. the amrta is distributed to the beings of this world with-out Sakyamuni buddha's personal intervention. Chapter four ("the buddha tree"佛樹)of the pusa chutai jing relates to these events in its final section on the special powers (rddhi-pada神足)the buddha ac-quired as a bodhisattva: 1) eye (divya-caksus),2)ear divya-srotram),3)nose4).  the yimalakirtinirdesa's narrationon the amrta distribution and its exploitation by the pusa chutai jing's authors (e. lgittimo) 〓 4)mouth,5)and5) bodily power. between the third and fourth power exists ar apparent chapter closing: twelve yojangs of living beings become awakened and ask to be reborn in the gandhasugandha buddhaksetra(香積佛刹)6)under the "moutl power" the text then states. From jambudvipa up to the eighteenth heaven, everybody sces the tathagata eating. the bodhisattvas of the first stage up to the forth stage perccive the tathagata's body's lapis lazuli throat. the bodhisattvas of the non-returning (avaivartikafanagamin不退轉)stage up to the ninth stage perceive the strong and the ailing ones. The heavenly beings pick u thc tathagata's food, give it to a11 the other worlds, and there carry out buddha-activities (buddha- korya佛事).this is the retribution of the tathagata's mouth power. the tathagata shows the food's taste, the taste of tastes (rsarasagrafd次第味味),7)the unmovable taste that is neithcr swallowed nor chewed. while lifting up the food towards his mouth thc Tathagata concentrates his mind on thinking that the senticnt beings of the five destinics in the ten directions, and a11 the other beings, shall likewise experiencc this taste. when he thinks of them they a11 becomc full and satisfied. like mohks rcaching the ninth dhyan stage whose minds are soft, beautiful and satiated. this is thc bodhisattva mahusattva's pure and calm mouth power."8) another relevant passage is found in the sutra's chapter eleven"Felicity" anumodana 隨喜).the buddha has a golden body(金體)and holds an exposition for usnisa-raja (頂王)bodhisattva of the " Safe dwelling world"(安住世界) By his divine powers the buddha then transforms the frisahasra-mahasahasra lokadhatu (onc-billion-worlds) into shiny golden color. he makes thosc in the meeting see the world of joy where the bodhisattvas are sitting on seven-treasure lotus flowers. Their disciples and retinue are a11 in golden color. they feed on meditation hyana) and release [and taks t] as their food and drinks.9 The ps chutai jing's authors took over several themes and narrations from the vimalakirtinirdesa. but they eclipsed the principal "heroes" and sakyamuni buddha is the sole "hero" responsible for the creation of golden-colored bodhisattvas. his food, respectively the satiating taste of it, is telepathically distributed from Jambudvipa to the beings of a11 the other worlds. 〓i. an analysis of the asta-vimoksa conceptin relation to food or drink within the chinese canon the concept of the eight-fold liberation asta-vimoksa八解  its exploitation by the pusa chutai jing's authors (e. lgittimo)(53 the vimalakirtinirdesa's Narration on the amrta distribution and 〓)is seen in simile-like relation with: the eight-fold path, meditation, nirvana, the six abhiina powers, water of release, a pond, or something eatable or drinkable This last combination is of significance for the topic of this paper. The few scrip-tures containing this theme can be classified into two categories: ) the three ver-sions of the vimalakirtinirdesand three vimalakirtinirdesa commentaries,11) and2) three texts translated by zhu fonian The simile like picture of the asta-vimoksa concept in relation to food appears twict in the vimalakirtinirdesa: in chapter three ("sravakabodhisattvavisarianaprasna", "th sravakas' and bodhisattvas' refusal to question[vimalakirti]) and in chapter nine. In chapter three the buddha tells his worthy disciples to make a visit t vimalakirti and to inquire about his health. one after the other, they refuse with 【eference to theit past encounters and discussions with the virtuous man. ever Kasyapa refuses and explains that vimalakirti had once criticized him: Honorable mahakasyapa, if you can without overstepping the cight depravities concentrate on the eight liberations, if through the equality of the depravitics you penetrate the equal-ity of holiness, and if by this single rice ball, you are able to satisfy a11 the beings and tc make offerings to a11 the buddhas and a11 the holy beings, only then you should eat your self. thc one who eats in this way is neither soiled nor non-soiled, neither concentrated nor out of concentration, neither in transmigration, nor fixcd in nirvana.2 In chapter nine the assembly is at vimalakirti's place. when the discussions on the bodhisattvas' entry into the doctrine of non-duality (advaya) end, sariputra worries about their lunch. vimalakirti reading his mind tells him: Honorable sariputra, the tathagata taught the sravakas the eight-fold liberation. you should adhere to it and should not listen to the dharmna with thoughts related to material things. however, if you want to eat, wait a moment, and you will cat food you have neve1 tasted before.13) The set of texts translated by Zhu Fonian includes: the antarabhavasutrthe sutra on the intermediate-state, zhong yin jing中陰經),4)the pus chutai jing and the ekottarika-agam (zng yia han jing増壹阿含經)15) In the antarabhavasutra the motive appears ina poem of chapter sixhe divine powers", rddhi-pada神足)spokenin praise of subuddhi tathagata:  the vimalakirtinirdesa's Narration on the amrta distribution and its exploitation by the pus chutai jing's authors (e.lgttimo) after having stayed for a long time hungrily and thirsty on the path, they drink by means among the devas and humans he is the most honored one without comparison. His light illuminates the sentient beings. of the eight-fold release.16) In the pusa chutai jing the particular combination is found at the end of chapter ten ("permanence and impermanence" nityo-amitya常無常)in a poem expounded by the Buddha: Through the eight-fold liberation [i, the buddha showproduce] the tasty juice of the swee dharma-dew(甘露法味漿)making those who are thirsty and desirous to feel fully satis fied in an unthinkable way (acintya)17) In the ps chutai jing and the antarabhavasutra the metaphor appears in verses oi passages that are only loosely linked to narrative contents. among zhu Fonian's translations only the ekottarik-gama sets the combination into a specific context: once, the buddha and his disciples made their begging tour through a certain brahmin's village, but did not obtain any alms, because Mara had told the villagers not to give anything to the sramamas. at that time the buddha expounded the won-derful teaching on the nine things or concepts which should be considered as food One of these is the food of the eight-fold liberation.18) In this light the passages of the vimalakirtinirdesa appear as reminiscences of these events. The authors of the p chutai jing and the antarabhavasutra were either influenced by the ekottarika-agama or by the vimalakirtinirdesa. of some jignificance might be the fact that while the motive in question is employed for Sugandhakuta in the vimalakirtinirdesa and for Subuddhi tathagata in the antarabhavasutra, the ekottarika-agama and the pu chutai jing use it for Sakyamuni buddha. The pusa chutai jing points to conservative counter-currents. the discussed notives and events help support its authors' sakyamuni-centered worldview. their copying procedures were motivated by their wish to correct passages they thought were diverging from their faith. The tathagata's amrta distribution is one out of numerous examples found in the pus chutai jing that clearly show a effort to restore the buddha sakyamuni's omnipotence. The present paper is only a particular case study. further important motives and themes, for example from the lotus  the yimalakirtinirdesa's narration on the amrta distribution and its exploitation by the pqchufai jing's authors (e.〓glttio)(55 svtra, underwent similar transformations bibliography LAmotte, etiennc, 〓'seignemenf de yimalakirti (vimalakirtinirdesa),1987,louvain-la-Ncuve. Legitimo, elsa i., aabysis of the pus chutai jing菩薩處胎經(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>12</v>,no.<w>84</w></ref>), inter-national college for postgraduate buddhist studies, phd thesis, 206, tokyo. (publica-tion planned in the series melanges chinois et bouddhiques of the institut belge des Hautes etudes chinoises, bruxelles, i7) 〓vrra, transliterated sanskrit texi collated with tibetnaa chinese translations, ed.by the study Group on buddhist sanskrit literature, thc Institute for comprehensive studies of buddhism, Taisho university, tokvo,〓4. 〓 1)cf.tl2,no.84,p. 18b25. 2)on the basis of internal as wcll as external evidence i showcd in my doctoral thesis (cf. leglttimo,20)conducted on this sutra, that it is not a chinese composition anc was translated around the vear4adby zhu Fonian(竺佛念). 3)cf. t vtinra,204,p.89.for the vimalakirtinirdesa's French translation cf. laottE,1987. 4)This power probably bases on the concept of the pureness of the nose (ghranaparisud-dhya鼻淨). 5)the passage also refers (with some distinctive deviation) to the first syllables of the 〓Racana syllabi, cf. tl2,p.1023. 5)cf. tl2,no.394,p.1022c. 7)one of the thirty-two laksaas of a buddha )cf. tl2, no.384, p.1033. 9)cf.tl2,no.384,p.103 10)cf.tl4,no.474,p.522a, and p.532a, tl4, no.475,p.40a-b, and p.52a, and tl4, no.47,p. 5lc-a, and p.579a 11)The three commentaries are the weimo jing yii維摩經義記(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>85</v>,no.<w>276</w>,p.<p>34</p></ref>), the jingming jing jiieguanzhong shu淨名經集解關中疏(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>85</v>,no.<w>2777</w>,p.<p>487</p><c>b</c></ref>) and the jfinming jing guanzhong shichao淨名經關中釋抄(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>85</v>,no.<w>2778</w>,p.<p>532</p><c>b</c></ref>. (2)cf. tvkirtira,204,p.99,and tl4,no.475,p.5 10. 13)cf. t〓tra,2004,p.354, and tl4,no.475,p.5 4)cf. tl2,no.385.This sutra is presently investigated by prof. Mark bM(publica-tion forthcoming) 5)cf. the chinese ekottarika-agama ,no.12although gautama samghadeva is  the vimalakirtinirdes's narrationon the amrta distribution and its exploitation by the pusa chutai jing's authors (e. legittimo, mentioned as the translator, the greatest part of the collection (or the whole) as we know it today is (still) Zhu fonian's. terminological comparative inquiries showed that the chinese ekottarika-agama contains a great number of formulas and expressions exclu-sivcly found in works translated by Zhu Fonian. i plan to further investigate this topic in a study dedicated to the chinese ekottarika-agama. on this topic cf. also mzunC Kogen, 1956,p.4190. 16)cf. tl2,no.385,p.10- (7)cf. Tl2,no.384,p.103 18)cf. T2, no.125,p.772b (Key words&gt;初期大乗,竺佛念,菩薩處胎経,vimalakirtinirdesa, asta-vimoksa post-doctoral researcher at the lnternational collage for postgraduate studies ) compiled by m. yaMaakl and y. ouSaka InDXTo MAjjHianikay 本文473頁・定価35.50ポンド pali Text society 〓006年  
</root>
