<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
discerning the original language of the tibetan versions of Mahayana Sutras From a simple Mistake in the ldem kar ma regarding the djatasatrukaukrpyavinodhanasutra MIyakI Tensho 1introduction a excellent historiographer may sometimes make a mistake. once the error is compiled in an influential catalogue, it can long be accepted as historical fact, in-deed until it is noticed and corrected. The account of the aiotasatrukaukrtyavinodh-anasutra kv given under the caption of "Mahayana sutras translated from Chinese" in the ldem kar 〓, one of the oldest and the most authoritative Tibetan catalogues of buddhist canonical scriptures, is most likely to be one suc 〓ase. what strikes us first about the understanding of the origin of the tibetan ver- 〓on of the akvis the discrepancy found between the dk and the 'pang thn m (〓)the two are almost contemporary ( around the first half of the 9th century), but unlike the dk, the p classifies the sutra among "sutras translated frorr Indian.")since there seems no doubt that both catalogues refer to the same extant 〓kv, composed of five fascicles, the truth will lie either in the account of the dkor in that of the p.to examine which account is more credible, this paper will dis-cuss the subject from the following three viewpoints: first, what the colophon sug-gests, second, what chinese materials suggest, and third, the use of relatives in Tibetan translations. 〓What the colophon suggests The colophon of the akvmentions two scholars as those engaged in the translation of the sutra: Maniusrigarbha,an indian monk, and Ratnaraksita, a tibetan monk re-ferred to in the sgra sbyor bsm po gnyis pa.4) neither scholar leaves any sign of having translated material from chinese scriptures. given that specialists well versed in chinese buddhist scriptures were obviously needed in the projects involv-ing translation of sutras from chinese, the extant Tibetan version is therefore clearly  discerning the original language of the tibetan versions of Mahayana sutra (T. miyak) not taken froma chinese original. 3What chinese Materials suqqest since each of the extant three chinese versions of the djkv, i.e. the asheshi wang iing阿闇世王經(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>626</w></ref>),the wenshuzhili puchao sammei iing文殊師利普超三昧經 〓627),and the weicengy zhengfa jing未曾有正法經(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>628</w></ref>),shows no literal agree-ment with the extant tibetan version, we are left with the possibility that either the dk is erroneous or, if the record is in fact correct, that the text mentioned in the dk could represent a missing chinese version of the sutra. the kaiyucn shiiao lu開元 釋教録(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>2154</w>,<p>70</p><c>e</c></ref>),in fact, argues that "the akvhas three extant versions and three missing versions."5with whatever little certainty we attach to this source, it cannot be completely denied that the sutra referred to by the dk may have been imong these three missing versions. in addition, there is another possibility that a specific text translated into local, vernacular chinese, thereby escaping the attention of the compiler of the chinese catalogue,6) might have been made use of by tibetan scholars and listed in the dk. However, how should we examine such a possibility that "an extant text" could have been translated from "a missing text?" the examination of the description in the dkconducted thus far has involved no more than circumstantial observations, and we will remain in a fog unless we change viewpoints. we will now move on to the third, and final, perspective that points to "the style of translation" as direct evi-dence of the original form of the suitra. 4 The use of Relatives inTibetan translations one of the most effective indices with regard to "style" to distinguish Sanskrit frorr Chinese is the use of relatives, sanskrit has highly developed relative structures that are completely lacking in chinese. tibetan translators, while originally unfamiliar with the use of relatives but later introducing them through the process of transla-tion from Sanskrit, felt the right to adopt a different style of translation in terms of a relative structure in accordance with the stylistic differences of the original texts. The use of relatives can effectively function as the method for discerning the origi-nal of tibetan translations.7)however, given the complete lack of philological stud-ies on this theme, a couple of examples will be shown by quoting from the Mahayana sutras before proceeding to examine the case of the djkv  discerning the original language of the tibetan versions of Mahayana sutra t. Myazak) (1)the purnapariprccha and the sunarnaprabhasa two mahayana sutras are regarded as having been translated from chinese: the 〓purnapariprcch ,prp8)and one of the suvarnaprabhasas ,suyh t In these sutras, while a certain kind of relatives proved to have originated fron chinese does appear, another attested to in Sanskrit never does. (a) the expression "gang 〓i de ('i ni," corresponding to the expressions "ming yi"名為,"ii shi"即是,etc., as shown below, is an example for the case in which style that had originally been devised for the purpose of translating from indian originals was applied at a later time to translation from chinese tinged with the nu-ance of " paraphrase" or "emphasis." ・de lta bui dmigs pa med pa'i byams pa gang 〓ina de ni chos kyi byams pzhes byd'o 〓de lia bui chos kyi byams p gang 〓i de mi sangs rgys kyi byams pzhes by'o 如是無所得慈名爲法慈。如是法慈名爲佛慈。10) ●yang dg p'i ngo bo nyid gang 〓i de mi de bzhin nyid y de bzhin nyid kyi ngo bo nyid gang 〓i de mi de bzhin gshegs pi yongs mya ns'szhes by'o 實性體者即是眞如,眞如性者即是如來,名爲涅槃。11) (b)the purp and the suvch tb include a relative clause of place, "ga la ba der," cor-responding to " yenena" in Sanskrit. Here i present an example from each text ●de has bras ze zhig tu spul te /rgyal po deglaba der on ncs 時即化作婆羅門,往詣王所12) ede dag gzhon mu tham phyi dro'i dus na bcomds gang na ba der lhags te/ 如是等人(…)各於哺時往詣佛所頂禮佛足,13) (c) the verses of Suvchthb include relative pronouns, which are used to meet the re-striction of svllables in verses /sems can gang dg skyabs dang dbung gnyen med mgon med sdug bsdal song bar gyur ba d  'ongs skal ba ku de dmod dang skyabs dang dpud gnyen gyur par shog/ 若有衆無救護長夜輪迴受衆苦我於來世作歸依令彼常得安隱樂14) (d)in stark contrast to the use of relatives in the examples mentionedin ,(b) and (c),many kinds of relatives do not appear in the suvch tib and the pp.as one of these examples, we enumerate here "relative clause of time", e.g. "gang gyi tshe -  discerning the original language of the tibetan versions of Mahayana sutra (t. miyazaki) tei ishe" or "mzi tshe," common phrases corresponding to " y- 〓da" in translations from sanskrit originals. probably for the reason that this struc-ture, when translated, is difficult to retaini chinese, the lack of its appearance can be used as an index that suggests the original should be chinese. an ideal example for this case can be drawn from the suv, which has two tibetan translations, one 「rom chinese and another from Sanskrit, as shown below. Skt yada samudriko navah sayantrah spatakikuh/ sthalam aruhya gaccheyus tada dhatur bhavisyati / Skt&gt; ib m zhig rgya mtshoil gru bo che / 'khru 'khor dang ni gyor mor bcas  /thang la byung ste 'gro bae'i tshe ring bsrel yod par gyur <ref><canon>T</canon><w>655</w></ref>假令大船舶盛滿諸財實能令陸地行方求佛舍利 Cib te gru chen thams cadnor dang rin chen rb bkang ste / /thang bu skaml 'gro nus n bcom ln ring bsrel bisal bar b (2)aikv In the extant Tibetan translation of the ajkv, there are many kinds of relative struc-tures, one of which is "the relative clause of time" as mentioned in. it will suf-fice to quote here an example from Sanskrit fragments fortunately preserved in the Schoyen collections.16 Skt yada ca maitreyena bodhisatvena bodhih prapta bhavisyati tatra esa punar eva tatas sahayamlokadhatau upapadyisyati akhyatovi ( Tib gang gi tshe na byang chub sems pa sems dpa' cheno byams pa byang chub mngo par rdgs par 'ishang rgya 'gyur bar 'gyur pa def tshe yang(byang chub sems pc sems pa chen po migyo b zhes bya bar gyurro 5Conclusions The conclusions reached above were that, first, the colophon suggests that the trans lators of the extant akv had no involvement in the projects translating from Chinese texts, second, the existing chinese akvshows no literal agreement witl the tibetan versions, and third, the distinctive condition of Chinese originals lack-ing the clause of time is not satisfied by the extant akv. Thus, the classification employed by the pt that must be correct and it is highly likely that the compiler of the dk made a simple mistake in recording the name of the sutra.  discerning the original language of the tibetan versions of Mahayana sutra (T. MIyaak) 1)dk:m. lalou [5"les textes bouddhiques au temps du roi khri-sroi-lde-bcan' journal asiatique〓,pp.3-353,S. yoshimura ["the denka-,ldes, catalogue of the tibet buddhist canons." aklalou[53]no.257, yoshimura [195 do.256.2)pte. kawagoe [200],dkar chang 'phang than ma.3)kawagoc [20051 〓o.744)M. ishikawa[1ritical editio of the Sgra sbyor 〓am po gnyis pa. studia tibetica〓8,p.l.5)三存三欠(t2154629b)6)d. ueyama[1"a study or the life and works of fa-ch'cng (hgo chos grub),a translator of buddhist tcxts at tun-hunang under the tibetan rule. part i"in japanesc),journal of oriental studies#39. pp.119-222.7)s. harada [18"toban yakkyo shi"吐蕃訳経史Tonko kogo kenkyu and ueyama  etc.8)purp is not listcd under thc translated texts from chinesc in any catalogue, but it is rcgardcd as the retranslated tcxt froma baoii jing fulouna hui大 宝積經富樓那會(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>310</w>(<v>17</v>)</ref>)as the previous studies indicates (e.g. b. sakurabe ["sei zoyaku daihoshakukyo no kenkyu"西蔵訳大宝積経の研究and ueyama[1],etc.).9 suvch tb was translated from jin guangming zuisheng wang jing金光明最勝王經(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>665</w></ref>) bya cheng法成thc othcr two tibctan versions of uy and d557)were translat-ed from indian, and the sanskrit vcrsion of vsk) survives. suyskt. nobel, j [1937]u-varnaprabhasottamasutra.d1717)43l5-16. other cxamplesd1 〓〓17)440l117)44b2,etc. the cxamples of gang yi p'di ni d1717)438-91717)414, etc.11)d55 〓4other cxamplcs d38555 〓a1904,etc.12)d17)4-27 another example: d17717)413)d55〓5 other cxamples. d〓49-10,ctc.14)d74 other examples: d4,, etc.15)sl4 vsk p.174128b6.6)aikyski: harrison and hart-man"ajatasatrukaukrtyavinodhanasutra," manuscripts in the schoyecollection 〓 buddhist manuscripts, vol.i &amp; harrison and Hartman"anothcr fragment of the aiatasatrukaukrtyavinodhanasutra," manuscripts in the schoyencollectiobuddhist namuscripts,vol17)ask no.3-4anothcr examplc: 〓kvsk no.4 &lt;kcy word&gt; jatasatrukaukrtyavinodhanasmtra, idem kar ma, 'pang than ma, thc usc of relativcsinTibetan translations (Graduate student, tokyo university )  
</root>
