<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
journal of indicn d buddhist studies vol.55,no.3, march7(一) 〓 raksases in vedic ritual1 TS6.2.123.9.2 IZawaatsuko 1.Invedic ritual, raksases attack the sacrifices, and are finally expelled by the sacrificers of priests.2) though we often come across such a scene, especially in the Black Yaiur veda samhitas, it is not clear what the raksases really are. Therefore, i have extracted the words identified with raksases in order to determine their sub-jtance. these words are categorised into the following four groups. 〓1abstract nouns (a) amati (thoughtlessness) [pl.] and arati (hostility) [l.]tS5.15. (b) amati (thoughtlessness) and durmati (malice) TS..2 (c) arati (hostility)[pl.]tS 1.62.1,;3.1.,vS17ab, sb 1.1.2.2[sg.] kS17,,MS1..),1 (d)dvesas (hatred) [pl.]t63ee4 (e) nastr (destruction) [pl.]s2,3..1;38see 3-2,3;〓3 7.3.2.73.2.11-34.1.15 (f)papmn (evil) S.17.73.2.11 [2]hostile beings (a) bhratrvya (enemy) kS3kap37(181)see3-1,kS2. (11se3-2,kS210(1181,(1271),(12710) (b)yo aratyati (who has hostile intentions) kS2s3-1, ks212(17.2-3) 〓see 3-2MS1116)3see 3-2 (c)yo sm dvesti yac vayam dvismd (who hates us and whom we hate) TS6..2.32 [〓] compounds with asura They are found in the brahmanas.4) 4]praheti (weapon) vs11kS17.(2k(1105),MS〓8. (114.15)TS1  The raksases as praheti do not belong to enemies, but are regarded as the weap-ons against the enemlies. Among these[l] and[2]should be noted.[](a)(b) and (c) are negative emotions. and (e) and (f) are found in satapatha brahmana (Sb).so far it seems the raksases are connected with emotions such as aratis (hostility-not favourable) and amatis (thoughtlessness) in the black Yajur veda Samhitas. however, the connection be- 【ween these words and the raksases is not strong enough, because these words are mentioned only in the mantras and regarded as raksases in the brahmana portions. and it is not clear whether the negative emotions are directed toward the sacrifices, devas or sacrificers (priests ). regarding this point,[2」(c)is more concrete in that yo sman duesti yamc vayam dvismd' is connected with the raksases. therefore, in this paper i wish to examine ①taittiriya Samhita (ts) 61.8.3-4,②6.2.10.1-2; ③6.3.9.2-3.first, the relationship between these three and the original mantras 1)ts125.lde5),〓.1bc6),3139ik7)dealt with should be clarified. second, these three will be compared with the corresponding sentences in the other Yaiur veda texts. last, i will examine the other sentences that contain the mantra po sman dvesti yacvayam dvisma. 2.the relationship between ①ts6.1.8.3-4,②6.2.10.-2,③6.3.9.2-3 and the original mantras is as follows. (lmts12..lde, (〓.3.1.lbc idm aham raksaso griva api krntami  sm dest yamc vayomdvisma idamaya griva dpi krntami Thus i cut the neck of the raksas. Thus I cut the neck of him who hates us and whom we hate. 〓〓』 ①tS 6.8.4,②6.2.10.2idm ahm raksaso griva api krntami yo 'sn duesti y c vayam dvisma ity aha dvau viva pirusau yam caivo dvesti yas cainam dvesti tayor evanan-tarayam grivah krntati Thus I cut the neck of the raksas, who hates us and whom we hate 8)', he says. there are twc persons. one whom he hates and one who hates him, verily successively he cuts their necks. (〓ts1.9.2ik iidm aham rakso dhamam tamo nayamiy sm dvesti yc vaym dvismd idm enam adhamdm tmo nayom iThis raksas here i lead to the lowest darkness. khim who hateth us and whom we hate, hcrs 〓im lead to the lowest darkness  〓Ts6.9.2-3idm ahm rakso 'dhamam tamo nayami yo 'sman dvesti yamc vayo dvismd ity aha dvau vava purusau y caivcdvesti ys cainam dvesti tdv ubhava-hamdm tdmo nayati  This rdksas here i lead to the lowest darkness, who hateth us and whom we hate, he says, there are two (kinds of) persons, he whom he 〓2」hates and he who hates him, both these h4 leads to the lowest darkness. In these brahmana portions, it seems the original two mantras are made one, and the raksas is identified with y sm dvesti ymc vay dvismd, which is inter preted as two persons. in order to detemine whether or not such interpretation is common, i will next examine the following corresponding sentences in the other Yaiur veda texts. ①kathaka Samhita (kS)〓kapisthala katha samhita (kaps)37.5 (198.8-21)9 ②kS29(114224.1-13),②Maitrayani samhita (ms)38.8 (10.17-14),②sB1.4 ③sB3.2.14-1510) ).The relationship between the corresponding sentences and the original man-tras is as follows. lmkS2(14-6),(2m2.12(17.2-3)idm aham raksaso griva apikrntamidam ahmyo ns smano yo samano ratpyati tsy griva apikrntami Thus i cut the neck of the raksas. thus i cut the neck of him who, equal to us or not cqual, has hostile intentions. 〓』〓 dkS(937.198.10-12),②ks21(1.14(224.12-13 idam aham raksso griva apikyntamiti bhraty vyo vai rakso bhratrvyasyaiva griva apikrntati Thus ! cut the neck of the raksas , he says. for the raksas is the enemy. it is the neck of the enemy that he cuts. (2m)mS1.2(19.15-16)idm aham raksaso griva apikrntamidcm ahom yo me samano y samano 'ratiyoti tasya grivd apikrntami Thus I cut the neck of the raksas. Thus I cut the neck of him who, equal to me or not equal, has hostile intentions. 〓』〓 ②MS38.8(6.1-4)idam aham raksaso griva dpikrntamity aha raksasam dhvarayai rak-usam antaritya idm aham yo mell) samano yo samano ratipati tasya griva apikrmtamiti s mano va hy asamano varatiyati sarvam evaitaya paryapat Thus l cut the neck of the raksas,' he says, for the falling of the raksases, for the blocking  the raksases. "Thus i cut the neck of him who, cqual to me or not equal, has hostile inter lions, he says. for he, equal or not equal, has hostile intentions: it is by this that he reachec a11. (2m) vajasaneyi samhita (vs)5.26idam aham raksasam griva apikrntam 〓』』 Hercwithlcut off the neck of the rdksases 〓sB.1.idm aham raksasam grivd dpikrntamiti vajro va 'bhrir vajrenaivaitan nastra nm raksas griva dpikrntatil〓 'herewith icut off the neck of the raksases !' for the spade is the thunderbolt. it is with the thunderbolt that he cuts off the neck of the rdksases 〓m)vs6.16.idm ahm rakso 'bhitisthamidm ahmn rakso vabadha idm aham rakso dhamdm tamo hayami herewithi tread down the yaksas! herewith i drivc away the raksas! hcrewithiconsign the raksas to the nethermost darkness 〓〓』 ③Sb38.2.15idm aham rakso 'bhitisthamidam aham rakso vabadha idm aham rakso dhamam tamo nayamiti tad yajnenaivaitcn hastra raksasy avabadhate 'hercwith i tread down the rakscs! herewithi drivc away the rcksas ! herewith iconsign the raksas to the netheriost darkness!' Thus it is by means of the sacrificc that he drivcs awa. he destructions),the raksases. In the corresponding sentences there is no y sman dvesti ym c vaym dvisma.' note that kS and kaps identify the raksas with the enemy. as for the mantra of kS and MS, idm aham raksso griva apikrntami' is followed by idam ahom yo ns  me) samano yo samano 'ratiyati tasya griva apikrntami, and MS 〓.8.8explains these two individually. From this it is found that only ts connects the mantra y 'sma dvesti yc vayamdvism' with the raksas. 4.in the other sentences that contain the mantra yo 'sman dvesti yvayam dvismas. or y dvismo yais ca no dvesti..' there are few cases in which the one who hates us and whom we hate is identified with the enemy tS3.3.1,mS4. (13.4))or the competitor (mS11(79.1-80.4)). araru (the name of the asurarakss-see s17)appears in <ref><canon>T</canon><w>1191</w></ref>-,MS 1.1.10(.3-8) and sb-17. however, there is no identification, but just the fact that the location of the mention of araru in TS is nearer to the mantra than in mS and sb.  although TS63.2.2does not contain the mantra, the way of identifying the dve. samsi with the raksamsi appears similar to that of TS 6.4-3..2-3. The relationship between TS63.2.and the original mantra is as follows: TS1veda (rv)8.79.3 tvm soma tanukydbhyo4)dvesobhyo 'nydkrtebhya uru yantaisi varntham sviha.. Thou, o soma, art the giver of wide protection from hostility, brought about by ourselves or by others, hail ! 〓〓』 TS6.3.2.2 tvm soma tanukydbhya ity aha tanukyd dhy e dvesobhyo 'nyakrtebhya ity ahanyakrtani hi raksamsi "Thou, o soma, brought about by ourselves,' he says, for he is the one who brings about by himself, from hostility, brought about by others, he says, for the rdksases are brought abou1 by others. The corresponding sentences are kS26.2,kaps4,mS39.1and SB3.2- 21,among which only mS and Sb mention the above mantra. in MS3.9.1(128-9) itanukrdbhyo dvesobhyo 'nydkrtebhya' is interpreted as yad eva tanukrtam canyaky-tm cinas td etenapayaiati' (it is the evil which is made by ourselvcs or by others that he wards off), in TS63.2.2'tanukydbhyo dvesobhyo 'nyakrtebhya' is divided into two and 'tanukydbhyo' is connected with the soma and dvestobhyo 'nyakrtebhya' is identified with the rakscses. 5.conclusion InTS 6.1.3-4,10-2,63.9.2-3,the original two mantras are regarded as if one mantra, and the raksas is identified with y 'sma dvesti ym c vaym dvismd.' such interpretation is not found in the other texts. Moreover TS6.3.2.divides the original one mantra into two, and identifies ha-tred with the raksses. Hence one can say that in the black Yajur veda samhitas, where the raksases are just vaguely connected with the negative emotions, Ts is in a unique position in the respect that it tries to identify the raksases with hatred or persons who hate the sac-rificer or whom he hates. 1)due to limitations of space, i had to cut the utillised texts and their english transla-lions, which will be shown as a part of the extended paper at the first opportunity.  2)tS51.4,7,kS1(3.15),2(2316-17)and so on. 3)In sb, nastrd and rdksamsi are always found as a set, but in the case of kS70 11)and37.19),nastra is mentioned only along with the raksas. 4)In the sb, about one third of the passages containing aisura- or a compound or de. rivative of this word in fact have the compound asuraraksas-. cf. hale, w. e.[1986 asura-ary vedic religion, delhi, p.177 )a circle is drawn round the seventh footprint of the soma cow and mantra d is re-peated, followed by e 6)a line is drawn round with mantras b and c, before the erection of the sads. )these mantras accompany his throwing away the cut part of the grass blade which he has dipped in the blood of the cut of the omentum 8)english translations of ts given in this paper are those in keith, a. b. [16]the veda of the blck yaius school entitled taittiriya sanhita, pari ladharvard oriental series l and 1),delhi. keith, however, translated this sentence to "thus I cut the neck of the raks,who hateth us and whom we hate.' cf. part 2,p.49 9)the corresponding sentences of MS and sbS37.(83.11 sB.11-11) do not have the mantra yo 'sma dvesti ymc vayam dvisma.' 0)There is no corresponding sentence in kS. The corresponding sentences of mS(MS 3.10.2) do not have the mantra. 11)Mittwede, M[1tertkritische bemerkungezu maitrayani samhita, stuttgart, p.134. Schroeder: some 12)english translations of Sb given in this paper are those in Eggeling [18]the sata-patha-brahmana, part ii (The sacred books of the east 〓6),delhi. eggeling, however translated this word to 'the evil spirits.' cf. p.194. 13)mantra a is recited by the adhvaryu to accompany the making of libations in the salamukhiya fire. 14)icannot tell what tanukrdbhyo mcans, so i take keith's translation herc for thc pre-ent. however, among shcolars there are diverse tanslations and opinions:eggeling life-injuring or body making, from the enemies that assume (various) forms', geldncr (deinen) leiblichen erzeugern', Mayrhofer (a ia) 'selbstbereitet', oldenberg 'den (Frommen), die tatig sind sich die eigne tanz schaffen', Scarlata "fur die, die deineny leibich) zubereiten'. cf. Eggeling [1988],p.157,n.2. geldner, k. f.[1951],der rig-yeda, zweitel teil, leipzig, p.406. keith, part l, p.39,n.12;, part267],p.515, n.b. oldenberg, h. [1912]rgveda. textkritische und exegetische noten, siebentes bis rehntes buch, bcrlin, pp.1. scarlata, S.[199die wurzelkompositaimveda. wicsbaden, p.73. (key words) raksas, dvesas, bhraitrvya, araru Library staff, international college for postgraduate buddhist studies.  
</root>
