<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
Robes of Rags (funzoe) and silk in the edo period: Menzzuiho and ueda Shohen interpret the practice of the buddhist Robe diane RIGGS 〓. Introduction: during the edo period, interestin reviving the precepts spread throughout the maioi sects of buddhism. Those monks with strong commitment to the movement would pledge themselves in private ceremonies (iiseijikai自誓持戒)to uphold the full twc hundred and fifty buddhist precepts (gusoku kai具足戒).based on the interpreta-tion of the precepts of the shibunritsu四分律)promoted by the chinese vinaye Master, daoxuan jpn: dosen道宣596-667),they also practiced wearing linen and cotton robes exclusively, avoiding silk robes, the normal garb for the time. they chose muted colors and soon came to be recognized by the dull color and wrinkled appearance of their robes, even causing them to be accepted as a separate interest group by the edo bakufu (nishimura Ryo03).such robes also fit in with a long-standing practice in Japanese buddhism of associating black or dull colored robes with recluses and ascetics (osumi1965. These reformers presented themselves as returning to a more pure buddhist prac-tice, but in indian buddhist literature, it is the rag robe (funzoe糞掃衣Skt: pamsukula) that is traditionally associated with ascetic practice. ideally this includes picking up discarded cloth, washing and dyeing the pieces to a uniform color and sewing them into robes. the ten types of cloth suitable for rag robes are defined in the Shibunritsu by the use to which the cloth was put before it was cast away. these ten types of cloth have been: 1.chewed by cows, 2.chewed by rodents, 3. burnt, 4. used for menstruation, 5. used in childbirth ,6. carried away from the shrine by birds, animals or the wind, 7. taken from a graveyard, 8.used for petitionary rites to the gods, 9. discarded when receiving employ-  ment from thc king, 10. used to wrap a corpsc (<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>.〓<w>142</w>,<p>0</p><c>a</c></ref>). although eo period buddhists knew about the rag robe, the practice was not as widespread as the use of linen and cotton robes. why did edo monks in the pre-cepts movement emphasize rejecting silk instead of moving to adopt the practice of he rag robe? in this paper i examine how two authors during this period described these two types of religious practice. 〓i. the practice of the Rag robe as described by menzZuiho The teachings of the buddha's dharma robe『釈氏法衣訓』,written in8 the soto zen scholar-monk, Menzazuiho(面山瑞方1683-176) uses a wide selec-tion of citations to advocate the living practice of wearing the robe. Menzan ex-plains that he was motivated to write the piece because contemporary forms and practices were concerned only with the robe as decoration of the body and hence violated what he considered to be the first principle of the buddhist robe. to achieve the solemnity of the dharma body. menzn relies on two essays, kes kudoku(袈裟 功徳)and dene(伝衣),written in4by dogen1253),founder of the soto zen school. in these essays dogen praised the rag robe as most worthy of reverence. whereas the writings of his contemporaries typically mention the rag robe only briefly, Menzan cites fifteen different sources, including four citations from the shibunritsv, jujuritsu and uburitsu vinaya and commentaries, three from chinese treatises, and five from scriptures. Menzan clearly saw the rag robe as key to under-standing the meaning of the buddha's robe. In discussing the practice of the rag robe, Menzan cites the maharatnakuta (jpn daiho shakukyo大宝積経)three times. in the first instance, he merely comments briefly that the contemplations on the merit of the buddha's relics described in this scripture apply equally to the rag robe. he also cites the six contemplations of pick-ing up rags for making robes which occur in three stages of development. First, the two contemplations of the knowledge of what is necessary for nurturing the good give rise, second, to the two contemplations of lack of pride and a determination to accumulate good qualities. Third, this mental state in turn promotes thoughts of not adorning the body and commanding a pure heart. Menzan emphasizes that the rag robe by its nature leads one towards the buddha's teaching, and that is the source of  Robes of Rags (funzoe) and silk in the Edo period (. riggs)(135) ts merit. his final citation describes the rag robe practice of an ideal postulant (sha-mi沙彌Skt: sramanera): buddha said to Mahakasyapa, look at postulant Shuna (Skt: cunda) who picked up some thing from the midst of impure smelly and filthy rags, ate little, and when finished eating went to the great pool of anoku. he was about to wash them when thc heavenly bcings who lived around the edgc of the pond camc from far away to greet him. they bowcd thcir heads down to himin reverence and a1 rejoiced in purity. they took the impur rags (funzo) which shuna had picked up and washed them so that the impurity entirely disappearcd. They then took the washing watcr to wash their own bodies.a11 the hcavenly beings knew that shuna could maintain the pure precepts and entcr every concentratior of meditation and had grcat virtue, so for this feason they caine out to wclcome hit as noblc person and paid obeisance to him.11〓34711. By citing the muharatnakuta frequently in this section ezan emphasizes the con. nection between the rag robe and Mahakasyapa, a figure strongly associated with the ascetic practices, including the rag robe.i buddhism, Mahakasyapa is be-lieved to have directly received the transmission of the teaching from Sakyamuni and to have been entrusted with a robe for the future buddha, Maitreya (silk,2003) Menzan suggests how the practice of the rag robe could be incorporated into a life of contemplation and worship practices and that it is the proper attire for the simple asceticism portrayed by the postulant Shuna. but menzan is not simply citing scrip-tural passages as a ideal of the past.a patchwork robe stored at eifuku-an in obama, Fukui-ken believed to have been made and worn by menzan suggests that he recreated the physical practice of the rag robe as well. This worn and much atched garment is clearly not simply a demonstration project, but rather has seer years of use. 〓. The practice of the non-silk robe as described by ueda Shohen According to the vinaya, materials for the funzoe are discarded cloth and therefore indirectly received from the laity, but vinaya literature also establishes rules of di-rect donation from the laity who received merit in return. these "ten kinds of robes" in the shibunritsu refer to the types of fiber used in making the cloth, name-ly: linen(types),silk (2types), wool(2types), cotton, feathers and fabric made from  wood (<ref><canon>T</canon><v>22</v>〓<w>142</w>,<p>02</p>.<c>1</c></ref>)although each of the five vinaya specify that silk is suit-able for robes, daoxuan argued that since silk production involves killing silk worms, accepting it hinders the practice of compassion. although not a violation of these rules, daoxuan fuled that silk was inappropriate for mahayana monks. The prohibition referred only to cloth directly donated from the laity, not to rag robes. a rejection of silk would therefore have an impact on the relationship between the monks and the laity. The arguments for and against the use of silk in robes came under intense scrutiny by edo period scholar-monks who promoted a return to the vinaya. These argu-ments are reviewed and discussed by a Shingon risshu scholar-monk, ueda Shohen (上田正遍1828-1908)in his treatise on the proper practice of daoxuan's prohibition of silk robes『南山律宗袈裟禁絹順正論』(Shohen 880). Shohen's work is signifi-cant because he discusses the textual evidence for the abstract moral principle of the anti-silk position from the practical viewpoint of one who has incorporated this po-sitionin his own feligious practice. one of the issues raised in the treatise is whether or not one may receive silk for robes second hand. in this case, one is remote from the action of killing as the clotk has already passed through many hands. as the object was not ordered by the monk, but was received already made up into the garment, one cannot say that the monk is guilty of having intended the killing of the silkworms to make the cloth. As Yijing (jpn gijo義淨635-713) comments, "if one discusses killing, first there is the intention of cutting off a life, this is how karmic action is completed. if it is no1 intentional at a11 then it is not a sin. Three conditions must be met: intention, action and the result. if these three aspects are in accord with the mmonastic rules (ie. they are pure),then there is no fault." (<ref><canon>T</canon><v>54</v>.〓<w>2125</w>,<p>212</p></ref>In response to this Shohen ar-gues that if one uses silk, one contributes to the total economy of silk production: Those who deeply value compassion, how can they covet and wear the silk that causes more and more harm to lif? if one wears it then one desires it and this crushes one's compassion and increases one's bad karma. if i wear silk then someone will increasingly harm living beings by making silk. if i do not wcar it then that killing will end. That sin  and merit starts with me. (Shohen5.2) Shohen argues that one must see one's own responsibility for the entire sequence of actions involved in making the cloth. even if the silk is secondhand, using it en. courages silk production as a whole. Shohen emphasizes this idea of a global re-ponsibility at the end of the treatise where he cites the shiiki「四分律行事鈔資持 記」,a commentary o daoxuan's work by yuanzhao (jpn ganjo元照1048-1116.in the passage he suggests that the mental world of the bodhisattva is substantially dif-ferent because he is able to imagine the whole chain of relationships that lie behind the presence of the obiect: " bodhisattva imagines that which comes from afar. Even if one is removed from the act of killing, one is not without the action of kill-ing. stepping with the foot or wearing things on the body, one is saturated with kar. ma." (Shohen2) As these examples show, one aspect of this practice is contemplative. instead of tracking one's own mental, physical and verbal actions to ensure that they are in . cord with the monastic rules, one enters a contemplation of a11 possible connections beyond the perameter of one's own intentions and actions. This practice of avoiding silk robes, however, raises other ethical problems. how does the monk who avoid using silk deal with a donor who comes bearing a gift made of silk Shohen explains various solutions to this problem. Yiiing, who accepted the use of silk explained, "if a donor brings an offering with a pure mind then recite a bene-diction, and accept it, saying, "(this gift) sustains me and nurtures your virtue. Truly this is no error." (〓41,212)but Shohen feels that Yiling's solution is insuffi. clent. if there is a donor who brings (silk), then you must explain it to him right away so that he realizes the import of the teaching. if you do so, then he must exchange it for cloth such as  otton and donate it. or, one can enquire about thc donor's intcntion, receive it and usci for garments other than robes (kesa), then it is not a violation (Shohen6.). That is, the monk guards the purity of his practice by teaching the laity to bring a  more appropriate donation. shohen cites another solution that daoxuan proposed "Reading the vinaya, I saw that if one receives a mat (gagu) already made of silk, one should shred it and, mixing it up with hard soil, daub it (on the wall). by this means i doubled my reverence for the rules of the vinaya <ref><canon>T</canon><v>4</v>〓88,<p>879</p>.<c>38</c>-<l>19</l></ref>) by accepting the silk but later destroying it, the monk follows the rule for accepting donations, but satisfies daoxuan's rule by destroying the inappropriate gift. Iv. conclusion: Both Menzan and Shohen describe these two types of robes in terms of contempla tions. For Menzan, the rag robe promotes a contemplation of frugality and the meaning of the impure becoming pure through ascetic practice. For Shohen, the contemplation considers the chain of relationships that lead back to the act of killing silk worms, and is ruthless in excising the impurity of even a strand of silk. one senses in both authors a longing for a past era in which the robe was properly re-spected and understood, and a dedication to the idea of the robe as a sacred gar-ment. while both are grappling with the dissonance between their ideal and the re-ality of contemporary edo period buddhist practices, they are equally determined to manifest this ideal in their daily practice. their ideas are shaped by reading texts, however, rather than by traditionally transmitted teachings. in this sense, they are both involved in the reconstruction of the physical robe and its religious practices through texts. bibliography Mcnzzuiho.178. "Shakushi hoe kun."idai vihon bukkyo zensho, v.73,0721 Nishimura Ryo.23."kaiko no koe. kinsei ritsuzo ni okeru kene kinshi ni tsuite ." i mihon bukkyo sogo kenky osumi kazuo.19"tonsei ni tsuitc."lhokkaido daigaku bungaku bu kiyo. ueda Shohen.188"nanzan risshu kesa kinken unsho ron." i*dai Nihon bukkyo zensho*,v.74,3-310. (The research for this paper was supported by the numata fellowship administrated by Ryukoku university) &lt;key words) kasaya, pamsukula,禁絹,上田照遍,面山端方 (visiting researcher, Ryukoku university)  
</root>
