<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
〓n the Seventh abode in kukai's 〓ebodes of ind of the ysterious mandala Sania juRkovic "the mind realizing non-origination of the mind"(覚心不生住心)is the name of the seventh abode in kukai's model of the ten abodes of mind, which is related to the teachings of the chinese Sanlun(三論)tradition. The name of this abode is based on the concept appearing in the first chapter of the hahovairocanasutra, in the passage which describes the yogic practice of the second kalpa.li relation to putixi lureatise on bodhicitta,菩提心論),which is the other primary source for the establishment of the model of ten stages,2) the seventh stage in the kukai's model corresponds to that aspect of Mahayana practice which emphasizes the realization of emptiness of a11 phenomena(一切法空).3)beginning with the seventh stage, kukai directs the attention of the practitioner towards the mind itself, initiating the process of the realization of non-origination of the mind(心不生).stages seven and eight re-veal the process of the realization of emptiness until its complete transcendence at the ninth stage. 1. Kukai presents the teaching of the sanlun tradition, almost exclusively on the ba sis of jizang's(吉蔵)writings on the topic of the two truths(二諦)and the eightfold legation(八不),in 〓u xun yi (the profound meaning of the three treatises,(三論玄 義)and d cheng xuthe profound meaning of Mahayana,(大乗玄論).the purpos of the eightfold negation at the seventh abode is to cut off a11 "mental manifoldness" (prapanca,戯論)and bring the practitioner to a tranquil state of mind, wherein he re-alizes the non-origination of the mind. however, it seems that kukai considers the Sanlun realization of emptiness as remaining o a rather theoretical level. in the text of the eighth stage he states, that "bodhisattvas of the previous eon lthe sixth and the seventh abode] still engage in mental manifoldness."4) Moreover, he regards the eighth abode as the place of mind which is "unconditioned and without charac-  〓n the seventh abode in Kukai's 〓bodes of find of the mysterious mandu (S. juRkovic)(1 teristics," and it " explains nonduality as neither existent nor nonexistent."5)in th ext of the seventh abode, kukai extensively quotes jizang's writings on the incor. rect understanding of the middle way(中道)on the basis of the concept of two truths.6) the theory of the two truths was a subject of many debates among chinese buddhist scholars, especially in the fifth and the sixth century, and was a conve-nient tool to use in order to point out the false understanding of other traditions Sanlun is especially known for the concept of "destroying the false and revealing the correct"(破邪顕正),which was developed by jizang. kukai does not use this conceptin relation to the sanlun teaching in the seventh abode, but he refers to pas-sages in which jizang refutes the wrong understanding of the pi tang, cheng se, and She lun(攝論)traditions, and generally the other teachers (of the liang dynasty) in relation to the two truths. due to the tendency of earlier Sanlun scholars7) to re late the concepts of "emptiness" and "provisionality" with "non-being"(無)and "be-ing"(有)respectively, and to posit them as two ontological realities, tiantai mastel Zhiyi(智〓)emphasized the concept of the three truths(三諦)and the meditation of "three insights in the single thought"(一心三観),in order to provide a more pro found insight into the meaning of the middle way. although kukai fully acknowl-edged the importance of the concept of two truths, he may have had a slightly nega. livistic view towards the practical results of the Sanlun way of practice and meditation, in terms of the realization of the middle way. The tiantai concept of the three truths might have seemed to kukai to be practically more conducive to the re. alization of the true meaning of the middle way. i ni gi (Meanings of the syllable Hum,昨字義),he concisely states that the "three truths interpenetrate perfectly(三諦 圓渉)"8)furthermore, in the text of the eighth abode, he emphasizes the Tiantai method of "calming and contemplation"(止観道)and refers specifically to the medi-tation of "three insights in the single thought," which brings insight into emptiness. lependent origination, and the middle way.9 2. The concept of buddha-nature must have been extremely important for kukai as the whole shingon practice is based on the idea of the original identity of sentient beings and buddha. The depth of insight into the meaning of the original buddha-nature of mind may be one of the criteria for positioning the different teachings at  〓nthe seventh abode in kukai's 〓bodes of ind of the mysterious 〓andula (s. juRkovic. their respective places, when considering the progressive aspect of the ten abodes n expounding the meaning of the sixth abode, related to the Faxiang(法相)teach-ing, kukai emphasized the development of bodhicitta in a relative sense (samrttika. bodhicita,世俗菩提心).In relation to the realization of buddha-nature, in uni gi he criticizes the Faxiang view stating: "to teach that this possesses it, while that does not, is nothing more than a provisional doctrine."10)considering the seventh abode. itis known that jizang wrote a lot on the meaning of buddha-nature.ll) itis conside-red that it was the influence of jizang that later sanlun scholars held the view that "grasses and trees have a buddha-nature."12)however, Kukai did not seem to find ii significant to emphasize insight into buddha-nature at the seventh stage. on the contrary, in vni gi he states that "rejecting existence and establishing non-exis-tence, is diminution and decrease," which "cuts constantly the buddha-nature, a1- though the original buddha is without diminution and without decrease."13)within the tenfold model of abodes, realization of buddha-nature happens at the eightr abode of " the mind of the unconditioned one way"(一道無為心),which is related to the tiantai(天台)tradition. kukai characterizes the eighth abode with the realiza. tion of the principle of original purity(本来清浄理).14)on the basis of the practice of "calming and contemplation," the practitioner of the eighth abode attains suram-gamasamadhi(首楞嚴三味),which is another name for buddha-nature. zhiyi seems to be unsatisified with the Madhyamika approach as being "devoid of functions(無 功用)."15)The state of activity, transcending the state of stagnation in emptiness, is also an important factor for kukai in the establishment of the ninth stage.16) from the same perspective, it can be concluded that kukai considered tiantai insight into mmptiness, as it relates to the realization of buddha-nature, as more profound than the sanlun approach. 3. The esoteric approach to the seventh abode is related to the " samadhi of great emptiness"(大空三味)of bodhisattva Manjusri, who embodies both exoteric and eso-teric aspects of the teaching on emptiness. on the basis of the hahavairocang-sutra, kukai presents his mantra: "he he kumaraka vimuktipathasthita smara smarg pratiinana."17)The meaning of this mantra is calling for the prince who is abiding in the way of liberation to recall the vows taken in his previous existences. The esote-  〓n the seventhabode in kukai's 〓ebodes of ind of the hysterious and (s. juRkovic)(131 ric interpretation of this mantra is condensed in the syllable "ma," which mean emptiness. Manjusrr's esoteric aspect is the "tathdgata of no mental manifoldness" (無戯論如来).in esoteric teaching, he teaches the "wheel of revolving syllables, which is the samadhi of the five letters(五字輪)"ara pc na." 18 4. conclusion The seventh stage has the function of initiating the process of the development of bodhicitta at the ultimate level (paramarthikabodhicitta,勝義菩提心),which is subse-quently deepened at the eighth and ninth stages. compared to the later stages, the Sanlun teaching is still engaged in "mental manifoldness," and the discriminatioi between subiect and obiect is not yet transcended. kukai's preference for the tianta teaching, instead of the sanlun, is due to the tiantai's emphasis on the realization of buddha-nature, which may be interpreted as a positive aspect of emptiness. it may be stated that, in the context of the ten abodes, Kukai ignored the aspect of sanlun teaching related to the development of jizang's theory o buddha-nature. however his intention may not have been to present the sanlun tradition's teaching from its own doctrinal standpoint; kukai emphasized those aspects of Sanlun teaching which are conducive to the progress of a mantra practitioner, based on the 〓ahavairocanasutra and putixi lun. his approach to the sanlun tradition is from the perspective of the Shingon abode, which considers the main historical ahoyang teachings to be different entrances harmaparyaya9to the same teaching, repre sented by the samadhis of four bodhisattvas of the central eight-petalled lotus divi- 〓ion of the garbha mandala. 〓)the original text refers to the mahayana practice only. taisho shinshu dizokyo ab-breviated as <ref><canon>T</canon>)<v>18</v>,p.<p>-14</p></ref>. kukai interpreted this passagc as two stages and relates hem to the sixth and the scventh abodc in his 〓ebodes of ind of the mysterious Mandcla(秘密曼茶羅十住心論)and precious key to the mysterious treasury(秘蔵守 鑰),『定本弘法大師全集』2,3(abbreviated as t.z.),高野山1993. 2)putixi lun is especially important for thc establishment of thc model often progressive stages irecious keyfo the ysterious treasury 3)t.32,p.573b.1-14 4)〓.z3,b.1 5)ibid. )Inu xn yi, jizang refutes the wrong views of non-buddhists, pi tang(毘曇), 〓  〓n the seventh abode in kukai's 〓bodes of hiind of the ysterions handalc (s. juRkovic) 〓 Cheng se(成実)traditions, and the false understanding of Mahayanists. t.45,pp.-14 jizang was particulary vigorouis in refuting views of cheng se scholars. paul l. Swan-son t'ien-t'i philosophy, asan humanities press, 1989,pp.82ff. 7)see whalen w. lai: sinitic understanding of two truths in the liang dynasty (5. 557),philosophy est and west, vol.28,no.3, university press of hawaii,1978 8)〓.,p.63. 9)t.Z.2.7 10)〓.3,p3. this criticism refers to Faxiang's classification of people into fivc groups according to their different, inherent predispositions towards the attainment of enlighten-ment(五性) 11)on jizang's theory of the middle way as a direct cause of buddha-nature(中道仏性) and refutation of other different theories on the direct cause of buddha-nature prescnt at his time, see <ref><canon>T</canon><v>4</v>,pp.<p>35</p><c>b</c>-<p>37</p><c>a</c></ref>. also, see ming-wood liu: the yogacara and madhy-amika interpretation of the buddha-nature concept in chinese buddhism, philosophy 〓ast and west, vol.3,no.2, pp.177ff, 1985; tThe early development of the buddha-na ture doctrine in china, journal of chinese philosophy, vol. 16,1989. 12)平井俊栄:『中国般若思想史研究』春秋社1973,p634. 13)〓.,p.63 14)〓,p.271 15)ng yu-kwan: tien-fai buddhism and early madhyamika, University of Hawai press,1993,pp.58ff 16)see jurkovic sania: on the ninth stage in kukai's ten abodes of the mind of the Mysterious Mandala-relation to the "mind which transcends no self-nature" lournal of indian d buddhist studies, vol.53,no.2, march 17)〓.,p.157. 18)on the meaning of the mantra, see酒井紫郎「文殊菩薩の五字咒法に就いて」『密 教文化』18,1952. 19)生井智紹:「曼茶羅と多様不二の理論」,『曼茶羅の諸相』,法蔵館,2005. 〓 (Kev words)覚心不生心,大空三味,十住心論,三論 (researcher, koyasan university research institute for esoteric buddhist culture)  
</root>
