<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
Continued Study of n Shigao's works The terminology of the mayi jing t732and the fagun jing <ref><canon>T</canon><w>611</w></ref> Hung hung-lung Introduction The following paper discusses two texts in the taisyuozu(大正藏),the 〓ay. jing(罵意經),which was translated by an Shigao(安世高),and the Faguan iing(法 觀經),which was translated by Zhu fahu(法護).the sutras records, which claim their translators to be as aforementioned, both originated from the lidai sanbao ii 歴代三寶紀)1),however, as it is well known, the records of the lidai sanbao ji are unreliable. in addition, according to the shiyi zajing l(失譯雜經録)of the Chusanzang jii(出三藏記集<ref><canon>T</canon><w>2145</w></ref>) the translators of both texts are in fact anony-nous2).therefore, in this paper, i would like to present an analysis of the texts' ter-minology that brings forth substantial evidence to verify the actual authors. the newly found shiermen jing and jie shiermen jing )which are both  Shigao's works, are very useful resources for the analysis and verification presented in the following. Classification of Sutras' content according to the research of the japanese scholar hayashiya tomojiro(林屋友次 郎),it seems that the author of the mayi jing is n shigao.4) yet, prof. tomojiro only mentioned this point, he did not offer substantial evidence to support this assertion However, interestingly i have found several paragraphs within the mayiing that are jtrikingly similar to the content of the fagun jing, a11 containing terminology of the distinct style of an Shigao. The following chart is a classification of the two texts' content. For the sake of convenience in making a comparison, the fagucn jing can be divided into two parts consisting of five paragraphs, and the mayi jing can be divided into three parts con-  continued study of an Shigao's works (h. hung)(123 sisting of seven paragraphs. The symbolrepresents the paragraphs that are almost identical, whereas the ymbol〓represents the paragraphs which have completely different content. 〓yi jing Fagun jing〓ayi jing Part l part I Paragraphl p.a26533b15 paragraphl p.2b28～2a9 Part2 lart2 part Part 2 paragraph2p.21a24b1 paragraph3 p.24～2b paragraph.2b1242a paragraphp.242a2～242 paragraph2p.33b15～533c6 Paragraph745340 paragraph33c15～534b5 Paragraph6p.34b24～534c2 Part 3 Paragraph3 p.53c7～533c15 non-existentparagraph3p.533c7～533c15 Paragraph5p.34b6～534b23 Non-existent Partl The content of paragraphlin the faguan jing is quite different from that of Paragraphin the mayi jing, also, the latter is longer than the former. for this rea-son, we have classified both texts' paragraphas part l, respectively. Part2 within the two texts, we can find the following pairs paragraph have nearly iden-tical content : paragraph of the fagun jing and paragraph 3 of the mayi jing , Paragraph 3 of the faguam jing and Paragraph7 of the mayi jing, paragraph the faguan jing and paragraphof the 〓ayi jing, paragraph 5of the faguan jing and paragraph 6of the mayi jing. thereby, this analysis subdivides these four pairs of paragraphs as being contained in part 2 of both texts, respectively. because of the existence of several differing words in part 2of both texts, we cannot distin-guish which text is the more original. however, we can say that both texts definitel come from the same source.  24)continued study of an Shigao's works (h. hunc Part3 The two paragraphs 3 and 5of the mayi jing, classified here as part 3, do not ex-ist in the faguan jing. Analysis of the terminology inpart 2 we can find at least il kinds of terms or sentences that exist not only in both the Fagun jing and the mayi jing, but also in several other works of an Shigao. those erms or sentences are seldom seen in other authors' (or translators') works. Therefore it is very distinct that the usage of those terms or sentences especially be-longs to an Shigao's style. 1)yinei renzhong意爲人種5).this term also exists in the anban shouyi jing(安般 守意經)6)2)zhongzai種栽this term also exists in the ana shouyi jing7 and the mingdu wushi jiaoi jing(明度五十校計經)8)and the aha kouie shieryinyun jing(阿含口解十二因縁經)9)3)niandai念待10).here, the meaning of nian念is awareness' (vitarka ),and the meaning of dai待is pondering' (vicara)both words are acts of intellectualization, later called jueguan覺觀or xunsi尋伺.this term also exists in the shiermen ji(+門經)12)and jie shiermen jing(解十二門經)13)and we find the term待念,which has the same meaning, appearing in the ann shouyi jing14)and the lie shiermen jingl54)yiyutan mim feichang bai意欲貪念非常敗16). There is a very similar term  dangnian feichang bai貪當念非常敗which ap. pears inan shouyi jing17))dangnian dui姓當念對18).the more complete sentence yi dangian dui suoyou elu〓當念對所有惡露appears in shouyi 〓ng9the similar sentence tanyinyiqi dangguanshen suoyou elu貪淫意起當觀身 所有惡露appears in  jie shiermen jing26)chenhui nia dengxin*恚念等心21), The sentence with the same meaning hian sidengxin shi wei zhi chenhui yao念四等 心是爲止瞋恚藥appears ian shouyi jing2),and the sentence chenhuiyi qi danghu dengxin愼恚意起當護等心appears in jjie shiermen jing7)yuchi mian benyiqiexing feichang愚癡念本一切行非常24).this sentence appears igucn jing, and the similar sentence yuchi nian benxing buchang愚癡念本行不常appears in the mayi iigThe sentence with the same meaning zii benheyinyuanyou shi wei zhi yuchi yao自計本何因縁有是爲止愚癡藥appears in the an shouyi jing2, and yuchiyi qi dangnian benmo愚癡意起當念本末appears in the jie shiermen  jing27)8)dun shen shishi斷身十事28).The same term also appears in the ahar kouie shieryinyuan jing29)zuo shishi cheng wuyin作十事成五陰30).the simi-lar term shi shishi hewei wuyin是十事合爲五陰appears in the aha kouie shiery-inyun jig110)jingy xingdao juezhe dechu經言行道覺耆得出32).the simi-lar sentence jingcongdao de tuo經言從道得〓appears in the anbn shouyi jing3311)bufu xiang不復向34).the same term also appears in the anba shouyi iig35)and the ahbitn wufaxing jing(阿毘曇五法行經)36).from the above evidence of the terminology analysis, we can decidedly say that part of both texts was ren. deredby  Shigao. analysis of the terminologyinpart 3 The content of Part 3 only appears in the Mayi jing. the following analysis of one sentence and two terms from withinpart 3 shows, undoubtedly, that it is a ren-dering in the style of an Shigao. 1)shouzhi bianguan gu. jingyzhigun juxing. weide sidi.守止便觀故。經言止觀 倶行。爲得四諦37):the similar sentence zhigun ju suixing.. ling weizuo sishi止觀 倶隨行令爲作四事appears in yinchiru jing(陰持入經)38).according to this phrase's content, the term sishi四事refers to same meaning as sidi四諦.in anoth-er sentence with a similar meaning eyi zhi biande guangu.. weide sidi惡已止便得 觀故…爲得四諦appears ian shouyi jing39),even though it lacks the term zi-guan jiuxing止觀倶行other than  Shigao, translators in early chinese Buddhism seldom utilized the term zhiguan juxing.2)yi bizou意便走40).this term also appears in the ana shouyi jing413)bu zhuam yi不轉意42).this terrr also appears in the anan shouyi jing43)and the jie shiermen jing44. analysis of the terminology ipart l of the fagun jing In the following, we will examine seven terms or sentences ipart l of the fagucn jing and analyze their usage, which is characteristic of an Shigao's style. 1)dang tie shenyi chi. chizhe weiyiqie wusuofan.當立戒身意持〓持者爲一切無所 犯45).The similar sentence shenchi qijie yichi sn jie. shiwei shenyi chi ye.身持七 戒意持三戒。是爲身意持也appears in the anan shouyi jing46)2)tandaofa xing-dao貪道法行道47).the same term appears in the anban shouyi jing48)zuoxing  dao坐行道49).the same term exists in the anban shouyi jing50)and the mayi fing51) 4)shangye houye上夜後夜52).this word appears in the pufayi jing(普法義經)53), and the qichu sangucn jing (七處三觀經)54)this term was translated as chuye houye初夜後夜at a later time.5)chuxi ruxinian mieshi出息入息念滅時55)This term also exists in the anan shouyi jing56))ke zi guanshen. yike guan tarensh-en. youshi buke zi guanshen. yi buke gun tarenshen.可自觀身。亦可觀他人身。 有時不可自觀身・亦不可觀他人身57)。we can find the similar sentences youshi ke zi guanshen. yike gun tarenshen.. youshi buke zi guanshen. yi buke guan tarensh-en有時可自觀身・亦可觀他人身。有時不可自觀身。亦不可觀他人身appearing in the ana shouyi jing58)7)jianfei dangnin fengzhang. jicm bainiam sirengu. jian-ni meinicn siren yuhuaishi se zhu qinghei. jjia chisu mia xie.見肥當念逢脹。見 白念死人骨。見膩眉念死人欲壞時色轉青黒。見赤絮念血59)。The similar sentences 見肥當念死人脹。見白當念死人骨。見眉黒當念死人正黒。見朱脣當念血正赤are contained in the anba shouyi jig and the sentences意愛女人身白好當念死人 骨正白。意愛女人肌肉好當念人死壤時身裕痕。意愛女人脣赤好當念死人壤時四 正赤・意愛女人眉黒好當念死人壤時正青黒appears in the jfie shiermen jing6l). Analysis of the terminology inpartl of the mayi jjing Liu bolomi六波羅蜜:the term u bolomi appears in part l of the mayi jjing62 and it is a very important concept of Mahayana buddhism. although kang senghui used the similar term liudu六度〓nliuduii jing63),neither  Shigao nor his disci-ples had. So it is possible that part l of the 〓ayi jjing is a composite of text by a Shigao and another author.in agreement with hayashiya tomojiro's assertion, the uayi jjing seems to be a work of a shigao, but we can not declare this with cer. tainty. summary of the terminological analysis of the fagun jjing In the analysis of the l9 terms or sentences cited from the fagucn jing, it is ap. parent that they a11 correspond to an Shigao's style of oral rendering. the follow-ing list tallies the number of these terms or sentences that appear in other works by him. anban shouyi jing15jjie shiermen jing6  continued study of an Shigao's works (. unG)(127) ah koujie shieryinyun jing ahbitan wufaxing jing2) Mingdu wushi jiaoji jing Mingdu wushi jiaoji jing円 〓ingdu wushi jiaoi jing一pufayi jing〓 pufayi jing円 qichu sanguan jing一shiermen jing円 In addition, from the above list, we can find the number of terms appearing in the anbn shouyi jing is the most out of a11 other an shigao's works. Moreover, the beginning paragraph of the faguan jing64)diyi heyigu shuxi. yidexing weidiy-ichan第一何以故數息…以得行爲第一禪is closely connected in meaning to a part of the anban shouyi jing and originally should be placed before the sentence shusi yiwei sueidierchan數息以爲隨第二禪65) conclusion lt is likely that the 〓ayi jjing is an shigao's work, since apart from the termlu bolomi, most of the terminology is characteristic of his style. regarding the fagua jling, contrary to the previous assumption, it was not translated by zhu Fahu, but rather is an oral rendering by an shigao, as can be can be clearly determined by the analysis of the terminology. moreover, the beginning paragraph of the fagucm  jing diyi heyigu shuxi  yidexing weidiyichan contains partial content of the original translation of the ahbun shouyi jing, which is also a work of Shigao. (Bccause of limited space, the footnotes are deleted) &lt;key word&gt;  Shigao, Mayi jing, Faguan jing, anban shouyi jing Assistant professor, asia university, taiwan,  
</root>
