<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies References to bodhisattva in the large sutra of prainaparamito Denryay pannaloka 1.Introduction The purpose of this paper is to examine references to bodhhisattva names (referred to as bn) that occur at the beginning of chapter l (the scene) of three versions of the large sutra (〓S))of prainaparamita .The three versions examined are the sanskrit (Skr), Chinese (ch) and tibetan tib) versions. This examination is conducted in order to identify variations found between these texts and to cast light on their development and evolution. a total of twelve versions out of numerous versions are used in this study. 2.The sources The twelve versions used in this study are as follows. (1)satasahasrik prainaparamita-kr- (2)dabore iing大般若經初會(大般若波羅蜜多經(六百卷)初分唐),t22h 3)shes rab kyipha roltu phyinpstong phrag brgyap,4)ttpno.73 [-ib (4)pancavimsatisahasrika prainaparamitd-kr-] (5)guamgzan jing光讚經(十卷),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>)[c (6)fomgguang bore jing放光般若經(十卷),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>- (7)〓ohe bore boluomi iing摩訶般若波羅蜜經(二十七卷),t2238c-k (8)da bore jimg大般若經第二會(大般若波羅蜜多經(六百卷)第二分唐),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>22</w></ref> 「Ph- (9)shes rab kyipha roltuphyinp stong phrag myi shu lngapa,Tpno.71i 1 (10)shes rab kyi pha roltu phin stong phrag mi shu ngapa,11)tp no.5188 [p-i (11)da bore fing大般若經第三會(大般若波羅蜜多經(六百卷)第三分唐),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>22</w></ref>  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies )references to bodhisattva in the large sutra ofprainaparamita (. deniyaye 〓- (12)shes rab kyipho roltu phyinp khri brgy'ad stong p,3) tTpno.732d-ti The Sanskrit, chinese and tibetan versions vary in the total number of names b used Each of these versions is largely independent and unique. some versions omit prominent bn and diverge in differing degrees on epithets used. Tibetan versions-tib,p-fi-, aad-tib) often record extended lists of bn and share a greater number of terms than is shared with sanskrit and chinese versions. The p-b-2 iersion, however, which is a tibetan translation of the re-cast versionosr,14)differs considerably from the p--version that preceded it. 3.bodhisattva names (. The total number of bn used in the twelve versions of lS examined in this study are summarised in the table belowv. S-skr andp-skr give37)and4 respectively.23 of those names are used in both versions. s-skr uses1ew bn absent insr, i.e. ratnagarbha, Ratnadatta, grhagupta, Bhadrabala, anantamati, anavaranamati, anantavirya nityaprayukta, candragarbha, Marabalapramardin, mahakarunacintin, Mahavyuha, Vyuharaja, and Merukuta.psr uses one bn absent in -skr and s-ch, i.e. subhagupta.p--ues phug sbas (grhagupta). two bn are used in bothsr asr with only minor changes i.e. Susarthavaha in-sr is sarthavahaisr and anupamamati in -skr is anupamacintinisr. both s-tib and 〓-tib write these as ded dpon dma pa (Sarthavaha) and blo gros dpe med pa upamamati). The chinese hsuan-tsang versions S-ch, p-c-ha ad-ch use4017),26)and1 Bn respectively. the palso uses the greatest number ofnout of the four chi-lese translations oh.<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>,t221ad t223versions fecord independent lists of bn as dharmaraksa(T222)〓,20)moksala (<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>)221)and kumaraijiva <ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>)〓  the japanese ociationof indian and buddhist studies ceferences to bodhisattva in the large sutra of prainaporamita .deniyaYe Though the four translations differ they do share certain n, i.e. naluoda pusa那羅達菩 薩(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>),zengyi pusa増意菩薩(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>),buxujian pusa不虚見菩薩(<ref><canon>T</canon> <w>222</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>,220), changjushou pusa常擧手菩薩(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>220</w></ref>),cishi pusa 慈氏菩薩(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>222</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>220</w></ref>), daoshi pusa導師菩薩(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>),daoshi導師(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>221</w></ref>, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>223</w></ref>,〓220).two tibetan versions S-tib. ad -i-1)totally agree on the37b. the 〓-i-version contains only〓the ad-tib version contains3The bn Bhadrapala is used twice in spghosa), i.e.nos. l and 10.nevertheless, both tibetan versions, s-tib ad-i-, replace bhadrapala with bhadrabala (bzang po'i stobs) the sec. ond time that bn is used. p-sr omits kumarabhuta from the earlier bn manjusri kuma-rabhuta ('jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa).a11 tibetan and chinese versions are in accord with the s-skr version in its use of the fuller name. The name praharaia in sp(ghosa) and gra-haraiaikyo ms of -skr is read as vyuharaia in the tibetan mnam par bkod pa'i rgyal po) and chinese(莊嚴王)versions. the usage used in the later two versions seem to be more in accord with the original version. interestingly, Maitreya is not used by kumarajiva in 223making it different from the Skr and tib versions and from222,t22and T20 verslons. 4.conclusion From the foregoing observation, we can see that the s-skr version is an extendec iccount refected in its much greater number of bn. This version contains 13more bn than is contained in the skr version. the -skr and versions are both shotter and morc similar in their contents. Though the contents oib ar are understandably similar, theversion is even more similar to the s-fib version than is the psr version. The Tibetan version -tib is more similar to the pib version than to the -tib version. consistent with sanskrit tradition, the ad-skr version though the complete text is lost)seems to have been saller. 〓 examination of the sanskrit versions s, p add evidences an evolution with the most likely chronological order of the writing of these texts beingd first followed byp ollowed by s. the tibetan versions seem to reverse this chronological ordering withbe-ing followed by s. while s precedes pi chronological order in the Sanskrit versions, the reverse is true in the tibetan versions where pi-i)seems to precede s-tib chronologi-cally.  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhiststudies references to bodhisattvain the large sutra of prainaporamita (.deniyay, The absence of the terms maitreya(慈氏)and Suvikrantavikramin(mthu dam pas mnam par gnon pa) in both-kp-i-2 versions is perplexing. The fact that -- i-,in bka' 'gyur and the other in bstan 'gyur, 7)record different numnbers of bh reflects theit different archaic sources.-i.being akin to -skr and s-tib, records37bn. in contrast,pi-2 contains only2. according to our present knowledge on the historicity ofpemerged at least two hundred years after 〓i-.despite this fact, p-i- omits 16contained in the earlier -version. Later chinese and tibetan translators might have had access to the earlierversion. This is possible. classical texts were copied and preserved by competent scholars in diverse regions of ancient asia. Classical buddhist texts probably reached china as a result of trav- 〓ling monks or scholars who collected those texts form different regions of South asa.〓8 Notes 1)This study is basedon the records in the three versions of large sutra, i.e.ppi0 lines (S),ppi0 lines  adpi8o lines ). 2)satasahasrikprainaparamitaI pghos, ed. pratapacandra ghosa, calcutta,1902,p. 〓ff, tokyo university manuscript of skr, no.2(tkyoms). 3)〓-ch, The taisho Shinshu daizokyo or taisho issaikyo (ti), vol.5, tokyo,1988,p.i ff. 4)S-tib, tibetan tripitaka, peking ed.(Tp),1956,vol.12p3,4, taipei ed. ( taiwan),1991 vol.3,p.1ff. 5)p-sr, part i, ed. nalinaksa dutt (dutt), london,193,p. 5, 1.15sr, i-1, ed. takayasu Kimura (kimura) , tokyo,〓007,p.1f 6)dharmaraksa(竺法護)transl., tivol.8,p.147. 7)moksala(無羅叉)transl., ti vol.8,p.1 . 8)kumaraiiva(鳩摩羅什)transl., ti vol.8,p.217ff. 9)xuanzang(玄奘)transl., ti vol.7,p.1 10)tTp, vol.18,p.39f, d(taiwan), vol.6,p.1 ff. 11)tTp, vol.88,p.217f, d(taiwan), vol.6,p.1 . 12)xuazang(玄奘)transl., ti vol.7,p.427f. 13)TTP, vol.2,p.1,(taiwan), vol.6,p.332. 14)revised with reference to the abhisamayolankar of maitreyanatha entury a.d.). 15)ssp(Ghosa,p.6,7. 16)dutt, p.5, kimura, p.1,2. 17)Ti vol.5,p.1. 18)i vol,7.p.1, 19)Ti vol.7,p.7. 20)Ti vol. 8, p.17  the japanese ociationof Indian and buddhist studies References to bodhisattva in the large sutra of prainaporamita eniyaye)(6 21)TI vol.8,p.1. 22)ti vol. 8,p.217. 23)tTp no.730,ra 3a,3b (taiwan) 8, ka sa, 3b, ttp no.731,nyi 3a,3b,d(taiwan)9, Ka 3a, 3b. 24)tTp no.5188,ga3b,d(taiwan)3795,ga 3a.16absenti-are rin chen snying po, rin chen byin pa, skyob sbed, chu bdag lha, bzang po'i stobs, 'phags pa'i blo gros, blo gros mtha' yas, sgrib med blo gros, mthu dam pas rnam par gnon pa, brtson'grus mtha yas, zla ba'1 inying po, bdud kyi stobs rabtu 'joms pa, snying nje cher sems, rgyan chen po, rnam par bkod pa'i rgyal po, andribo'm. 25)tTp no.732,ni2b,d(taiwan)10,ka2b. conze records only2aes (edward coze The large sutra ofperfect wisdom,1ze], p.38)omitting Ratnagarbha (i po che snying), ratnadatta (rin chen byin), anantamati (blo gros mtha' yas),anavaranamati (blc gros sgri bmed),anantavirya (brtzon'grus mtha 'yas), nityaprayukta (rtag tu sbyor ba), can-lragarbha (zla ba'i snying po) and mahakarunacintin (sying tje cher sems). conze's Subha-gupta and-ibs phug sbas (Grhagupta) are not foundin other versions. 26)conze,pl., p.40a part of the text foundin gilgit manuscripts has been published by coze (pp.xxvi+9, serie orientale rom xxvi,1962. 27)TTPnos731and5188,d(taiwan) nos. 9 and3795,d(tohoku) nos. 9 and3790.tibetan translators are yeshessde and, Tshulkhrims rgyalba (Jayasila) and zhi ba bzang po (santi-bhadra) respectively. of the first, the sanskrit version is lost (coze,pl., p.34), and of the second version, not known to chinese translators, the Sanskrit version remains in nepalese ms (ibid, p. 36) and it has been the base text for modern researchers inEurope and japan. the chapter's closing sentence "y-pancavimsatisahasrikoymbhagavatyrajnoparamitayom abhisamayalankoranusorena smsodhitoyom" is proof that p-i-2 has been later fevised under the influence ofa. hence, this version was written some time after maitreyanathacentur a.d.) the author oa. 28)chou hsiang kuang, the historyofchinese buddhism, delhi,1956,p.2ff. &lt;key words) bodhisattva, prainaporamito  
</root>
