<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies defilement (klesa) originating from erroneous judgment ayonisomanasikora) according to the Mahayana sutras Mryazkitensho 1.Introduction ayonisomanasikara, a terminology peculiar to buddhist literature, is attested in the contex1 of the arising of defilements in the nikoyas, and yonisomanasikara, its antonym, is usec in later times to refer to an important practice in some texts of the viinaptimatravadin. The explanation that kles originates from ayonisomanasikora appears in the ratnagotrayi-bhag,as pointed out by takasaki [1988.prof. takasaki has revealed that the explanation was originally taken from the*Gaganaganjapariprccha gp) and the jnanalokolamkara, and that similar explanations are found in the* dharani-svararoicsutra h), the*aksayamatinirdesn) and the* bodhisattvapitakap). Based o prof. takasaki〓s work, Sasaki [1991]has classified the explanation found ir the rv into two types: one where klesa originates directly from ayonisomanasikora and the other where avidy precedes ay'onisomanasikura in the context of the twelvefold Interdependent origination (pratityasamutpada). in addition, prof. Sasaki has indicated that the origin of these two types goes back to the abhidhorma literature and the agama of the sarvastivadin, respectively. The first type, as found in the gpi the rgv, derivec originally from the〓abhidharmaprakarana(阿毘達磨品類足論)and was succeeded by the*mahavibhasasustra(大毘婆沙論)and the abhidharmakosabhasya. The second type, which appears in the icited in the rg,the aksn and the bdp, derived from the sahetusapratyayasanidanasutra4, which was compiled by the sarvastivacin and appear in other treatise (sstras) of the sarvastivudin and the yiinaptimotravadin. Based oprof. Sasaki's classification, i will explore some of the mahayana sutras re-ferring to the explanation of klesa originating fromayonisomanasikora. these sutras have nothing to do with the Tathagatagarbha theory or the rgv. the main aim of this paper is to shed light on the relationship between the Mahayana sutras and the works of the sarvasti-vadin and the viinaptimatrovadin, an issue which was not solved in Sasaki [991].  the japanese ociationof indian and buddhist studies defilement (klesa) originating from erroneous Judgment ayonisomanasikara)(7 according to the mahayana sutras t. myazaki, 2.klesa originating directly firomayonisomanasikora As examined by takaski [188] and Sasaki [1991], the rvbases the understanding that klesa originates directly from ayonisomanasikura on the accounts attested in the ggp5 In a11 three extant versions ofthe gagp, we find almost the same explanation In addition to examining the sources of this understanding, i add here an account of the *yisesacintibrahmapariprccha vbrahp).it is clear that the three later versions of the Vbrahp contain similar expressions of the explanation , although in the oldest translatior by dharmaraksa,持心梵天所問經(tno.585),the expression is rather ambiguous: 假使思惟順如應者,凡夫愚〓言發塵勞,心之本淨無能汚處。以無能汚,是故名曰本末清 淨。設不染汚故,曰本淨是故解脱,爲解脱也(〓15.6 The phrase〓思惟順如應'seems to correspond to* yonisomanasikara, but, since its coun-terpart in the other versions uses*ayonisomanasikara, this might be a mistranslation where the translator overlooked the negative prefixayonisomanasikora. Itis noteworthy that this explanation appears in both the gagp and vbrahpi the con-text of elucidating the innate purity of mind. This raises the possibility that there was some connection between these two works. 〓集果體能本準無能び。以無能汚,是故名日本未消 〓 3.ignorance (avidya ) originating fromayonisomanasikarain connection with the Twelvefoldprafityasamutpdd The rgvtakes ffom the jithe explanation that avidya originates from ayonisomanasi-kora, and this understanding is also found in the dhr, the aksn and the bdp,as takasaki [1988]and Sasaki [1991]pointed out. Jan the three extant versions of the ja, including the newly found Sanskrit text, the explanation appears as one of the sixteen modes of the buddha's enlightenment(菩提 一六相)9).however, the chinese translation by*samgabhara(僧伽婆羅),度一切諸佛境 界智嚴經(tno.358), which seems to preserve an earlier form,has a different explane tion 文殊師利1無生滅者不起心意識,不思惟分別。若有分別,則成無明。不起此無明則無 十二因縁(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>12</v>.<w>25221</w></ref>) The underlined sentence means: "if you have a false notion(*vikapa(* parikapa), ignorance (*avidya) arises." in the parallel part in the other versions, however,*aponisomanasikara appears instead of*vikap* parikalpa.  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhiststudies 8) defilement (klesa) originating from erroneous judgment (ayonisomanasikara) According to the mahayana sutras(T. Mryaaki) 〓hRThe d contains two examples of a similar explanation. both examples car been found in a11 the extant versions of the dhr, including the oldest Chinese translation by dharmaraksa,大哀經(tno.398), as quoted below. [a]其内淨者彼無想念已,無想念除於顛倒。唯念柔順不住無明。已不住無明,則不復住 十二有數。已能不住十二有數,則無所生。(〓149 [b謂縁報?何謂事業?從不順11)念而致縁報,從無明事,衆生之類而致欲塵。從無明事 而致行矣。…不順12)念報應因縁生明慧事業無明行及其所造作。(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>13</v>.<p>417</p>-<c>c</c><l>8</l></ref>) Example [a] describes one of the sixteen modes of the buddha's Enlightenment, which corresponds to the descriptions in the jiand the bdp. Aksn The explanation is found in the later two extant versions of the aksn. but the oldest chinese translation by dharmaraksa,阿差末菩薩經(tno.403), does not have this account13). Tbpi a11 the three existing versions of the bdp, i find four examples of a similar ex-planatiothe fourth example in the bdp illustrates one of the sixteen modes of the Buddha's enlightenment, as appears in the iaand the dhr. In addition to these four texts mentioned in previous studies, i will mention here three other mahayana sutras that refer to the understanding: the lokottaraparivartp,the ratnakarandcsutra  and the bodhisattvagocaropoyavisayavikurvamanirdepvn). 〓p The lpis known as one of the chapters of the avatamsaka, with its oldest chinese translation by dharmaraksa,度世品經(tno.292), surviving as a separate work. the ex. planation is found in a11 four extant versions of the lp, including dharmaraksa's transla tion, as quoted below15) 計於諸法,悉從縁轉。因虚僞退,從習不順,合於無明十二縁起,至老病死。除不順念, 無明則除。無明已除,生老病死永悉除矣。(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1493</w></ref>) Rk similar expressions are found in a11 three extant versions of the rk, including the oldest chinese translationby dharmaraksa,文殊師利現寶藏經(tno.461) 無清淨寂即立無點。所念靜點,無黠則不立。已無有立,則爲永寂,是謂無黠盡。彼以念 靜盡,觀四大之身,是爲愚癡之身(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>14</w></ref> of these phrases, which are difficult to understand, though,所念靜點(underlined) and念 靜are most likely to correspondto*yonisomanasikara in the other versions. bbguun only bodhiruci's chinese translation of the bguvvn,大薩遮尼乾子所説經 (<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>272</w></ref>),contains the explanation, as quoted below  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies defilement klesa) originating from erroneous Judgment (ayonisomanasikara) According to the mahayana sutras (t. myazk. 云何名因?云何名縁?知諸衆生思惟不善是生死因縁。因不善思惟故生長無明,是故不善 爲因無明爲縁。因無明故則生於行,是故無明爲因諸行爲縁。如是乃至因生則有老死等苦, 是故生則爲因老死爲縁(t955c12-15) bodhiruci's chinese translation, which is about three times the length of the first chinese ranslation, seems to have been greatly extended, and in the counterpart of the tibetan translatio,there is no parallel phrase. 4.The origination of avidya fromayonisomanasikora without connection to the Twelvefoldprafityasamutpad we find another type of explanation that avidya originates fromayonisomanasikara having no connection to the twelvefoldpratityasamutpada. this type, which the rgv never men-tions and which has not been dealt with in previous studies, is of significance in under-standing the background of the two types of explanations. This third type appears in the following two sutras: the*aratasatrukaukrtyavinodanosutrakv and the*ratnd meghosutra gh). 〓4kv the explanation appears in a11 the extant versions of the dk), including the oldest chinese translationby lokaksema,阿闍世王經(tno.626) 阿闍世王復問:"助貪愛者根爲在何所?"佛言:"無點是。"則復問:"誰是無點?"佛言: "所作與念異是故根。"(〓1535-29) The above quoted passage is a link in the unique causal relationship in the akvas fol-lows. popakarmaviparytkoyadrsti〓*auiyonisomamasikura(*smaropa only in tib.)*bhutaparikambhuta Rmgh mong the five existing versions of the rngh, only the second chinese transla-tion by*Mandrasena(曼陀羅仙)and* samgabhara(僧伽婆羅),大乘寶雲經(<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>659</w></ref>), provides the explanation. 是諸煩惱從何縁生?是諸因縁復依何生?即得知見煩惱因縁則是無明,無明因縁不善思惟。 不善思惟復何因生?不聽正法。不聽正法復何因縁?不近善友。如是知已煩惱因縁,煩惱 原由,煩惱境界。(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>16</v>.<w>22</w></ref> n the other versions,we find no sentences cotresponding to the underlined ones. 5.conclusions [n this paper i have examined some of the mahayana sutras not mentioned in previous  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies ) defilement klesa) originating from erroneous judgment (ayonisomanasikara) according to the mahayana Sutras (t. myaaki) studies that contain the explanation that klesa originates fromayonisomanasikara, which is attested in the ybrchp, the lp, the rk, the djkv, bodhiruci's translation of the bgvn(大 薩遮尼乾子所説經)and the chinese translation of the rgh by*Mandrasena and *Samga-bhara(大乘寶雲經).such sutras as the gogp and the ja that have been examined in the previous studies are closely connected to the tathagatagarbha Theory or the rgv, while the mahayana sutras I have discussedin this paper seem to have nothing to do with them Moreover, it is worthy of note that the vbrahp, the rk and the ajkvcan be categorized as the sutras of maniusri. Given that the explanation is found in the old chinese translations such as loka-ksema's translation of the ajkvand dharmaraksa's translation of the dhr, the lp and the Rk, it seems quite possible that the explanation was introduced into the Mahayana sutras at a comparatively early stage. moreover, unlike the texts of the sarvastivadin, the 4jkvhas the unique explanation that avidy originates fromayomisomanasikuara without connection to the twelvefoldpratitycscmutpcdc, and we thereforewe need to be concerned with not only the sarvastivcdin's influence on these mahayana sutras, but also the mutual relations between the mahayana sutras20) 1)mejor, m., "controversy on the mutual conditioning of avidya and ayonisomanas (i) kara in vasubandhu'sabhidharmakosa," journal of the internotional college fodanced buddhist Studies#4,〓01. 2)takasaki, j., "kvakuiin-bonno: nyoraizo-shiso no bonno-ron," nyoraizo-yhiso j, pp.21252, 1988(frst publishedin75. 3)sasaki, s., "The explanation of the origination of klesa in the ratnagotravibhoga"i japa-nese),jb#40-1,pp.89383,1991 4)matsuda, k., Three sutras on the pratityasamutpad theory in the chinese version of the sampuktogamd" japanese),bukky'o kenkyu#1,pp.899,1984 5)In the rgv. the gagp is quoted inch. i-v-unoriginated character of the Innate Mind'. in this paper, the chapters and the sections of the Rvfollows Takasaki, j. [96] a study on the ratnagotravibhagttaratantra). 6)大集經虚空蔵菩薩品<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>397</w>(8)<p>131215</p><c>a</c><l>1</l></ref>,大集大虚空藏菩薩所問經tno. 〓41tib. trans. P u288.however, in the latter half of the examples quoted bv the rn.46,ib. pu, the oldest chinese translation in the daiiring, tno.397(8), lacks the explanation. 7)思益梵天所問經tno.5861,勝思惟梵天所問經tno.58715.8,ib trans. pphu72.  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies defilement (klesa) originating from erroneous Judgment (ayonisomanasikara) According to the mahayana sutras (T. Myaak) 8)In the rgv, the iais quotedinch. i-〓-(3The doctrine as the truth of Extinction'. 9)Skt. of thej,如來莊嚴智慧光明入一切佛境界經tno.357129,入諸佛境 界智光明莊嚴經tno.35912-29. 10)takasaki, j., the formationof the tathagatagarbha theory japanese),1974,pp 〓6. 11)taisho reads〓愼',but we take the variant〓順'in the three editions(宋元明三本)and the old Song edition belonging to the library ofthe imperial household(宮内庁本). 12)see note 11. 13)大集經無尽意菩薩品<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>397</w></ref>(12)13.19783; tib. trans. aksayamatinirdesa suitra, (ed. by braarvig, j., 1993)ipp.776.The counterpart of the dharmaraksa's translation 阿差末菩薩經(tno.4.972-7) does not contain the explanation 14)[]大宝積經菩薩蔵會<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>30</w></ref>(12)11.1999,大乘菩薩藏正法經tno.3167 〓773, tib. trans.  di295[]<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1120</w>-<v>1</v></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><v>11</v>.<p>786</p><c>b</c><l>2</l></ref>si296 [〓]<ref><canon>T</canon><v>11</v>.<w>202</w>,<v>11</v>.<p>7</p><c>d</c></ref>si2925a2.[<ref><canon>T</canon><v>11</v>.<p>228</p></ref>, 11.879wi212. 15)六十華厳tno.278,八十華厳tno.27930b-9,tib. trans. p si16 16)大方廣寶篋經tno.46272-, tib. trans. p chu 17)tib. trans. nu87-8. The first chinese translation of the bguyvn,菩薩行方便境界神通 變化經(tno.271),has no counterpart. 18)普超三味經<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>62716</w></ref>;未曾有正法經<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>6284779</w></ref>,tib. trans. p tsu 〓b2. 19)寶雲經tno.65816.2-1;寶雨經tno.6016.315-17,除蓋障菩薩所問經Tno. 48917372,tib. trans. pdzu87b2. 20)we find two instances of this explanation in大薩遮尼乾子所説經and大乘寶雲經as well. considering the fact that other versions of these sutras do not contain this account, these expla-nations must have been incorporated later in the process of transmission or translation. This may indicate that this understanding would have been spread among the transmitters and the transla-tors of the mahayana sutras. (key words)ayonisomamasikara, klesa, avidya, the twelvefold pratityasamuppada, ratnago-ravibhaga, sarvastivadin, mahayana sutras (Graduate student, The university of tokyo, jSPs research fellow)  
</root>
