<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies )journalofindiam ad buddhist studies vol.58,no.3. March The vyaghri-jataka known to sri lankan buddhists and its Relation to the northern buddhist Versions MaTSUMURA Junko 1.Introduction onthe wall of a rock cave at aluvihara temple in matale, sri lanka, among other jataka stories and famous paintings describing tortures in hells, several painted stories of bodhi-sattva, or jdtakas, are found, of which o pali version is known. one of them is the well. known story of bodhisattva's body-sacrifice to a hungry tigress. The story is, however, not included in the canonical pali Jataka collection, in which is found only a totally different story of the same name, the vyagghajataka (Ja no.272),where bodhisattva is a tree god. but the story which the people o this Theravada buddhist island know by the name svyaggha-jataka', or vyaghrl-jataka', is not the one in the pali jataka collection, but exactly the same story which is well-known and wide-spread among northern (or mahayana) bud-dhists. this fact is the starting point of the present author's research for this article: how this story came to be known in sri lanka. The facts of the research may reveal some of the historical intercourse between Southern and northern buddhism, upon which, so far not much research has been pursued. besides this, the story's version known on the island is not the sole one. but. as we discuss later, there seem to be several versions to be related to defnite versions found in the northern buddhist texts. 2.versions of the tigress story The bodhisattva body-sacrifice to a hungry tigress story (hereafter called the tigress story', orin Skt., 〓vyaghri-jataka', as i ryasura's jatakamala) is related in several notthern buddhist texts. The most well-known version may be the one in the suvarn (p) bhs-utraor the suvarnaprabhasottamcsutra). For this sutra, there exist the sanskrit text, the three translations in the chinese tripitaka, and the translations inhibetan, mongolian, khotanese, and Uighur languages. however, itis beyond the scope of this article to examine and compare a11 these  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies The vvaphri-jataka knownto sr lankan buddhists andits relation to the norhern buddhist versions j. masumURa)( exts. inconnection with the present article's theme, therefore, only the chinese translations will be treated. In the xiam-yu-jing賢愚經,the so-called sutra of the wise and the foolish, another famous version of the story is found. The main story of these two texts is essentially the same. however, the number of cubs to which the tigress gave birth differ, namely seven in the fotmer and two in the latter. For the study of tigress story versions only these two have been attracting much interest. The number of cubs has been the most decisive characteris-tic, especially for art-historians, to identify the story's painted versions. Beside those two texts, there are several other versions of the stoty which are divided roughly into two groups: texts in which bodhisattva was prince mahasattva, and texts in which bodhisattva was a brahman ascetic. in the following sections i will list the texts o1 these two groups with brief accounts of their contents. 3.versions in which bodhisattva was prince mahasattva(摩訶薩〓 3.1.The suvarn (pra) bhasa-sutra(金光明經tr. by dharmaksema(曇無識)385-433c. e., 〓1no.663,35c22-3c21;合部金光明經,a revised version of the former, completed in 597c. e., t16no.64,3962399c21,金光明最勝王經,anew translation by yi-jing(義淨) completed in. e., t6no.6,45c22-44b2). bodhisattva was prince mahasattva(摩訶薩〓),the youngest of three sons of king maharatha, the eldest being prince mahapranada (or mahabala), and the second, prince mahadeva.1/he saw a starving tigress with seven cubs and, out of compassion, he laid his body in front of the tigress. but, because of his power of loving-kindness, the tigress did not dare to eat him. so, having pierced his neck with a bamboo spike, he jumped down from a high mountain and lay dead in front of her The tigress and her seven cubs could then eat his body and their lives were saved 3.2.the xian-yu-/jing賢愚經,or the sutra of the wise and the foolishcompiled by hui-jiao(慧覺)and others, based upon stories heard in the country of gao-chang(高昌,turpan, or tradi-tionally called turfan), 5th century, <ref><canon>T</canon><v>4</v>.<w>202</w>,<p>352</p><c>b</c><l>1</l>-<p>353</p><c>b</c><l>16</l></ref>)the plot of the main story is very similar to the one in the suvarn (pra) bhusasutra. The only difference is that Prince Mahasattva's father is Maharatna, not maharatha, and the number of cubs is two. it also has a typical jotaka story structure, namely, a story taking place in the present (paccupanna-vatthu) and concludes with explanation of the connection of the characters in the main story with those in the present day story (samodhana)  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 〓 the vvaghri-jataka known to si lankan buddhists andits relation tothe northern buddhist versions(j. aTsumura) 3.3.The fo-shuo-p-s-ben-xing-jing(佛説菩薩本行經,4th-5th century c.e., translator unknown <ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v> no.<w>155</w>.<p>119</p>-<c>29</c></ref>) 摩訶薩〓太子時.爲餓虎故放捨身命.when bodhisattva was prince Mahasattva, he sacrificec his life for a hungry tiger (or tigress). there is no mention of the cubs. 〓..The pu-ben-sheng-mn-un(菩薩本生鬘論,〓) late loth century to the early 1lth centur. c. e., <ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v> no.<w>1633223</w>-<p>333</p><c>b</c></ref>9)except for a slight difference of the introductory narration the content is apparently adopted from the suvarn (pra) bhasasutra. 3,5.The fo-shuo-y-xing-she-shen-jing(佛説要行捨身經,tang dynasty, translator unknown probably a compilation madein china, t85no.2895,14156-7) having understood the truth of sunyata, prince mahasattva offered his body to a hungry tigress and her sven cubs. 4.versions in whichbodhisattva wasabrahmamscetic 41aryasura's jofakamaha or the bodhisattyavadanamdah～oth century c.e., ed. h. Kern.1-6): bodhisattva was borni a tich brahman family and became an ascetic. when he was wandering ir a forest accompanied by his disciple, aiita, he saw a tigress that was about to devour her cubs ou of intense hunger ( number of cubs unstated).after having sent ajita to look for food for the tigress, he threw himself in front of the tigress 4.2.The dipvavadoned.p.l. vaidya, 310,29312,2) bodhisattva was botn in a rich brahman family and was named brahmaprabha. He became an iscetic. when he and his two fellow ascetics saw a hungry tigress with two cubs, he gave his body o the tigress to prevent her from eating hei cubs. 〓3The li--ji-jing(六度集經,translated by kan seng-hui(康僧会,9～280c.e.),T3 no.152 〓b-26) when bodhisattva was practicing austerities on a mountain, he saw a hungry tigress nursing her cubs. bodhisattva threw his body head-first into the mouth of the tigress. (number of cubs unstated)。 4.4. ksemendra's bodhisattyavadanakatpaluta no.51(rukmavatyavadana, ed. vaidya, i 〓1-319 Bodhisattva was first botn as a woman named Rukmavati. She cut her breasts off and gave them to a poor starving woman as food, and through the satyavacana done in front of god sakra she was transformed into a man and became king sattvavara. Then, in his next life, he was teborn as a  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies the vvaghri-jataka known to sri lankan buddhists and its relation tothe northem buddhist versions (j.mansumUra. brahmin named satyavrata and became an ascetic. when he saw a tigress, who had given birth to wo cubs, about to eat them out of hunger, he gave his body as food to the tigress 5. The tigress story of the Fo-shuo-p-tou-shen-h-qi--yin-yn-jing(佛説菩薩投身[飴]餓虎起塔因縁經) In addition to the tigress story versions discussed above, there exists a very interesting and unique, in which bodhisattva was a prince called candanamati and later became an ascetic. The textis extant onlyichinese translation, but itis almost surely translated from a Sanskrit original, giving us a close look at a probable relationship with the gandhara tegion. This text's name is the fo-shuo-pu-s-tou-shen-y-e-hu-qi-t--yn-jing(佛説菩薩 投身飴餓虎起塔因縁經,<ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v> no.<w>172</w>,<p>4244</p><c>12</c></ref>).according to the colophon, this text was translated by a monk, Fa-sheng, from turfan in northern liang(北涼高昌國沙門法盛譯). so itmay be assigned to ca.4.e. asummary of the story is as follows: buddha once went to the kingdom of gandhara(乾陀越國)and there he related the following story Nine kolpas ago, bodhisattva was botn as crown prince zhan-tan-mo-ti(梅檀摩提,*candana-nati) of a great kingdom called Gan-tuo-mo-ti(乾陀摩提,*Gandhamati). his father, the king, was Gan-tuo-shi-li(乾陀戸利,*Gandhasri), and his mother, the queen, was cha-mo-mu-qu(差 摩目怯;*ksemamegha?).The crown prince was fond of practicing charity, but, fearing to put his family into destitution by using up a11 the tiches of the foyal house, he secretly went to another kingdom called pei-ti-she(斐提舍,*vidisa), where he sold himself as a slave to a brahman for one thousand pieces of gold. these he then gave as alms to the poor. while he was collecting fire-wood on a mountain, he found a great amount of gosirsacandana (the best canduna wood, said to cure a11 diseases), with which he then cured the king who suffered from leprosy. The king of pei-ti-she (vidisa) was very pleased, and after freeing the prince from slavery, sent him back to his na-tive kingdom. However, the prince again left the palace and went deep into the mountains to join a group of ascetics. One day, he saw a tigress with seven cubs, freezing in the snow at the bottom of a deep gorge. he told his teacher and five hundred fellow ascetics that he wanted to sacrifice his body to save the tigress and her cubs. although his teacher tried to stop him, saying that he was still young and had much to learn, the prince replied that, in the distant past, he had made a vow to give his body a thousand times and had already done so nine hundred ninety-nine times in his former lives. this, then, was the final occasion to fulfill his vow. he climbed up to the top of a high precipice, threw himself off, and landed dead in front of the tigress. his parents, the kind and queen, built a stupa there containing the prince's bones. at the end ofthe story, the relationship of the characters in the past time to those in the  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies the vyaghri-jataka knownto sri lankan buddhists and its relation to the northern budchist versions (j. atsuMura) present time is revealed, and the teacher in the group of ascetics is identified with bodhisattva Maitreya. this is a noteworthy characteristic in connection with one of the sri lankan versions to be discussed below. this chinese text also reports that the dan and Xiang editions(丹郷本)have a sequel: the king in the time of buddha) built a great stipa at the place, and it exists even to this day. at the east side of the stupa, there is a temple compound and five thousand monks venerate the stupa continually. Fa-sheng(法 盛,the translator of the text) himself saw that people from various countries who have an llness like leprosy or other diseases with no known cures always come to this stupa to pay homage, and they are a11 cured.3) The content of this text is, as seen above, very unique among the many versions of the tigress story. that Fa-sheng(法盛)seems to have visited the place and probably obtained the otiginal Sanskrit text there, and also the fact that the name, Gandhara, is mentioned in the text itself, gives proof that this version may have been the most popular one in sth century Gandhara. in addition, the text is endowed with features of masterly prose composition with a smooth narration vivid and sometimes even with humor. The present author would like to give only one example here: when the crown prince runs away to another kingdom to sell himself, the queen, the mother, becomes half-crazed and reproaches the king "夫人罵曰『由王樫貪,護惜錢財,不愛念子.今寧可以錢財為子身不?』王曰『吾失 在先,今悔何及?且其還宮,保不失子.今悔何及?且共還宮,保不失子."(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v>no.<w>172</w> 〓<p>59</p>-<c>11</c></ref>) The queen curses the king saying, "it is because you are stingy, grudging money and don't really love your son. now what are you going to do for your so's life with the money?'The king answered: 〓what's done is done. what use for regret ? now let's go back to the palace. i wil certainly protect my son.' although in this case, the cause of argument is rather serious, the conversation is a quarrel that might be heard between any husband and wife. 5.The vyaghryapadana in the bodhisattvavadanakalpalato In addition to the version discussed above there is another unique version found in the bodhisattvavadanakolpalata, no.95vyaghryavadana (ed. vaidya, vol.2,pp.7538)in which bodhisattva was prince karunarekha,4)not prince mahasattva. in this version, emphasis is put on the story of the present time (paccupannavatthu), and, what is noteworthy, is that this story is more detailed than the one in the introduction of the samne story in the  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies he vvaghi-jataka knownto sri lankan buddhists and its relation tothe Northem buddhist versions j. maumura)( 〓i-yu-jing or the sutra of the wise and the foolish (above3.2.).however, the main story that it accompanies is totally different, bodhisattva was a prince named karunarekha, who gave his body to a tigress in order to prevent her from devouring her own two cubs out of intense hunger. It is interesting that the bodhisattvavadanakulpalata includes two totally different versions of the tigress story (c.4.4 7.The tigress stories transmitted in sri lanka and their relation to Northern versions The paintings at aluvihara temple are apparently not of very old origin. but this fact does not mean that these jataka stories were only recently introduced to sri lanka. The painting of the tigress story shows surprising cotrespondence with the version in the divya-vaddna discussed above(2.), because there are depicted two fellow ascetics of bodhisattva and two cubs of the tigress. There is also concrete evidence i a-xian's travel record to India and sri lanka, the goo-seng-xizhucn(高僧法顯傳t51o.〓85), that northern or mahayanistic jataka stories were known to sinhalese buddhists in the sth century c.e. Fa-xian stayed at abhayagirivihara in anuradhapura for about two years (c.4.e.), and during his stay he witnessed the tooth Relic festival. in his description of the festival we find the following passage: 佛齒常以三月中出之.未出前十日,王莊校大象,使一辯説人著王衣服騎象上撃鼓唱言. 菩薩從三阿僧祇劫作行不惜身命.以國城妻子及挑眼與人割肉貿尚截頭布施投身卸 虎不悋髓腦.如是種種苦行爲衆生故成佛.(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>51</v>no.<w>085</w>,<p>82</p>-<c>25</c></ref>) Here, not only the tigress stoty but also the story of cutting off one's flesh to save the life of a dove ( the Mahayana version of the sibi-jataka) and the story of cutting off the head to give it as alms ( the king candraprabha jataka, for which the pali textis so far unknown) are men-tioned. also, the period of bodhisattva's past lives to fulfill a11 poramitos to become a bud-dha is here said to be three asankhyeya-kalpas, a period commonly said in most mahayana Buddhist literature, while in the Theravada tradition it is usually said to be four asankhvevgs and a hundred of thousand kalpos. actually, on his way to india, fa-xian visited the place where bodhisattva sacrificed his body to save a tigress. 自此東行七日.有國名竺刹戸羅.竺刹戸羅漢言截頭也.佛爲菩薩時,於此處以頭施人.  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 敷促長致率線康相織種教導性強物機ガ此示物変混大養せ番算ブる 故因以爲名。復東行二日至投身倭餓虎處.此二處亦起大塔.皆衆寶校飾.諸國王臣民競 興供養.散華然燈相繼不絶.通上二塔彼方人亦名爲四大塔也.(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>51</v>o.<w>208</w>,<p>858</p><c>b</c><l>6</l>-<l>11</l></ref>) as discussed above, Fa-sheng(法盛)also visited the same place only about20years later than Fa-xian(法顯)。〓)therefore, the story that Fa-xian knew may be most probably the same version of theptou-shen f e-hu qi-ta jing菩薩投身飯餓虎經,or the fo-shuo pu-s tou-shen yi e-hu qi-yyn jing佛説菩薩投身飴餓虎起塔因縁經(tno. 172)translated into chinese by fa-sheng, and not the famous version in the suvar (pra) bhoscsutra, this is because in the ino.172version, the stupa containing bodhisattva's bones was built at the place where bodhisattva sacrificed his body. and at the time of Fa-xian and Fa-sheng, people believed the stupa near taxila (probably at mardan) was that one, while in the suvarn (pra) bhasasutra version, buddha relates the stoty at the request of the bodhi tree under which he attained enlightenment. The stupd appears from the earth when buddha starts the sermon and it disappears at its end. about years later, wher Xuan-zang(玄奘)visited the same place, there was still that same stupa, but the cloister was almost deserted. This may be the reason why xuan-zang connected the place with the Suvarn (pra) bhasasutra version of the story. In sri lanka, another painting of the tigress story is found on the outside wall of an image house at ruvanvalisaya innuradhapura. in this painting, however, there are depicted neither the two brothers nor the cubs. we may say that this painting corresponds to the version in the fo-shuo-p-ben-xing-jing (above 3.3.) Finally. there is a written text of the tigress stoty in sri lanka.a wesleyan missionary, robert spence hardy, reported the story in his manualof buddhism publishedin: 〓The next birth received by bodhisat was as a brahman, in the village of daliddi, and on account of the great beauty of his person he was called brahma. as sixteen years of age he had read the three vedas, iriu, yaiu, and sama, and was acquainted with a11 the sciences. near the rock of eraka, but then called munda, he became an ascetic, and had5 followers, of whom the bodhisat who will one day become maitri budha was the chief. one day, when this(!) disciple and brahma were wandering about the forest to gather fruits fof theif sustenance, they saw near the tock a tigress that had some time before brought forth, and was then suffering from hunger. brahma, on seeing this, reflected again on the evils ofexistence, and sent his disciple if he could find any bones of offal that they could give to the tigress to appease its hunger. during his absence, brahma remembered thatit was only by the birth ofa budha that these evils could be femoved, and calling to mind that resolu-tion he had previously formed, he reflected that in order to the attainment of this great object it  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies the vvaghni-jataka knownto sni lankan buddhists andits Relation to the northemn buddhist versions (j matsumura) would be necessary for him to give in alms, many times, his own heads, eyes, wives, and children Then exclaiming, "may iby this become a budha" he placed himself in the way of the tigress, that by giving his flesh he might preserve its life and that of its little ones. when the animal perceived him. it bounded from the rock to the place where he stood, seized him, and tore himin pieces. by he power of the merit arising from this act he was born in adeva-oka." This story is, according to its author, based upon the saddharmaratnakaraya, the 15th century sinhalese work written by dharmadinna vimalakirti. in this stoty we can see the resemblance to the jatakamala version, in which bodhisattva wandered in the forest accompanied by only one disciple, ajita. but it also shows resemblance with the tno.172 version, in which bodhisattva joined the group of500 ascetics and their leader is identified with the future buddha Maitreya. however, this version is also different from the twc painted story versions that the present author saw in srilanka. 8. conclusion As we have seen above, we know still very little about the actual theravada buddhis1 tradition. although it is generally believed that Mahayana buddhism was denied and a11 Mahayana scriptures were destroyed by religious reform undertaken by king parakrama. bahu the Great in the 12th century in sri lanka, some of the northern or mahayana tradi-tions once introduced on the island have been transmitted in various ways. it is very impor tant to search for those elements both in art and in texts in order to understand the reality of Sinhalese buddhism, or even to understand how the literal tradition was transmitted over centuries. to discover these elements, it is important, on the one hand, to investigate the great mine of sinhalese medieval (11th-15th centuries) buddhist literature as well as the post-canonical pali literature of the same period, since in that age the sinhalese buddhist scholar-monks were very active and produced many works. it is in these that the old traditions of the island still alive at that times. o the other hand, also important, as the present author has shown by example, is a more detailed study ofthe texts belonging to the Northern tradition, especially the texts only surviving i chinese translations along with the study ofpali or southern buddhist texts. needless to say, to get the complete picture of Sinhalese buddhism we must go back into history, into its art and literature, a huge task for which the concentrated collaboration of scholars in the allied fields of archeology, art history and linguistics is to be greatly intensified and deepened.  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies 1)1o.663,35376-39921,no.6640425.For the skt text, see nobel, johannes(1937),svarnaprabhosottamasutra, ds goldgutra ein sanskrittext des mahayan-buddhismus nach dedschriften und mit hitfe der tibetischen ubersetzungenleipzig: otto harrassowitz), pp.2402)for this chinese text. advocated as a translation of aryasura's jatakamala, see the famous article by brough, johr (1964),"the chinese pseudo-translatien of atyasuta's Jatakamala, a maior,new series xi.i, pp.27-hara minoru and wright, j.c.(1996) ed., collectedperslondons school of oriental and african studies), pp.217-2433)The abridged version is found in the chinese fing-i-yi-xiang(經律異相t53no.212,compiled by bao-chang(寶唱)and other monks i6c.. the tigress stoty is foundin Scroll13,1622n which bodhisattva was Crowprince of the kingdom of gan-tuo-shi-li(乾陀戸利,*Gandhasti?), and it is stated that the story is taken from the ou-yhenfeu qi-ta jing(菩薩投身飯餓虎經),which obviously indicates the -sho pu tou-shen yie- qi-t yin-ycn ing(佛説菩薩投身館餓虎起塔因縁 經).however, the jing--yi-xiamg adopts only the latter part of the original text corresponding to T3 〓79,i.e. the stoty of the prince's sacrifice of his body to the tigress.4)according to the recent research made by okano kiyoshi, the prince" s name is karunarenu. See okano, kiyoshi (岡野潔)(2009),"avadanakalpalata chap.97and SMRaM chap.23edition and japanese Translation of yasomitra, vyaghrl, hastin and kacchapa stories" (avadanakalpalata9-97章と iMRa23章-yasomitra, vyaghri, hastin, kacchapaの校訂・和訳-),sout  ssicl studies(南アジア古典学),no.4,pp9-177.5)cf. legge, james(1886),arecordo1 buddhistic kingdoms: beingccount by the chinese monk -hieof his travels inindia and Ceylo search of the buddhist books of discipline, translated and annotated with a corean recension of the chinese text (oxford: clarendo press, reprint, new york: paragor Book reprint co., 1965),p.105.6)cf. legge, op.cit., p.32.here legge also mentions the tigress story in spence hardy's book in fn. 2. cf. fn.10below.7)as for Fa-sheng"s biography and his travel account to india and sri lanka, see ochiai, toshinori(落合俊典)(2001) "shaku hoio sen rekkokuden oboegaki [notes on fa-shen'i go chun]"(釈法盛撰『歴匡 伝』覚書),fs. prof. ishigami zenno(石上善應教授古稀記念論集),tokyo sankibo busshorin, vol. 2, pp.29-43.8)hardy, robert spence(1853),a mamuclofbuddhism in its modern development (london: partridge &amp; oakey, repr. chowkhamba sanskrit studies vol. lvi, varanasi, 1967),pp.91f. cf. von hinuber, oskar(1998),entstehung und aufbau der jataka-samnmlung. studlien literatur des theravad-buddhismsi(stuttugart: franzsteiner, 1998),pp.11 and fns.3and. (The research for this article was supported by the grant-in-aid for scientific research ()no. 21320015 from jSPS) (key words) vyaghrilataka(投身餓虎),sri lanka, gandhara, Fa-xien(法顕),Fa-sheng(法盛) (professor, international college for postgraduate buddhist Studies, ph.d.)  
</root>
