<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies 〓nksemendra's version of the pratihorysutra YaMasakI kazuho 1.Introduction Ksemendra (ca.99-1077a.d.) composed a buddhist narrative work bodhisattvavadang-kalpalato (hereafter av-klp).The fourteenth chapter of this work is devoted to the story of miracles pratiharyasutra, hereafter prsu).1while nakagawa[1982]and okamoto [28. have analyzed and contrasted the versions of the prsu found in the pali canon and tibetan translations, they do not consider ksemendra's version in their study.Focusing on kse-mendra's version ofprsu, thus, this paper aims at showing which versionofprsu ksemen-dra consults in composing his own version ofprsu by comparing ksemendra's versiono1 Prsu and other vetsions. 2.structure of prsuinv-kp Before proceeding to the central argument, it will be useful to outline the narrative vents within ksemendra's prsu in sixty-one verses of the av-klp. the elements of prsu 〓v-klp are as follows: (a) introductory verse (v.1) (b)heretics feel jealousy toward the buddha who is in high favor with king bimbisara and are possessed by mara. (vv.2-6 (c)the heretics ask the permission of king bimbisara to conduct a contest of miracles against the Buddha, king bimbisara refuses it. (vv.7-9) (d) the heretics ask the permission of king prasenajit to conduct the contest, king prasenajit grants it and asks the buddha to take part in the contest. (vv.10-28) (e) the story of prince kala. (vv.29- (f)king prasenajit builds a hall for the contest of miracles. (v.41) (g)the miracle of the buddha causes a kalpa-tree to shoot from the earth. (v.42) (h)the buddha emits a brilliant light from his body. (vv.43-46) (〓)the miracle of the buddha causes lotus-flowers to shoot from the earth and creates buddhas.  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 〓 ksemendra's version of the pratiharyasutra (k. yaasaki (vv.4-) 〓)gods praise the buddha. (vv.5-51) k) The buddha preaches the law. (vv.5-54) (1)audiences give up the false notion ofpersonality. (v.55) m) the heretics are overwhelmed by the power of the buddha's miracles and cannot work any miracle. (v. 56) (n)Yaksa raises up the wind by which the heretics are swept away. (v.57) o) The buddha preaches that people should take refuge in the buddha, dharma, and saiga. (vv 〓8-59) p) the buddha converts the heretics and goes back to rajagrha. (vv.60-61) 3.classificationof prsu versions The versions ofprsu which i have taken into consideration are as follows: ・divyavadana, chap.1pratiharyasutra (ivy) ca.1oth century a. ・' phreng tshegs kyi gzhi (tib),translated by vidyakaraprabha, dharmasribhadra, dpal byor [ca.8-9th century a. リ〓-pen-shuhe-y-pi-nai-ye-a-shih(根本説一切有部毘奈耶雑事),vol.26 translated by i-ching(義淨)[710a.d.6 ●hsien-yi-ching(賢愚經),vol.2, chap.14chiamg-liu-sih-piin(降六師品),translated by hui-chueh(慧覚)[445a.d. ・s-i(四分律),vol.51, translated by budchayasas(佛陀耶舎)[408a.d.8 ・〓o-en-hsing-ching(佛本行經),vol.4, chap.2tai-shen-pien-pitin(大神變品),translated by pao-yun(寶雲)[42.d. ・〓-chii-p-y-ching(法句譬喩經),chap.3-y-piin(地獄品),translated by Fa-chui and Fa-li(法炬,法立)[209-30a.d. Fa-li(法炬,法立)[209-3.) jatak#arabhamigaiatak ・dhammapadatthakatha yamakappatihariyavatthu [a.4.d.2) These versions are classified into two basic groups. MSV group  the texts which pertain to the Mulasarvastivada tradition) and non-MSv group. nakagawa[1982]has already pointed out that the versions of prsuindivy, tib and ke-en-shuo-ji-chieh-y-p-p-nai-yeh-fs-shih have nearly the same elements. They form the mSV group. Elementsj,1) and (o)i ksemendra's text, as previously out-lined, are shared by other versions in the MSV group. while,〓and (m are also common to the non-mSV group, (e)(divy153.22-155.12,5 <ref><canon>T</canon><w>3325</w></ref>),(1),331c1-17),13)and (o(divy1-d36  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies o ksemendra's version of the pratiharyasutra (k. yaasaki)(3 P4-49,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>3331</w>-<v>10</v></ref>) are peculiar to the mSv group. we should specifically note with regard to element (b) (divy14914d P37b2-,3295-329b19) .The pali versions ofprsu and prsu in the ssu- contain a reference both to the buddha who forbids his disciples to use their miraculous powers jatak10-23,dhammaapadutthakatha 〓03.13-204,--b19711) and to the monk pindola-bharadvaja who gets〓 wooden bowlby using his miraculous power, they do not contain areference to mara. ・psu in the hsien-yii-ching, in which the buddha works miracles in front of king bimbisara (<ref><canon>T</canon><p>361</p><c>b</c><l>2</l>-<l>5</l></ref>),and prsu in the fo-pen-hsing-ching, in which the heretics who vainly boast of their knowledge harbor enmity toward the buddha (246,contain a reference to mara (hsien-y-ching t3c17-361b2,o-p-hsing-ching 4-14). ・prsu in the -chii-p-ching does not contains a feference to mara but to the heretics who feel jealousy toward the buddha (52-6). what is immediately apparent is that both ksemendra's version and the versions in the MSV group refer both to heretics and mara. This fact strongly suggests that ksemendra consults prsu transmitted in the mulasarvastivada sectin composing his version of prsu. 4.discrepancies betweenprsuinMSV and prsuinav-klp as shown above, ksemendra's version of prsu and the versions in the mSv group have many common elements. however, there are narrative elements that appear in mSV group versions that are not included in ksemendra's version: (〓)enumeration of Tathagatas' obligations. (divy15015-26-77,329c26- 330a2) (〓)the buddha recollects that the past buddhas worked miracles. (divy1722-5,d7-3; P78,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>333</w>-<v>4</v></ref>) (〓)heretics seek help from their allies. (divy151.19-153,33a9- 330b14) (〓)disciples of the buddha offer to take part in the contest against the heretics. (divy 159.20-16018,4,8,33c27-332a13) (〓)the buddha works the twin miracle yamakapratiharya).(divy 16-7-5, 〓,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>3321</w>-<v>26</v></ref>) (〓)purana meets an eunuch, disciples of purana meet an harlot. (divy1-16, 165.16-166,d52-533,573-7,5b5-8,3327-333b13,333b23-333c8) (〓)purana commits suicide. (divy157-8,t3b13-14) ksemendra's version omits outright elements), however with regard to elements  The japanese associationof Indian and buddhist studies 〓ksemendra's versionof the prutihoryasutra (. YaasakI) (〓v) the following substitutions are noted .instead of element (v), ksemendra's version of prsu has element (g), which is foundin the Pali versions jataka28-265, dhammapadatthakatha18-207.14) and in the ver-sions in the hsien-yi-chingc8-11) and the ssu--495-7).14) ・instead of elements (), ksemendra's version has element (p), which is found in he version in the Fo-pen-hsing-ching (c21).上 we can see that in his version of prsu, ksemendra omits the elements which the versions of the mSV group commonly have and that he replaces elementsv) with elements found in the versions of prsu in the non-mSV group. it is significant that kse-mendra is familiar with the prsu transmitted by the versions of the non-mSV group. it is not unusual for ksemendra to embellish his retelling of stories transmitted in the the mula-sarvastivada sect with stoty elements derived in consultation with non-MSv versions, which is seen in other chapters ofav-klp.1 5.conclusion (1)ksemendra's version of prsu contains a majority of elements which are common to the versions in the MSV group. This shows that ksemendra consults the prsu transmitted in the mulasarvastivada sect. (2)however, ksemendra's version of prsu contains a few elements which are not found in the versions of the mSV group or contains elements which have been re-placed with non-mSv elements. (3)the main source of ksemendra's version of prsu is undoubtedly the prsu trans-mitted in the mulasarvastivada sect. but it is important to note that ksemendra is aware ofprsu as narrated in the versions of the non-mSV group. ksemendra does not intend simply to rewrite prsu transmitted in the mulasarvastivada sect. asa poet, he is takes liberty to make his story more compelling through narrative em-bellishments of non-mSV origin. *My special thanks are due to dr. david mellins for correcting my english and giving many sug-restions. i also wish to thank professor kiyoshi okano for providing me the copy of the tibetan  lock print of the fifth dalai lama (Tohoku#7034). Notes 1)S. ch. das &amp; vidyabhusana, eds., "pratiharyavadana,"iadana kapalato, (calcutta,  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies 1888).1:4429.see also J. w. de jong, "notes on the text of the bodhisattvavadanakalpala-ta pallavas 7-9and1-okke bunk kenkyu(1996)26-28. 2)see masanori nakagawa, "shaeijo jimpen setsuwa" 〓pratiharyasutra) , jjournalof indiam 〓d bucdhist studies6(1982)657-658, kensuke okamoto, "shaeijo ni okeru ikyoto to but-sudeshi shariputra no arasoi" (The contest between sariputra and heretics at sravasti ), (papel presented at the fifteenth conference of the history of indian thought, kyoto, decembei 〓008). 3)the following meters are usedinsu inv-klp:anustubh,4sanzas74%);vasantati. laka,15stanzas2%),malini, 1 sanz (%),sardulavikrudita, 2 sanzas.28%).of the anustubh stanzas: pathya,68 half-stanzas(79.07%);na-vipula, 9 half-stanzas47%); ma-vipulhalf-stanzas(%),bha-vipula, 5 half-stanzas(81%).it may be worth point-ing out, in passing, that ksemendra uses a considerable amount of vipuia half-stanza to compose his version of prsu. in the kumarasambhava (wiesbaden, 1980), kalidasa uses 3vipula half-stanzas(1026%). 4)c. b. cowell &amp; r. a. Neil, eds., "pratiharyasutra" ihe dyovadana, (cambridge,1886). 143-166. The date of divy has not been fixed. according to hiraoka, divy is dated around the eleventh century a.d. (satoshi hiraoka, setsuwa mo kokogakurchaeology of narrative), (tokyo,2002),135-139).however, as bongard-levin &amp; volkova points out, a few stanzas of Av-klp are incorporated into the text of divy. we may say that divy is dated around the end of the eleventh century a.d(G. m. bongard-levin &amp;o.f. volkova, "The kunala legend and a unpublished asokavadanamala manuscript, indicm studies st present5(1963)117). 5)d#6,41-5b5,井1035,37a8-0b2 6)〓145329a1-3 7)202,a10. 8)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>井</v><w>14289413</w>-<p>952</p><c>b</c><l>15</l></ref>. 9)+19327-87a3. 10)〓211,5959c18. 11)v. fausboll, ed., " Sarabhamigajataka"ihe jatondon,1879),263-275. 12)helmer smith, ed., yamakappatiharyiyavatthu,"ithe commentayo the dhammapad3 (london,1925),199-230. 13)This element is not foundisuidivy. 14)This fact has been pointed out by okamoto []. 15)this fact has also been pointed out by okamoto[2]. 16)see m. cone &amp; r. gombridge, the perfect generosiyofprince kessontora. (oxford,1977), xxxix. (key words)pratihoryasutra, divyavadana, mulasarvastivadavinaya, bodhisattvavadanakal-palata, ksemendra (Graduate student, hiroshima university)  
</root>
