<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 〓n the praise of the21Taras in the ariai cave temple Yamaguchi Nariko The ariai cave temple is located on the ordos plateau in westein inner mongolia, chi-na. The temple, which is thought to have been built at some time during the bei-wei(北魏) to ming(明)eras, consists of three parts: sumetu arjai (the arjai having a temple), yeke ar-jai (the large arjai) and ba ariai (the small arjai).among them, Sumetui arjai is the mos1 esearched. for generations, the lords of the temple have been called 'delub qutuptu', which is the mongolian name for telopa (Skt. tailikapada).as this title indicates, the tem-ple belongs to the bka' brgyud pa sect, which has heldaminor position in mongolia). on the inner walls of the temple3 ) , more specifically on the western and eastern walls of cave no.32, we can see the icons of the21taras4) and the texts in praise of them writ-en in three languages: Sanskrit, which is spelled out in lantsa characters, tibetan and lassical mongolian. in regard to the mongolian text, Yang (2008)has transcribed and compared it with the text from a wood block print made i13(hereafter referred to simply as143")i bejjing.13is also a polyglot text, and its original is said to date back to the uan(元)era)we can see sanskrit, tibetan, classical mongolian and classical Chinese versions in praise of the21Taras, as well as icons for each of them (see figure 1 for an example). Thanks to the work of Yang (2008), the Mongolian text on the walls and that of11 mre now available for study. however, the sanskrit and tibetan texts have vet to be tran-scribed and published, and Yang (2008) makes no mention of the praise contained in the Mongolian kanjur).given this background, this paper reports on the comparison of a11 of the texts on the walls with those of1as well as the textin the kaniur, and then discusses an issue pertaining to the correspondence between the texts and the icons Praise andicons of the 21Taras he entire inside of cave no.32, including the ceiling and floor, shows severe peeling,  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies 〓n the praise of the 21Taras in the ariai cave temple (n. yamguchi) with the eastern and western walls barely keeping their surfaces. as shown i Figure 2, each tara icon is drawn within a square formed with bold lines. on these "frames' is placed the polyglot text (Figure 3).the main tara (the green tara) to the 7th tara appear on the western wall. and the 9th to the 17tharas on the eastern wal1 Now, taking some parts of the polyglot text on the walls as examples, i will compare them with the 143and kaniur texts. the parts marked by underline are the texts seen o the walls9). Skt.mong. Mong. m namos tare tuye vire tuittare bhayunasane (〓usane) ture srvarthaddtore svahakore pomotンオ puiban cay-un burqed-un uilesi bitiigegci dar-a cke (noku) d-iyen iren soyurqu/ namo stnte /purban cy-un burqad-un uilesi butigegci These texts are found around the ico of the main tara on the westetn wall. where inost of the tibetan texts pertaining to it have been lost. The beginning part of the sanskrit text is in praise of the main tara and corresponds to the text of143on the other hand, the mon gollian text does not correspond, this is not even in praise, but is an 'invitation' which is used to invite the goddesses into a offering place, and is very similar to the beginning of a manuscript text which is in the private collections iordos and a classical chinese text which is contained in the taisho-daizokyou, as yang08)has already pointed out). around the icon of the 1s tara, which is positioned next to the main tara, the mongo-lan invitation' continues. These sentences are similar to those appearing in the ordos and  lassical Chinese texts the other hand, the Sanskrit text is the praise of the ls tara, which matches the icon drawn. Then, where is the mongollian praise of the main tara? we can find it beside the 〓 Tara's icon with the Sanskrit praise of her. Skt. Mong. namah stasaraccandrasampurnapatalanane aum morgummu tari bayatur arasahasranikaraprahcsatkiranoijvale  uttari ada tudpar gegeken bolyayci/ uri qamuy kuisel dar-a eke-dur suvaha usiiy-tur bimaptan morguimu morgumu f From this point on, we find that each mongolian text has shifted by two icons, for ex-ample, the praise of the〓 Tara is placed beside the 〓h tara, the praise of the4tara is beside the dh Tara, and so on. for the sake of brevity, i will omit the details for each icon on the western wall and will instead provide some examples from the eastern wall. on this  The japanese associationof Indian and buddhist studies onthe praise of the2 taras in the ariai cave temple (n. yamaguch)( wall, most of the sanskrit texts have been lost, but the tibetan and mongolian texts are still available. here, again, the mongollian texts show similar discrepancy. for example, Tib. Mong. phyag 'tshal dkon mchog gsum mtshon phyag morgumu tarad kemeged bad kemekui-ber rgya'i sor mos thugs khar lkar」 rnam pal cinatus-un jasal-i masi-da ebdegci brgyan ma/ [〓inatus-un onisutu kurduin-imasi-da daruyci] ma lus phyogs kyi 'khor lo mrgyan'khor barayun quriyan jegun jiigsen kol-iyer daruju os brgyan] pa'i rang gi 'od kyi tshogs rnams sitamal yal kuirulgekuii masida badarayci-ta ikhrug ma Unlike the Mongolian texts, the sanskrit and tibetan texts a11 correspond to each other, as in the example that follows, Skt. tamas turapadaghatahu m karakorabiite / phyag 'tshal tu re [tu re'i]zhabs ni brtabs pas merumandarakailasabhuvanatrayaculini 7 hum girnam pa'i sa bon nyid ma/ ri rab mandara [mandara] dang 'bigs byed (7 Tib. ig rten gsum rnams g-yo banyid ma7 This discrepancy between the mongolian text and the icons and other texts is entirely due to it beginning with the "invitation'. following this review of the mongolian texts, it is clear that the text on the walls corresponds closely to that of14but not that of the kan-jur. Conclusion acomparison between the different texts andicons pertaining to the2taras has beer made. This comparison has revealed some discrepancies regarding the mongolian text on the walls, which leaves us with some questions that remain to be answered. in addition, presenting the transcriptions of the full texts with the icons is a task for the future. as a final remark, the description of the mongolian text on the wall is more similar to that of143than to that of the kanjur which was printed in the ch'ing(清)era. The sec-ond line of the7praise is perhaps the best example of this among the examples of texts presented in this paper. in addition, the original of1431was made in the yuan era. These facts indicate that the text in the cave could be based on the text which had been available during the period from the yuan to the ming eras.  The japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 〓n the praise of the2 Taras in the arjai cave temple (n. yaMaguchI) (figure 1) (figure 2) 1)for further information on the arjai cave temple, see haiyin yang, historiclthropolog. ical studies on the arjai caves, ordos, mongolia, fukyo-sya, 28. this work refers to the cave temple's construction, historical legends, the excavated mongolian texts among other aspects. as for the unearthed tibetan texts, see naomi sato, 〓preliminary report on the investigation of the unearthed tibetan documents from the ariai grotto" , journol ofindicn d buddhisf std-ies5(1)(2007), pp.. 2)Yang (08),pp.1-51. 3)the arjai cave temple has 66caves, and the icons and the praises ofthe taras are on the walls of cave no.32i sumeti arjai. see yang (08),p.21ff 4)as widely known, tara is a goddess/a female buddha who is very popular in tibetan an Mongolian buddhism. the worship of her seems to date from about the oth century in india, where she was regarded as the consort of avalokitesvara. She has several forms, of which  the white tara' and "the green tara' are well known. The 21taras have evolved from the green Tara. see l.a. waddel, 〓The indian buddhist cult of avalokita and his consort Tara The sav-iouress  illustrated fromremains in magadha', 〓2(894),pp.51-89. 5)this work was made in the age of the sth emperor of the ming dynasty, xuan-70ng(宣宗) The original seems to have been made in the yuan()era. see h. karmay, eorby o-tibeton art, worminster,1975,p, yang 8)p.87ff. Yang 208)has already shown the com-parison of the text on the wall with the text of1431,as well as with the ordos manuscript text which is mentioned belowiootnote 10. 6)ilain tegiis nogcigsen eke deke-yi iineker tuyulum burqad ber maptamn nomlaysan. (Se lokesh chandra (ed.), mongoli kaniur vol.5),new delhi,1973,folio no.117) 7)before presenting this paper, i briefly reported on the Sanskrit and tibetan texts of the cave at the international conference oriai grotto which was heldin september8.(nariko yama-guchi, 〓areport on the manuscripts and the writings on the wall paintings ofthe ajai grotto", collectionoapers, inner mongolia academy of social sciences, arjai grotto academy ir otog banner, 〓8,pp.5.) 8)due to partial peeling, not a11 of the icons and texts can be seen. in regard to the texts, almost  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies onthe praise of the2 taras in the ariai cave temple (n. yamaguchi)(15 〓 half have been lost. onthe earstetn wall a11 the sanskrit text has peeled off except for the 17th'と and the tibetan texts and monglian texts are also barely available. on the western wall, almost a11 the tibetan texts have been lost except the 4th's, although the sanskrit and mongolian tex1 are still available. the mongolian texts are in good comparatively condition, although the 4th's and17ths have been lost. 9)the transcriptions of the text are from1,but the shaded parts are the words not present in 1431, which actually exist on the walls. The mongolian transcriptions ate basically taken from Yang (8).concerning the use of brackets: [].in the mongolian text, this indicates the the description in the text of the mongolian kan-iur, whichi have newly added here in this paper, while in the tibetan text, this indicates the words foundin the text which is contained in the tibetan bk'a'gyur (bcol's m sgrol ma la yomg dgpar'dsp'i samgs rgs bstodp gsungs pa.[77]). (&gt;… indicates more suitable spellings. 10)the ordos text begins as follows, om budalan-u erkim manglai-yin orun-a noyupan dam-un uisug-ece qubilan abida-bar teriguin-ben cimegsen/ yurban cay-u burqad nar-un olii dhar-a eke-nugud selte iredgun or more details, see haiying yang (ed), mamuscripts forivate col-lections iordus, mongolic(),koln,20, pp.117-126,as well as haiying yang, historical-anthropological studies ongolicnuscripts, discovered fom the ariai cane, ordos, Inner mongolia, grant-i-aid for Scientific research (c(2),jSPs005)p.117and Yang (〓008),p.97.) The corresponding part of the classical chinese text sheng jiudtfomu ershiyizhong lizaniing(聖 救度佛母二十一種禮讃經[<ref><canon>T</canon><w>11</w></ref>)is as follows,波答拉勝境緑色答麻字生三世佛 業母頂嚴無量光祈並眷属臨. 1)the ordos text is, tngri ba asuris-un titim-yi qoyar kol-ben lingqub-a-dur bikilgen/qamuy ele uigeyiguin-i deyiluigci getulgegci eke-dur bi morgimu/ The classical chinese text is,諸天非天頂耆嚴恭敬跪捧兩足蓮度諸窮苦中之母致禮 救度佛母前. (key words) inner mongolia, arjai cave temple / grotto,21 taras, polyglot text (part-time lecturer, osaka university)  
</root>
