<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies A study of Sjieyi四解依in the anbam shouyi jing <ref><canon>T</canon><w>602</w></ref> and the Newly-Found kongo-ji anban shouyi jing HunG hung-lung Introduction previously  journal of indicm ad buddhist studies#118) i have discussed the issue of the "sijieyi四解依,four abilities of unhindered understanding and expression cuh-pra-tisamvid)"(hereafter cp) in the newly-found nbm shouyi jing"(hereafter k-bSyj),and the relationship between k-abSYj and yinchiru jig (hereinafter ycrj).In what follows we are going to fully analyze the possibility of a cotresponding relationship between K-abSYj and taisho tripitaka no.oshuo d anb shoupyi fing (hereinafter dbSYj) regarding "p", and interpret their meanings what buddhist system do the cPbelong to? In the pali language systemof Theravada buddhism, whether in the scriptures of Sutra or abhidharma, the cpalways appearin the sequence of yi・ fa・ ci・ bian(義・法・詞・辯). In the chinese language system of the Mahayana, they also appear in the sequence of義・ 法・詞・辯,but such a sequence is found only in a very few scriptures of Sutra. in ma-hayana abhidharma, they always appearin the sequence of fa . yi・ci・ bian(法・義・詞 辯).based on this rule of thumb, we can infer that the "p" belongs to the mahayana trip-itaka system. does dbSYJ really correspond with k-bSYj? The paragraphs that cover "are not very distinctive inbsYj, but through the comparison with k-bSYj. we still cn see that there exists a certain cotresponding rela-tionship between these two scriptures. From the text sequences in these two scriptures, we 〓n learn that there exist cotresponding relationships amnong the four paragraphs of "- matha-vipassana止觀""yatha va suriyo uddyamto譬如日出"" viia-vimutti明解〓",and  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies Astudyof siieyi四解依inthe anba shouyi jig <ref><canon>T</canon><w>602</w></ref> athe newly-found kongo-ji bam shouyi jing (H.hunG)(157 "四解依(cp)"as follows. K-bSYjabSYj 止觀219ff～221ff 〓602,p.〓c23～26 譬如日出222ff～223ff <ref><canon>T</canon><w>602</w>,p.<p>169</p><c>a</c><l>4</l>～<l>6</l></ref> 明解〓226ff～230ffno existing 四解依230ff～24ff〓602,p.16a9～b3 as you can see from the above table, there is no paragraph elaborating "ming jie tuo明 解〓"in dbSYj, the corresponding paragraph mainly elaborates "hui jie tuo慧解〓 (pannarimutti)""yi jie tuo意解〓(cetovimutri )" andk畫亦〓〓)(via ca vimutti ca)". we believe that, due to its being a comparatively complicated concept of buddhist practice, an Shigao therefore left out" ming jie tuo明解〓"indbSYj. Analysis the cPink-bSY Firstly, let us analyze the contents of "si jie yi四解依"in k-bsYJ. the four para-graphs are quite distinctive and clearin the original texts. 法解(法無礙解)230ff～232f 利解(義無礙解)233ff～236ff 分別投解(詞無礙解)236ff～239ff 辯才博解(辯無礙解)240f242f Here, let us review the opening text of each paragraph of"四解依".we discover that there exists a fixed pattern of usage, i.e, the issue of the so-called "fixed pattetn sentence" 〓nbSYj, at the beginning of each paragraph, the words "cong di從諦"were used, but ink-bSYj, "biru ying you di彼如應有諦"and "biru you di彼如有諦"have been used 10and17times respectively. from the petakopadesa we can find that the two words "ru you如有"correspond to the pali yathabhuta. the word "di諦"in both"從諦"and"彼 如有請"should bear the same meaning as the word "di諦(ariya-sacca)" of "si di四諦 (cattari ariyasaccani)"therefore there exists a corresponding relationship between"從諦" and"彼如(應)有諦",or we could say that the two words "ru you如有"were omitted when the version was changed from k-abSYj to dabSYj. Firstly, let us analyze the first sentence regarding " fa jie法解"that appears in k-ab- SYj"從世間法行有亦法世間著".in"qi chu san guan jing七處三觀經3)", the corre-sponding word of "shi jian zhe世間著"inpali is bhavoyo).the meaning of the whole  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies 58)astudyof sijieyi四解依inthe anban shouyi jing t602and the newly-found kongo-i abam shouyi fing h. Hung) sentence is: to practice good dharma in the mundane world, and there is also some (non-good) dharma attached to the mundane world. in the ""shi fa fei fa iing是法非法經"trans-lated by  Shigao, the word anudhammacari was translated into "sui fa xing隨法行", therefore we can infer that the term"法行"holds water. Next, let us look at the first sentence regarding"利解"appearing in the second para-graph:"從本生有亦從本因縁著".the meaning of the whole sentence is: evetything aris-es fromconditions, and some are attached to the dharma of interdependent arising. iYcRJ, we can also find the term "ben sheng本生〓)".its counterpart in pali is paticcasamuppa- 〓), which also means interdependent arising. in the ben xiang yi zhi jing本相猗致經" translated by a shigao, we can also find the term ben yin yuan本因縁1)".its counter part in pali is idappacc which means "the conditions of these"" and it means interde pendent arising too. as statedibhidharmamahovibhcsasastra阿毘達磨大毘婆沙論(hereinafter dppsL) "宣説縁性縁起等理…是勝義諦9)"(In his teaching, buddha preached the principle of "the con. ditions and interdependent arising etc…. " it is within the domain ofultimate truth), we cn learn that the contents of "li iie利解"belong to the ultimate reality (paramartha). frombhidharmamyayamusarasastra阿毘達磨順正理論(hereinafter SZL)又達世 俗勝義二諦。名初二無礙解10)meant "reaching to the worldly reality and ultimate reali-ty"", which is called the initial two unhindered understandings. clearly understanding the worldly reality and ultimate reality is the so-called unhindered understanding of dharme and its internal meaning, we can learn that "fa jie法解"means worldly reality, while "li iie利解"means "interpreting ultimate reality",allinall, the "fa jie法解"and "li jie利解 in k-abSYjis corresponding to "unhindered understanding of dharma法無礙解(aharmg. pratisamvid)"(hereafter dp) and "unhindered understanding of the internal meaning義無礙 解(artha-pratisamvid)"(hereafter ap) of the cpmentionedinabhidharma. the "fen bie tou ie分別投解"and"已若有名・解知是法・…如有投説(if the name is designated, and we lso understand its meaning. we then can explain it to others by verbal or written language when nec-ssary)"are equivalent to"既正知名次尋其義11)"as mentioned in SZL. the sentence 正知義已欲為他説means "once we accurately leamn its name and form, we then have tc find out what is the ultimate reality lying behind it. after we gain the true understanding, we will feel like to let other people know through verbal or written languages". the tem tou shuo投説"means explaining to others. Therefore this paragraph is referring to"詞無  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhiststudies ystudy ofstjieyi四解依inthe amban shouri jig t602andthe newly-found kongoji anbamshouyijing (h. hung)(1 礙解unhindered understanding of terms (nirukti-pratisamvid)"(hereafter np). In the fourth paragraph"辯才博解"in k-absYj, we can find the text"從慧慧知・慧 慧成・從慧慧解".from the text"三智即前三無礙解・即縁三種無巽礙智・名第四無 凝解12)(the three wisdoms are refeming to the first three wisdoms of unobstructed understanding, and based on the first three unobstructed understandings the wisdom thus established is called the fourth unobstructed understanding) mentionedin SZll. we can learn that the"畫慧知・慧慧 成・慧慧解"in k-bSYj is equivalent to the first three unobstructed understandings that give rise to the "unhindered understanding of explanation (pratibhana-pratisamvid)"(hereaf-ter pp),in other words, the wisdom ofpp contains three parts of wisdoms. they are the wisdom of understanding the wisdom of dp, the wisdom of achieving the wisdom ofp and the wisdom of comprehending the wisdom of np. Therefore it is obvious that the con-tent coveredin this paragraph is about pp. Comparison of the cPbetween k-bSYj and dbSY. 〓 Based on the sequence of texts, dabSYj cn be divided into five major paragraphs. The first13) and the third paragraphs14)are equivalent to"法解"(dp) that interpret k-ab- SYj. the second paragraphis equivalent to"利解"(ap). but the sentence"法正者謂 道法"in the second paragraph belongs to the contents of the first paragraph. the fourth par-agraph)is equivalent to"辯才博解"(pp).the fifth paragraphis equivalent to分別 投解"(np) .following table shows the corresponding relationship between k-bSYj and 〓abSYj regarding "p". 四解依(四無礙解cp)k-abSYjbSY 法解(法無礙解dp)230ff～232ff〓602,p.16a1;169a19-22 利解(義無礙解ap)233ff～236ff〓602,p.16 分別投解(詞無礙解np)236ff～239ff 〓602,p.161-3 靜才博解(辯無礙解pp)924～242〓602,p.16a22-b1 First let us try to understand the term〓法解"(dp)ibSYj. we can approach this issue from the keywords"念法","意著","法中",and"所念".the term"念法mindful-ness of the dharma" is referring to道(buddhism dao) that meditates on the inner dharma (the pure dhama of the mind) or"萬物a11 phenomena" that meditate o outer phenomena (material desire). the term"意著18)"means "rest your mind upon","法中"means"道法 〓19)(following the dharma of dao)"or "mindful of the dao (mindful or thinking of the way to  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies 0)astudyofsjieyi四解依inthe anbam shouyi jing t2and the newly-found kongo-i abun shoui ing h. hunG ultimate reality)". thoughin a broad sense"所念"means the obiect that the mind thinks of, here it means"有所念the things that one thinks of".however in bSYj,"有所念the things that one thinks of" bears a negative implication. e.g."有所念為罪〓0),itis a fault if one's mind is being held up by any kind of object". therefore"意著法中"means to rest vour mind upon the places that are in association with buddhism dao, while"意著所念" belongs to the dharma of cyclic birth and death which is not in association with buddhism dao. in any event, the text"世間法行…法世間著"in k-bSYJ bears a corresponding re-lationship with the text"意著法中…意著所念"indbSYJ. it is very likely that an Shi-gao made use of the word"意"from the dabSYj sutra's title"安般守意"to replace the term"世間"ink-bSYj. in doing so, he made the passage easier to explain. Next, let us examine the contents of"利解"(ap)ibSYJ. The keywords in the text are"本起・本著意".we can also fnd the term"本從起〓1)"iYcRJ. we can learn frometakopadesa that it bears the same meaning as"本起"。its pali countetpart is patic-casamuppada, which also means arising from conditions. The term"著意〓a)means that your mind is attached to something. Therefore we can say that the phrase"本生…本因縁 著"ink-bSYj was originally coiresponding with the phrase"本起…本著意"inda SY. They both indicate " the dharma of dependent arising. attached to the dharma of de-pendent arising縁起法…於縁起法而起執著".but during the eastemm hn dynasty when Buddhism was initially introduced to china, it would be a big challenge to talk directly about"縁起法the dharma of dependent arising". Therefore an Shigao resorted to a sim-pler way, and he replaced the term"縁起dependent arising"" with〓心"or"意",both mean emind". The statement"皆本從意起・便著意・便有五陰・所起意當斷・斷本・五陰便斷7 neant: "ll the occurrences of cyclic birth and death originate from the mind. due to the atachment of the mind, the five aggregates arise. Therefore we should eradicate a11 the thoughts of the mind. if we can eradicate the root of the deluded mind, the five aggregates can also be eradicated."" Such interpretations not only meet the uppermost principle of"守 意"as the title"安般守意"indicates, but also avoid the trouble of interpreting the tern "dependent arising". Nnow let us examine the paragraph regarding"分別投解"inabSYj. this paragraph 〓 is comparatively short, and its contents have a close relationship with y).if we com-pare k-abSYJ with dabSYj, we can also find there exist the corresponding terms and  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies astudyof stilieyi四解依inthe anban shomyi jing t602andthe newly-found kongo-j amban shonyi jing (H. hung)(161 phrase regarding"分別投解"between these two scriptures. The word"正"here refers to sammapanna, i.e."正智"-in other words, the totally correct wisdoms. therefore we can see that this paragraphin bsYjis to serve the purpose of explaining"分別投解"ink-ab- SYJ. 〓abSYjK-abSY 見陰受可見若陰 見〓受 有入若入 正者若從正 The meaning of suo ・ben・ zheng(所・本・正)of dbsY Finally let us examine the paragraph that concerning"辯才博解"(pp). we can tell the main significance of this paragraph from the following two terms."所本正"and"道説". From dbSYj and k-bSYj we can see that"所本正"actually represents the three con-cepts of"法解""利解"and"分別投解".the following table shows their corresponding relationship: 〓bSYk-abSY 所瓩念・所行・所起意所在 本本起・本著意・斷本本生・本因縁〓 正受正・自正・正心從正 Though there are some explanations according to whichn Shigao was making use of Taoist concepts (ge-yi格義)in interpreting the meaning of the original text in k-bSY and its counterpartinbSYj, from the table above we can see that each of the three words"所・本・正"represents the contents ofthe three paragraphs which are concerning "法解"(dp),"利解"(ap) and"分別投解"(nP)in sequence respectively. it is the same as the contents of the fourth paragraph"辯才博解"(pp)of k-bsYj. inside the辯才博 解paragraph, the three terms of慧慧知・慧慧成・慧慧解mean the first three unhin-dered understanding. as mentioned, the wisdoms of the first three unobstructed understand-ings give rise to the wisdom of*辯無礙解"(pp). this shows that the paragraph of"所本 正"is elaborating the contents of pp. moreover, in the paragraph of"辯才博解"indab. SYj, there is another term"道説",which can be traced to the phrase"辯無礙解縁道及 〓24)indpsl. the original meaning ofc道及説"is that, no matter what kind of situa tion, the ppis always in association with meditation and wisdom. and thus the unhindered  the japanese sociationof Indian and buddhist studies 2)astudyofstjieyi四解依inthe anbam shouyi ing T2 andthe newly-found kongo-iiabam shonyi ig . hung) rhetorical abilities are gained. together with the evidence of*所本正"and"道説",it clearly demonstrates that this paragraph fromdbSYj is actually interpreting the meaning of the Pp. Conclusion The discussions of"四解依"appearing in k-abSYj and dabSYj are both very diffi-cult to understand. but from understanding of the doctrine of "catuh-pratisamvid" as elab-orated inabhidharma and the fesults of the keyword analysis for these two scriptures, an obvious corresponding relationship between the two scriptures can be shown. That is to say: the contents of p"ibSYJ are actually used to interpret the original text of"四 解依"ink-abSYJ. Though  Shigao adopted some explanations that employed taoist concepts(格義)to let the people of his time gain a better understanding, we still cn see that the original structure ofpiabSYjis almost identical to that of k-abSYj. This allows us to be more certain that both k-abSYJ and dabSYJ are works by  Shigao, and that the relationship between them also represents the relationship between"小安般 經"and"大安般經". Due to the limited space. the footnotes are deleted) &lt;Key words) n Shigao, anban shouyi jing, sijieyi四解依,abhidharma assistant Prof.. dharma drum buddhist college, taIwanN)  
</root>
