<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies Background to the compilation of Chapter iV of the aiotasatrukaukrtyavinodhandsutra: was chapter iv originally a Separate text?* Mryaki Tensho 1.introduction little attention has been given to the process and background of compiling the ajutasatru-kaukytyavinodhanasutrkv), with the exception of the study of chapter ii.chapte 〓 for the most part corresponds to the fongbo jing放鉢経(〓bj,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>629</w></ref>),as the chinese catalogues tell us. previous studies agree unanimously that ch.ii was originally a sepa-rate text that was subsequently added to the ak3) however, no studies have clarified the process by which the other sections of the aikv were compiled, probably because there is no clear evidence like that of the fbj available. In this paper i propose that ch.iv4),too, seems to be originally an independent text and to have been assembled into the aikv,as ch.iii was. in order to confirm this, we examine the following points: first, the content and the context of ch. iv, second, the difference and the inconsistency of the characters inch. iv. and third, the "vestige' of a separate text in the chinese translations of the aikv. 2.content and context of ch.ivof the aikl First, the content of ch. iv of the aikv. summarized as followed, confirms that the plot is almost self-contained. Sakyamuni tells sariputra of their previous life in order to show that one who wants to attain *nipvana as fast as possible should aim for enlightenment(*amuttarasomyaksambodhi) rather than enter the * sravakayana. The previous day when three children were playing on the road, the past Buddha* sarvabhibhavana came begging with his disciples and followers. one of the three children who made an offering to the past buddha is sakyamuni, and the other two who made offerings to the great sravakas of those days are sariputra and mahamaudgalyayana. in the last part of this chapter, the great sravakas, such as mahakasyapa, hear the story and grieve that they are inferior to the criminals who comnmitted one of the five most serious crimes(anantarya).  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies background to the compilation of chapter ivof the djatasatrukaukytyavinodhanasutra t. miyazaki) (75) we will now survey the contents of chs. iii and vi order to verify that they have no connection with ch. iv. the previous chapter, ch. ii, tells of manjusri surpassing samodhi and his and sakyamuni's previous life. while ch. iv adjusts the main focus to the argument of the advantage of mahayana over the srovakoyana, ch.ii places it on the emphasis of the absolute superiority of manjusri. it is in ch. v) that the main story of the ajkvbegins, with the appearance of king ajatasatru, whose name composes the title of this sutra and who is one of the main characters. king aiatasatru implores the buddha to relieve him of his remorse(*kaukrtya) for killing his father. butinch. v, his remorse is not in fact relieved by the buddha and Maniusri, and the story continues over successive chapters. So, the chapters before ch. v can be regarded as a prologue to the main stor which begins from ch. v. Judging from the above, the content of Ch. iv of the dikv seems to stand alone and be virtually independent of the previous and subsequent chapters. 3.differences and Inconsistencies in the characters of Ch.〓 The main story ich. iv of the ajkv, dealing with the previous life of sakyamuni and his wo great sravakas, develops through the dialogue between sakyamuni and sariputra as we saw above, and manjusri, who plays important roles in other parts of the akv, never appears. it is in this point that ch. iv differs from the other chapters of the akv. let us move onto the inconsistency of the characters. in ch. iv, *Sagaramati appears as a monk of the past who waits on the past buddha* sarvabhibhavana.o the other hand, 〓nch. i of the v,*sagaramati appears as one of the25bodhisattvas who discuss how*sarvaina is acquired〓.these two characters are obviously not the same person, bu1 both take the same name in the one book. we may assume that this inconsistency of the characters between chs. ivand iis caused by discontinuity between the chapters. 4.the 〓vestige of a Separate Textin the chinese Translations of the aikv Immediately before the great sravakas' grieve at the end of ch. iv, we see corresponding expressions only in the two older chinese translations, the asheshi wamg jing阿闍世王經 〓wj, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>626</w></ref>)and the wenshuzhili puchao sommei jing文殊支利普超三味経(〓p,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>627</w></ref>)9), as illustrated in the following quotations.  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies 76)background to the compilation of chapter iv of the ajatasatrukaukrtyavinodhanasutra (t. miyazaki) aw説摩訓衍品時,萬人悉發阿耨多羅三耶三菩心(t62639-10) 〓p佛時説斯大乘法典,則一萬衆人,發無上正眞道意(〓627417-8) The underlined words, supposedly a translation from*mahoyana-parivarta o *mahayana-sutra, attract our attention in that they appear in the middle of the aikv, rather than at the end of mahayana sutras as is more typical. moreover, no corresponding expressions can be seen in the two newer versions of the ajkv, the akyh、and the wzj. Thus, we can assume that the expressions originally appeared at the end of a separate text, and remained even after it was compiled into the ajkv. as time has gone on, it seems that these expressions were removed in order to improve the cohsistency. in other words, these expressions are the vestiges' of independent text1) This now faises the question of which part of the ajkv these expressions indicate. given that ch.iii is considered to be originally a separate text, as previous studies point out, and that ch. iv has its ow completed stoty and shows differences and inconsistencies between the other chapters, these expressions are most likely to indicate ch. iv as the independent text that was compiled into the ajkv. 5.conclusions from the above examination, itis evident that ch. ivof the dkvwas originally a separate text, and was later compiled into the aikv. in addition, since ch.〓i has been regarded as independent, the two successive chapters of chs. ii and iv might also have existed inde-pendently. Then, how were the preceding chapters, chs I and iicomposedFirst of a11, the main charactors inchs. i and ii, bodhisttva *pratibhanakuta accompanied bybodhisattvas, and their teachings never appear in the other parts. it is therefore safe to say that there is clearly continuity between chs. i and ii but discontinuity between chs. i and i and the other chapters of the aikv. Furthermore, ch. I unfolds with the2bodhisattvas severally expressing their ideas about*sarvaina, the style of which is widely found in other mahayana sutras, such as the vimalakurtinirdesa, Ch. viidvayadharmmamukha-pravesanaparivarta'. therefore it seems more reasonable to suppose that chs. I and ii were appended under the influence of the other mahayana sutras12). *This paper is based on the presentation entitleda study of the compilation of the aikv: with  The japanese association of indian and buddhist studies background to the compilation of chapter ivof the djatasatrukaukytyavinodhanasutra (t. miyazaki)(77. Reference to chapter iv and examples of the word mahayana' in the aikgiven at the58th annual conference of the japanese association of indian and buddhist studies in shikoku university. unfortunately here i have space for no more than the examination of the compiling of ch. iv of the ajkv, which is taken from the first half of the presentation. the remaining part, the analysis of the examples of the word "mahoyana' in the d4jkv, will be written up a pape1 soon. 1)In this paper we borrow the chapter divisions from the wenshuzhili puchao sanmei jing文 殊支利普超三味経(〓p5, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>627</w></ref>)for convenience. however, we can suppose that the chapter divisions in the 〓pj were added at the discretion of the translator, dharmaraksa, because they cannot be seen in the other translations. ch.ii of the akv pno.882kvb mdo tsu- 〓40b, t626392c18-3942,62749-418,62848-43c3.2)the faiing lu 法經録(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>2146</w></ref>),which has the oldest extant description of the fbj, says "the 〓b is another ranslation of the chapter of "throwing a bowl' in the puchao jig."放鉢經一卷右一 經是普超經奉鉢品別譯(t214610a19-20).In fact, the fbjhas content that cannot be seen in the akv.3)harrison, p. [1993"The earliest chinese translations of mahayana buddhist studies: some notes on the works of lokaksema", buddhist studies review,#10-2,pp. 135-277, harrison, p. and hartmann, u. [2ajatasatrukaukrtyavinodhanasutra" mamuscripts in the schoyencllectio, pp.167-284, murakami, S. [1994]ajase-o-kyo"(阿闍世王経), Shin kokuyaku izokyo(新国訳大蔵経),#9-1.4)ch. iv of the ajkv p mdo tsu 24b4-244l, t626343-395b22,〓6274-41416,t62847-43c29.5)ch. v of the 4iv: p mdo tsu1-2487,t626395b23-397a2, 6274417-4b16,t62847c- 138c11.6)4kvb:blo sgros rgya misho(*Sagaramati: p mdo tsu,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>626</w></ref>:沙竭 (395a9),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>627</w></ref>:海意(414a24),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>628</w></ref>:海慧(436b7).7)ch. i of the ajkv: p mdo tsu 220a5-299b7,t626389a7-391b26,t627406b15-409c10,t6284a-431c8.8)ajkvb: blo sgros rgy mtsho(*sagaramati: p mdo tsu5),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>626</w></ref>:海意(390a26-27,cf.沙竭末 (389a21)〓627海意(408a9),<ref><canon>T</canon><w>628</w></ref>海畫(430a1o).9)four complete versions of the ajkv survive: 1. the a626), the oldest chinese trans. by lokaksema(支婁迦識)in the Han漢period, 2. the w627),the second oldest chinese trans. by dharmaraksa(竺法護)in the jin晋period, 3. the djkvnb, translated in the 9th century (no.882), and 4. the weicengyou zhengfa jing未曾有正法經(〓zj, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>628</w></ref>),the newest chinese trans. by fadian(法天)dating from the song宋period (628).10)on the other hand, the expression which is common to only the two older chinese translations of the aikvis one of the examples showing that the aw and the 〓pjjbelong to the same recension. on the recension of the akvs versions, see harrison. p. and hartmann, u.[.11)ch. ii of the akv p mdo tsu7-233l,t626391b27- 392c7, 〓6274c11-418,t62843c9-433c-7.12)from this supposition, we can assums Chs. i-i were added simultaneously with or after the inclusion of ch.iii and ch. ivin the aikv. (key words) djatasatrukaukrpyavinodhanasutra, mahoyana-suitra, mahayana-parivart Graduate student, tokyo university,  
</root>
