<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhiststudies does the newly discovered shou yi  jing originate froman indian-language text or not? Hung hung-lung Introduction The following research paper will present further analysis of the kongo-j anban shonpyi jing, a manuscript that was recently discovered in9, which has been confirmed to be a work of an Shigao(安世高).following conventions, this manuscript will be hereafter referred to as k-aSYj. the k-aSYj most likely is an authentic manuscript, as it is ver closely related to foshuo da ambcn shouyi fing佛説大安般守意經<ref><canon>T</canon><w>602</w></ref>(hereafter referred to as 〓-asY) and xiuxing daodi iigshuxi pin修行道地經<ref><canon>T</canon><w>606</w></ref>數息品=apana Chap. of xXdd (hereafter referred to as xxddac.however, there is a maior question as to whether the k-aSYj was derived froma pali or sanskrit script, or was it created by a later author drawing from different sources? in this paper i shall attempt to answer this question. Both the k-aSYj and the xXddac are very similar in content and in their use of terminology, and strikingly correspond with the terminology of the sattatimsa bodhipak-khika dhamma三十七品經法,the Thitty-seven practices for the attainment of Enlight-enment. These37 practices include cattaro Satipatthana四意止( the four bases of mindful-ness), cattaro sammappadhana四意断(the four proper exertions), cattaro iddhipada四神 足( the four supernatural powers), panca indriyani五根( the five roots), panca balani五力 (the five powers), satta boiihanga七覺意(the seven factors of enlightenment) and attangiko Maggo八行(the eight-fold noble path). In this paper, i will also compare k-asYj and xxddcwith samatha vipassana 止觀(concentration and observation) and cattaro ariyasaccani四諦( the four noble truths).  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhiststudies 138) does the newly discovered shou y jing originate ffom an indian-language textor not? .hung) Four kinds of Satipatthanathree kinds of samadhi 内外身身觀止空定向活 内外痛療痛養觀止不願定向活 内外意意觀止不(思)想定向活 内外法法觀止 The text referring to cattaro satipatthana in the xxddcis very short and concise: qi x xin zhe dang zhi lico zhi, se qi mie chu tong yamg fayi, gucm qi mie ben ch qiyin yian, guoqu dng lai xing wu yuamding其修行者當知了之。色起滅處痛痒法意。觀起滅 本察其因縁。過去當來行無願定1).comparing the content referring to the cattaro sati-patthana of the xxddc and the k-aSYj, the latter is extremely lengthy.The content in the k-asYj is composed of one summary sentence and twelve individual sentences4, which are derived from a combination of the four kinds of Satipatthana and three kinds of samadhi: The four steps of cattaro satipatthana are aiihattabahiddha kaye kayanupassi viharati, ajhattabahiddha vedanasu vedanasupassi viharati, ajihattabahiddha cite cittanupassi viharati and aihattabahiddha ddhammesu dhammanupassi viharati. The three kinds of samadhi are the samadhi of emptiness(空定),the samadhi of aimlessness(無願定)and the samadhi of no-form(無相定).it is most likely an Shigao himself who created this combination, and depicted it in the twelve sentences appearing in the k-asYJ. however, according to da piposha lun大毘婆沙論8),within the samadhi of emptiness and the sa-madhi of aimlessness, each of the four contemplations of cattaro satipatthana are active. Yet, within the samadhi of no-form〓 there is only the activity of the contemplation of dhammesu, dhammanupassi viharati(法念住).therefore, i believe that this was a mis-interpretation by n Shigao, as the xxdd-ac does not include the content as indicated by Shigao in k-asYj. This shows that the paragraphin cattaro satipatthana that an Shigao wrote was notin the original pali or sanskrit sources. cattaro sammappadhana we can compare the contents of both cattaro sammappadhana in k-asYj7 ad xx- 〓d8).There are some differences in the terminology, but the meaning is almost the same in these two texts. K-asYjxxddc ①未生弊悪意法。不復生〓〓未起惡法。則不復生  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhiststudies does the newly discovered shou yi jing originate from an indian-language text or not?h. hung)(139 ②已生弊悪意法。即舍 〓〓諸惡自盡 ③未生清淨法。即生 〓〓未起法念。當使興發 4已生清淨法。便増多有生〓①所興善法。令具足 cattaro idhipada Ccattaro idhipada means the four steps of samadhi, chandasamadhi(欲定),viriyasama-dhi(精進定),cittasamadhi(意定)and vimamsasamadhi(思惟定). The interpretations of cattaro idhipada in k-asY are shown in a more detailed formula in each of the " supernatural powers" than they are in xxdd).but the first part of Cattaro satipatthana, chandasamadhi, contains a more precise explanationixdd- 〓1)than in k-asY2)the content of both texts are as shown below. K-asY xxdc ①如應欲得。〓〓心已如是隨其所欲。 ②是名爲欲。 〓〓是謂自恣。 ③從是欲,所生念一心。 〓〓令志專一。 ④是名爲定。 〓①是謂自在定意。 ⑤彼如是應行相連不中止。→〓從是次第 ⑥有信,有精進,有念,有定,有慧。 〓⑥信,念,精進,觀察護命。 ⑦名爲斷生死。 〓〓是謂為信。思惟其行。 ⑧故説欲定斷生死隨行成神足 〓〓是謂自恣三味專精手道而獲神足 k-asYjxxdd ②是名爲欲。〓〓是謂自恣。 ④是名爲定。〓①是謂自在定意。 ⑧故説欲定斷生死隨行成神足〓①是謂自恣三味專精于道而獲神足 〓ncomparing the usage of terminologies in thetwo paragraphs, we can see that the term ②yu欲(chanda) corresponds to〓zizi自恣,③niom yi xin念一心corresponds to  zhi zhuam yi志專一,and⑤xiang licmzhong zhi相連不中止corresponds to eci di 次第13) but what is the relationship between欲定(chandasamadhi) andg信inxxdd There is very little explanation in the tripitaka, but we can find the term cattaro idhipada mn its original Sanskrit text "sravakabhumi14)", in the paragraph shown below: (1)chanda-samadhi-prahana-samskara-samanvagatasya rddhipadasya,(2)sraddha-virya-citta-mimansa-samadhi-prahata-samskara-samanvagatasya rddhipadasya, (3)virya-citta-mimansa-samadhi-pradhana-samskara-samanvagatasya yddhipadasya xuazang玄奘translated only the following paragraph into chinese : 「四神足者。一欲三摩地斷行成就神足。二勤三摩地斷行成就神足。三心三摩地斷行成就 神足。四觀三摩地斷行成就神足。」(『聲聞地』〓3,.42-5) This paragraph in the chinese translation cotresponds only to the original Sanskrit sen-  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies (140)does the newly discovered  hon  jing originate from an indian-language textor not? h. hung) ences)and(3),as he did not translate sentence (2)into chinese. but sentence (2)contains a very important meaning. Sentence (2)is almost the same as sentence (3), except that it has the prefix "sraddha,"" which means xin信(faith). the sentence (2)has the grammatical usage of tatpurusa in Sanskrit. prefix 〓sraddha"in this sentence keeps the instrument ccse with virya". The meaning of sentence (2)is almost the same as the (〓gof xxddac. The meaning is that when the practitioner has completed his first step of cattaro iddhipada 〓chanda-samadhi-prahana-samskara-samanvagatasya rddhipadasya, although he has not yet completed the other three stepsvirya-citta-mimansa-samadhi-pradhana-samskara-samanvagatasya rddhipadasya, he nevertheless will have had gained the faith to complete the three other steps. So the explanation of chandasamadhi is more precise inxxdc than itis ink-asYJ. Paica indrivani K-aSYjxxddc ①彼如有諦。信。信者不離信意生。 是生意能得隨分別可。念可。可。是名爲信根。 ②身亦念攝持。是名爲精進根 〓〓己獲神足是謂信根 →〓身心堅固。謂精進根 〓〓所可思法。是為意根 〓①其心專一。是謂定根 〓〓能分別法而知所趣。是謂智慧根 ③意生不忘請。是名爲念根 ④一心向行。是名爲定根 ⑤觀。是名爲慧根 The three terms ①sui fen bie ke隨分別可,nicm ke念可,ke可make up the faith Root. They are the same terms as wei sui ke微隨可15),zhong xiang sui ke中相隨可16), and sui ming wei ke隨名爲可1ink-asYj. and they are the outcome of practicing muan 暖xding頂ren忍,the former three steps of the四善根(four good roots). these three steps, retain the same meaning, and are subdivided into nine steps ixxd). the term②shen yi mian身亦念is parallel to〓 shen xin身心ixddc. The term ③di諦means四諦(four noble truths). it parallels the 〓fa法kinxxc. the f neans " dhammanupassi viharati, contemplating things in general as devoid of inherent existence. so the term di is parallel to the term fa. The term④yi xin king一心向has the ame meaning as一向念19)in yinchru jing陰持入經(hereafterycrj), and its original pali ermipetakopadeis "tekaggam cittassa". and o The term qixzhuan yi其心專- is a special term in several works of Zhu fahu竺法護.so the term yi x xiamg parallels the termqi xinzhucn yi.  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies does the newly discovered  shou ki fing originate from an lndian-language textor not? . huno)(141) Panca balani 〓 K-asYjxxddj2 K-asYj1) xxddj-2) ①信。不信不能得壊信。是名爲信力 〓⑤其信温和是謂信力 ②精進。不精進不能得壊精進。是名爲精進力。〓〓精進力 〓〓精進力 〓〓精進力 ③念意。感意23)不能得壊念意。是名爲念力。〓〓意力 ④定意。感意不能得壊定意。是名爲定力。 〓①寂意力 〓①寂意力 ⑤智慧。不慧不能得壊智慧。是名爲畫力。 〓〓智畫力 The use of terminologies of panca balani in k-asYj are almost parallels to that in xxddc. although the sentences in k-aYj are longer than those inxddc, the descriptions are reasonable24) 〓 Satta boiihaiga K-asYjxxd K-aSYJ ①念不忘。是爲念覺種意。 ②觀。是名擇法覺種意。 ③身行亦所念得攝。是名爲精進覺種意 ④從諦足喜。是名爲喜覺種意 ⑤身亦然已念止。是爲止覺種意 ⑥一向念。是名爲定覺種意 ⑦意隨願得觀。是名爲觀覺種意 The zhong yi種意is a term rarely usedi shigao's works. but we can see the term, 〓iom jue zhong yi念覺種意in the notes of Yc).the term hu jne yi護覺意inxxd- 〓c, not only exists in many works of Zhu fahu, but also exists in several works of a Shigao. we can also discover its original pali term, upekkhasamboiihaigo,petako-podesa. we find that Zhu fahu follows the terminological usage of an shigao. The tem 〓in jue yi信覺意is a special term translatedby zhu Fahu onlyto conclude, we can sa) that the terminological usage of satta boijhanga in these two texts are parallel to each other. 〓①能及諸法。則心覺意 〓〓分別諸法。是謂擇求諸法覺意 〓〓身心堅固是謂精進覺意 〓d心懐喜踊得如所欲。是謂欣悦覺意 〓〓身意相依信柔不亂是謂信覺意 〓①其心一寂。是謂定覺意 〓⑨其心見滅婬怒癡垢所志如願。是護覺意 atthangiko maggo K-aSYjxxdd K-aSy ①觀。是名爲直見。 ②至誠計。是名爲直行正計。 ③直身亦念攝制。是名爲正方便治。 〓③設使別觀諸法之義。是謂正見。 〓〓諸所思惟無邪之願。是為正念。 〓⑥身意堅固。是為正方便。  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 142)does the newly discoveredan shou yi jiing originate ffom an indian-language text or not? .hung) 〓直意生念不斷。是名爲直正念意。〓〓心向經義。是為正意 〓d心向經義。是為正意。 ⑤直行一向念。是名爲正定。 〓〓其心專一。是為正定。 The meaning of the three pairs,①〓,③〓,⑤〓,in these two texts are vety similart each other, as they are just like pancindriyani. although the usage of the terminologies differ between the two authors, we can say that the content of these two paragraphs paral-lel each other. except for the above five components of atthangiko maggo, there are three other components. generally speaking, the terms used are right speech(正語),right action (正業)and tight livelihood(正命).but instead of using these three terms, both these texts use three other special terms. They are body, the spoken word, and the mind. They are sel-dom used in the other texts in the tripitaka. the paragraphs in the two texts are as shown below. 〓-asyj28) 8)→上頭三法。三道行。已具足行。何等爲三道。一直〓。直身。三直意。 如是。是得道者八種道。 xxdd-a29) 〓身意造業是三悉淨。爾乃得成八正道行。 〓 Samatha vipassana・ cattaro ariyasaccani The concept of "samathavipassana yuganaddha"" is seldom mentioned in the works of primary chinese buddhism, however both of these texts mention this concept. k-asYj30) 〓Yj30)〓xdd3) 止亦觀雙倶行是觀寂二。如兩馬駕一車乘行 The descriptionof "samathavipassana yuganaddha" follows " cattaro ariyasaccani" di-rectly ink-asYj. The same description also follows "cattaro ariyasaccani"ixddj-ac, but the description fills a long paragraph. however, we can find a similar description in both k-ayj2)and Ycr3) 〓-a→止亦觀雙倶行。行便行知受解34)四諦。一識苦。二舍習。三畫自證。四行道瀘。 C→止觀亦如是。雙隨行。一處一時一意上至意。爲作四事。爲識芒苦相應爲断習習 相應。爲盡自證盡相應。爲行道滿道相應。 we also can find itin the original pali sources ipetakopadesa,as below. evameva samathavipassana yuganaddha vattamana ekakale ..pe.. (ekakkhane ekacitte cattari kiccani karoti, dukkham parinnabhisamayena abhisameti, samudayam pahanabhisamayena ab-hisameti, nirodham sacchikiriyabhisamayena abhisameti, maggam bhavanabhisamayena abhisa-meti.)  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies does the newly discovered  shou i jing originate ffom an lndian-language textor not? h. hung)(143) And we can find the same allegories about si shi四事inboth texts. 〓-asyj36) 36)→譬如日出作四事。一壤冥。爲現明。三爲見色萬物。四成熟萬物。 〓cj37) 止觀亦如是。正雙行。便知受解四諦。一識苦。二舍習。三盡自證。四諦行滿也。 〓止觀雙倶行。一處一時一意。上要至竟。為成四事。譬如日出。上至竟 為現作四事。致明。壞冥。現色。現竟。 The paragraph of Ycrj also has its original pali sources in petakopadesa38) evameva samathavipassana yuganaddha vattamana ekakale ekakkhane ekacitte cattari kiccani karoti, Yatha va suriyo udayanto ekakale apubbam acarimam cattari kiccani karoti, andhakaranr vidhamati, alokam patukaroti, rupam nidassiyati, sitam pariyadiyati : The allegories of the ""sun appearing" and the term "samathavipassana yuganaddha" are seldom mentioned in the theories of anapanasati. Therefore, we can confirm that the para-graph of Samatha vipassana・ cattaro ariyasaccaniin k-asYj was cited fromycRj by 〓n shigao. And we can find the other paragraph indicating two kinds of liberation in k-asYj39 and YRthe meaning of these two paragraphs in both texts is nearly the same. yet, the chinese translation of the latter passage is more readily understandable than the for-mer, as it can be easily returned into its original pali language. therefore, the paragraphin K-asYjis most likely cited fromYcRj. k-asyj41) 〓1→欲愛不復愛。意解得脱。癡解。從解畫得脱 〓42)→貪愛欲不復貪。念意得解脱。癡已解。令從慧得解脱 agaviragam cetovimuttim avijiaviraganca pannavimuttim4) Conclusion after comparing the two texts, k-aSYj and xxdc, we find that they are very simmilarin content to sattatimsa bodhipakkhika dhamma. however, even though the trans-lations by the two authors are based on the same original sources, differences in the usage of terminologies between the two texts still remain. The reason is that the two authors re-tain their strong personal styles. on analyzing the contents of the newly discovered anbon shouyi jing, we can con-clude that the text was written by a Shiago, but is not entirely a direct translation from an original source, such as pali, sanskrit, etc. an Shigao compiled it based on his knowledge of the xxdd's original text. moreover, he utilized his knowledge of abhidharma,  the japanese sociationof Indian and buddhist studies 144)does the newly discovered  b shou yi fing originate from an lndian-language textor not? h. hung) sspecially about anapanasati in writing the text, in addition, quoting some paragraphs from YcRj and adding them to this compiled text. 1)606,p.2187-92)kongo ji issaikyo no kisoteki kenkyu to sinsyutu butten no ken-kyu金剛寺一切経の基礎的研究と新出仏典の研究p.190-191for line number (hereafter ln 2-1583)ln122-1274)n128-1585)「念住者。空無願三摩 地各四念住倶。無相三摩地唯法念住倶。」(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>145</v>,p.<p>539</p>,<c>b</c><l>19</l>-<l>21</l></ref>)6)this theory is also mentionedinapitan pipo sha lun阿毘曇毘婆沙論(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1546</w>,p,<p>-2</p></ref>),shuzheng li lu 順正理論(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1562</w>,p<p>7</p>,<c>c</c><l>3</l>-<l>4</l></ref>)) and zang 〓ig lun藏顯宗論(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1563</w>,p.<p>971</p><c>14</c>- <l>7</l></ref>)ln159-1628)<ref><canon>T</canon><w>606</w>,p.<p>218</p>,<c>18</c>-<c>19</c></ref>)ln164-18410)<ref><canon>T</canon><w>606</w>, p.<p>218</p>,<l>19</l>-<l>25</l></ref>11)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>60</v>,p.<p>218</p>,<c>19</c>-<c>22</c></ref>12)lN164-16713)not only are the isage of the terminologies欲定paragraph in the two texts are parallel to each other, but the other three paragraphs,精進定,意定and思惟定are , as well.(6,p.218,23-25)&amp;n168-181) 14)stbh.,p290,13f-17ff,patna,197315)ln016)ln1417)ln10 18)606,p.217,8-1019)〓603,p.176,1120)petakopadesa p122,ff14,pts1982, Editedby arabinda barua, ph.d.london)21)ln192-19922)T15,p.21828-b1 23)we find the terms③感意and④感意are etror wrote from"惡意"c.f.佛説大安般守意經 <ref><canon>T</canon><w>602</w>,p.<p>170</p>,<c>2</c>-<c>6</c></ref>24)we can find the same concepts iapitan ganluwei lun阿毘曇甘露 味論「信等五力惡不善法不能壤。是謂力。」(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1553</w>,p.<p>977</p>,<c>b</c><l>24</l>-<l>25</l></ref>)25)安般曰。念 覺種意。是之謂」(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1694</w>,p.<p>17</p>,-<p>20</p></ref>)26)petakopadesa p115,ff627)we fins only one instance in a translation by wu luocha無羅叉,wu most likely followed the translatior romzhu Fahu.28)l217-21829)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>06</v>,p.<p>218</p>,<c>9</c>-<c>10</c></ref>30)ln22 31)06,p.218,1232)ln220-22133)〓603,p.17,25-2834)the term知受解zhi shou jie does exist in other an shigao's works, except for k-asYj. it parallels相 應xiang ying inYcRJ. andthe latter has its counterpart pali term "abhisamaya"" (noun) or "bhisa-meti (verb) ipetakopadesa.35)petakopadesa p35,ff-236)ln222-225 37)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>15</v>,p.<p>179</p>-<c>12</c></ref>38)petakopadesa p,-2639)ln226-227 40)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>15</v>,p.<p>172</p></ref>41)ln227-22742)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>15</v>,p.<p>172</p></ref>-b43)pet-akopadesa p123,ff15-16 (key words) anban shouyi jing an Shiago original text (assistant prof. of dharma drum buddhist college, taiwanN)  
</root>
