<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies journal ofindicm d buddhisf studies vol.56,no.3, march(121 Nagariuna and Satavahana Yamano chieko Both chinese and tibetan sources include some amount of hagiography of nagarjuna and hence have been read as reference sources for re-establishing his historical activities or at-testing to the authenticity of his writings. many scholars have focused on the accounts of his contenporaneousness with king satavahana or king kaniska and the accounts of his activities as an acarya of a king. the rest of his legendaty accounts have been considered as the result of a later addition or the interfusion of the accounts of another nagarjuna and hence have been removed from the obiect of consideration. it seems that the re-establish-ment of his historical activities using hagiographical accounts is a crucial problem. archae-ological sources that testify the existence of the historical nagariuna remain undiscovered. In fact, to date, there exists a controversy regarding the periodin which nagarjuna lived-from the first century to the third century. i begin this paper by indicating the limitations of re-establishing his historical activities using these hagiographical accounts; next, by focus ing on the legends of nagarjuna and satavahana, iexamine the formation and development of the hagiography of the former separate from historical viewpoints. The attempt to identify king satavahana-who was nagarjuna's patron according to Xuanzang (602-664)-began with indian archeology in the late nineteenth century. in the ancient geogrophy ofindia, a. cunningham considered king satavahana as gautamiputra satakarni (.1who tuled over deccan in the second centuryafter cunning-ham, j. burgess established the dates of successive kings of the satavahana dynasty based on archaeological sources fromamaravati and Jaggayyapeta, and he assumed yainasri (〓.178)or pulumayi i〓(〓.215-0to have been nagariuna's patro5)as the in-vestigation of the remains of amaravati , jaggayyapeta, and nagarjunakopda revealed the chronology of ancient South india, the question concerning nagarjuna's patron was some-times addressed. the attempt to identify king satavahana has continued from cunningham and burgess until today.although previous studies adopted an approach based on ar-  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies chaeological sources, they assumed that the accounts of nagarjuna's contemporaneousness with king satavahana-which was made popular from the seventh century onwards-reflect some historical facts. in addition, it should be noted that no existing archaeological source provides substantiation for the relation between nagarjuna and a king of the satava-hana dynasty7). King satavahana in indian literature Satavahana is the name of the dynasty that ruled over deccan from the first century 8)t the third century. pratisthana (modern paithan), the capital of the dynasty, was located in the upper reaches ofthe krsna river. The satavahana dynasty is also referred to as the andhra dynasty'ipuranic literature because it ruled even the andhra region at a later time. sata-vahana is known by various names such as satavahana, salavahana, salahana, salivahana, Sadavahana and satakarni. additionally, Satavahana is known as hala in narrative litera-ture. 〓hala' in maharastri corresponds to the word "sada' in Sanskrit, which is an abbrevia-tion for sadavahana  although these appellations do not precisely indicate a personal name, a king named Satavahana or hala appears sometimes in narrative literature. par-ticularly, king hala is known as the compiler of the sattasai, an anthology of Maharastri poems. Therefore, Satavahana or hala is described as a king who has great knowledge of literature. although king hala is recorded in puranic literature as the eleventh king of the jatavahana dynasty,it seems that king satavahana or hala is a legendary king and that he cannot be identified with a historical person In buddhist literature, king satavahana was mentioned relatively early in the chinese version of the mchomegasutra translated by tanwuchen433). it was said that a king named Satavahana would appear in south india 1 years after the death of the bud-dha.later, the jain authors of the medieval prabandha literature wrote numerous of tales of king satavahana12). legends of nagarjuna and satavahana The earliest accounts of the relation between nagarjuna and Satavahana appeared in the 〓tg xiyuii written by xuanzang and the harsacorita written by banabhatta (c.-647). Because the former has already been discussed in other papers,i focus on the latter and related texts in this paper. banabhatta narrated that nagarjuna, when visiting a naga land,  the japanese associationof Indian and buddhist studies received a wreath of pearls from the naga king vasuki and presentedit to king satavahane upon his return. This story is inserted as an episode in a scene in which king harsa was presented with this precious treasure by a buddhist mendicant. s c taip muktaphalaih patalatale pi taraganam iva darsayadbhir ekovalim akalpaya1 /cakura c mandukiniti nama tsya  c bhagapatah somasy sarvdsam osdhinan adhipatel prubhavad atyantavisaghni himamrtasambhavatoc c sparsena sarvcsattvasamta-paharinibabhuu yatah s tum sarvada visosmasantaye vasukih paryadhattc / amatikramati ca kiyaty api kule kadocin nomnaikavalim tasman nagaroicn nagariuno nama nagair evanita  patalatalam bhiksur abhiksata lebhe c nirgatya c rasatalat trisamudradhipataye satava-hananamne narendraya suhrde s daduu  〓a naga land, he (vasuki) made a wreath of those pearls that shone like stars and named it man. dakini. because it has the power of holy soma, the lord of a11 medical herbs, and because it is made from cool (or lunar) amrta, which is an effcacious antidote, one who touches it gets healed of a11 sotts of fever (or pain). vasuki always wore itto reduce fevers. as time passed on, one day, a bud. dhist monk namned nagarjuna was brought to the naga land by the nagas ;, he asked the naga king for the wreath of pearls and received it. when he returned from the naga land, he gave it to his friend king satavahana, the lordof three oceans. as for nagariuna's visit to a naga land, kumaraiiva (5-409)has already mentioned in the biogrophy of nagarjuna that nagarjuna, who was invited to a naga land by nagabo-dhisattva, received the yaipulyasutra therel). wang xuance, who was sent to india as a diplomat during the seventh century, reported that there was a stupa by the seaside located 100li from the capital of kosala. a king built another stupa to cover the jeweled stupa that was presented to the king by nagarjuna-who, in turn, had received it from a naga king ina naga landtibetan tradition, bu-ston mentioned that Nagariuna, who invited to a Naga land by two naga children, brought clay to make a stupa and a sutra, which contains one hundred thousand verseslthough the story that nagarjuna presented the precious pearls to king satavahana is unique to the harsacarita, the plot in which the gift is given to nagarjuna by a naga king and further gifted to a king is similar to wang xuance's re-port. in this case, this gift is the wreath of pearls that is made from amrta and can felieve a11 sorts of pain. The power of the naga that is connected closely to vital energy becomes a mediator between nagariuna and satavahana. The birth of Satavahana is sometimes narrated as being related to the naga in indian lit-erature. in the yikramacarita, although being a later text18), itis mentioned that he is a son of the naga king sesa. in this story, Salivahana who was supported by his father-naga  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies King sesa-attacked and defeated the army of king vikrama of uiiayinl. the naga king breathed life into a doll army and scared away the enemy army with his Naga soldiers for alivahana9)the similar episode appears even in the caturasitisiddhapravrtti, wherein Nagarjuna, instead of the naga king, provided an army to salabhanda. he breathed life into the trunk of a tree and transformed it into an elephant vehicle for the kingagain, it should be noted that the power of the naga that provides vital energy becomes a mediator between nagariuna and Satavahana. The bitth of nagariuna is also narrated as being related to the naga in jaiprabhanda lit-erature. in the prabhcndakosa, he is said to be born to the naga king vasuki and a human princess of Satrunjaya. The naga king nurtured his son with blind parental love and fed him various potent herbs, therefore, nagarjuna attained many siddhis and became a guru of King satavahana Jain tradition, nagarjuna is known as a disciple of padalipta. phyl-lis granoff noted that Padalipta is also connected with the naga and that the naga's magi-cal power is one of the factors that link nagariuna to padalipta .Thus, the hagiographies of nagarjuna have been developed by linking various components and figures in legends with naga as the motif. finally, the honorific title "trisamudradhipati", which appeared in the harsacarita, in. dicates the lord of three oceans, the west Sea, the south sea and the east sea, that is, the conqueror of deccan. since a similar honorific title, which is added to the name of gauta-miputra Satakarni, appears in the nasik inscription,some scholar considered king sa-tavahana in the harsacarita to be gautamiputra satakarni .however, we must question the need to identify a legendary figure among historical characters. The hagiographies of Nagariuna have continuously developed and transformed through linkage of naga images within the world of stotytelling in deccan. although it is almost impossible to fe-establish Nagarjuna's historical activities using these hagiographies, they provide rich informatior on cultural circumstances of the place wherein the story is told. Notes 1)dated by burgess 2)a.cunningham, the ancient geography' ofindia, (trubuer,1871)595-596 3)dated by burgess 4)dated by burgess  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 5)j.burgess, "The buddhist stupas of amaravati and Jaggayyapeta in the krishna district, Ma-dras presidency, surveyedin82,archaeological survey of southernindia v.1(87)8 6)the following are the various opinions on the identification the king. gautamiputra satakamia.cunnungham[1871]p.s.sastri [15]l.Joshi [196] 〓v. ramanan[1l.kawamura[197david j. kalupahana [1992] vasisthiputra pulumayi, a.k.warder[1967,1974 Gautamiputra satakarni or vasisthiputra pulumayi, : s.ichimura [1992] Yainasri : m.winternitz[1920 Viiayasrih.robinson[967]j.waleser [20 Yajnasrior pulumayiiij.burgess[1887] Viayasri～iksvaku i.w.mabbett[1998] 7)an inscription found from near the jaggayyapeta stupa that records the name of nagarjuna. However, the inscriptionis traced back to the fifth andsixth centuries. 8)the satavahana dynasty began with king simuka, who is said to have lived in some period between the third century b.c. and the first century b.., however, it seems that the dynasty came to power in the first century b.c. 9)lilayai : q romantic kany inahorastri prakrit of kouhala with the sanskrit vrtti of kou-hald, edited by a. n. upadhye, singhi Jain ser.31(bharatiya vidya bhavan,196-4 10)vishnu prana : the 11h king, bhagavota pruna : the 9th king, voyu pruna : the 1th king 11)<ref><canon>大正藏</canon><v>12</v>.<p>1099</p><c>c</c>-<p>110</p></ref> 爾時一切南方天子.復以華香供養世尊白仏言.世尊.如是弟子.何時当出在何国土名 字何等.仏言.善男子.我涅盤後千二百年.南天竺地有大国王.名娑多婆師那.法垂 〓 欲滅餘四十年.是人爾時当於中出講宣大乗方等経典.拯抜興起垂滅之法.広令是経流 布於世. 12)purutanaprabandhasanigraha, prabandlhacintamai, prabamdhakosa, prabhuvakacaritc 13)山野智恵「ナーガールジュナとラサーヤナ」『智山学報』53(2004) 14)the harshacarita of bamabhatta, edited byp.v. kane (motilal banarsidass.1965137 15)<ref><canon>大正藏</canon><v>50</v>.<w>184</w>.<p>18</p><c>a</c></ref> 大龍菩薩見其如是惜而愍之.即接之入海.於宮殿中開七寳藏.發七寳華函.以諸方等 深奥經典無量妙法授之.龍樹受讀九十日中通解甚多.其心深入體得寳利.龍知其心而 問之曰.看經遍未.答言.汝諸函中經多無量不可盡也.我可讀者已十倍闇浮提.龍言. 如我宮中所有經典.諸處此比復不可數.龍樹既得諸經一相深入無生二忍具足.龍還送 出於南天竺. 16)this repott is quoted inthe fa-yuc-lin.<ref><canon>大正藏</canon><v>53</v>.<p>589</p><c>a</c></ref> 西域志云.波斯匿王都城東百里大海邊有大塔.塔中有小塔.高一丈二尺.裝衆寳飾之. 夜中毎有光曜如大火聚.云佛般泥〓五百歳後.龍樹菩薩入大海化龍王.龍王以此寳塔 奉獻龍樹.龍樹受已將施此國.王便起大塔以覆其上.自昔以來有人求願者.皆叩頭燒 香奉獻華蓋.其華蓋從地自起徘徊漸上.當塔直上乃至空中.經一宿變滅.不知所在. 17)the collected works ofbu-ston, editedby lokesh chandra. ya.99b  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 〓 de"i tse byis pa gnyis chos mnyan cing sa 'og tu song ba la su yin dris pas klu yin zer ba la slob dpon gyis gnod sbyin gyi 'dam khyer la shog gsungs pas. de dag gis klu'i rgyal po la zhus pas slob dpon spyan drongs zer te sbyan drangs pas dondu 'gyut bar mkhyen nas klu'i yul du byon nas chos gsungs so. de'itse klus bzhugs par zhus pas nga mchod rten bye babzhengs pa'i'dam tsol ba dang 'bum gan'dren du 'ongs kyibsdad mi khom. phyis 'ong srid gsungs te 'dam mang po dang. 'bum dang yi ge nyung ngu yang gdan drangs te. 'bum gyi zhabs nas bag tzam klus ma bskur zhes grag go. 18)it is dated to the forteenth century-the sixteenth century by ludwik Sternbach. 19)vikramg s adpentures;he thirty-ro tales of the throne, edited by franklin edgerton Hatvard oriental series vol.27harvard university press,1926)176-184 iti tadvacanat sadyo rosarunitalocanah sasainyo niragad raia nihantum salivahanam/ pratisthan- 〓m samasadya vikramadityabhubhuji ksanam tisthati sainyena bhagnas toranamalikah/ atrantare sametya 'su pauraih parivrtah sisuh alabdhasaranas tasya sesam pitaram asmarat/ tena kridakr-tam satvam gajavajipadatikam mahapralayasamtrasasamnaddham abhavad balam*snip* s 'pi jangamatam apa tena 'sau salivahanah/ tato yuddham avartista sainyayor ubhayof apif vikramarkabalam sesapres ita jihmaga yayuh/ plustam tan manusam sainyam asivasavisagnina kva divyasattvah phaninah svalpapranah kva manusah/ 20)abhayadattasri(c.11,caturasitisiddhapravrtti :北京.rgyud-'grel lu.a-b slob dpon gyis nga 'phags pa klu sgrub yin te khyod khyis ngo shes sam gsungs pas. gtam ni thos te ngo mi shes zhus so. slob dpon gyis ba lang rdzi de la khyod khyis nga chu las bsgral ba itngan pa ci dgos pa gter ba yin no. zhes gsungs pas. ba lang rdzina re, bdag la rgyal po 'ong ba'i thabs gcig zhu zernas. slob dpon gyis sa phyogs de na shing sa' la'i sdong po gcig 'dug pa la chu stor bas shing de de ma thag glang po cher gyur nas rgyalpo'i bzhon pa byas. dmag tsogs dgos zhu ba la glang po ches 'khun pa na dmag 'ong ba yin gsung ba de bzhin du byung ste. rgyal po"i ming sa' la bha ndha zhes bya la btzun mo'i ming si nd'i zhes bya bar gyur to. gnas trong khyer bha hi tana zhes bya ba'i yul khyad par 'phags pa cig grub ste. rgyal po la khral 'jal ba'i grong khyer 'bum tso brgyag cu rtza bzhila dbang byedpa'i rgyalpor byas nas. 〓1)prcbondhakosofrojasekhcrasiri, edited by jina vjaya: singhi jain ser.6adhisthatasinnghi Jauna jnanapitha,19384 dankaparvate surastrabhusanasatrunjayagirisikharaikadesarupe rajaputraranasimhasya bhopalan-amnim putrim rupalavapyasampurnam pasyato jatanuragasya tam sevamanasya vasukinagasya putro nagarjjunanama jatah sa ca janakena putrasnehamohitena sarvasam mahausadhinam phalani mulani dalani ca bhoiitah/ tatprabhavena sa mahasiddhibhiralaikrtah siddhapurusa it vikhyatah/ prthvim vicaran prthvisthanapattane satavahanasya rajnah kalagurur jatahf 22)phyllis Granoff, " jain biographies of nagariuna: notes on the composing of a bioraphy in Medieval india", monks cnd magicias  religious biographiesosaic press,1988) 4566 23)tisanudatoyapitavahana 24)l.joshi, " life and times of madhyamika philosopher nagarjuna", mahabodhi 73.1-2(16)  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies 〓-4 k.v. ramanan, nvagurjuna's philosophy,as presented in the mahaprainaparamitosastra (motilal Banarsidass.1966)25-30 (key words) harsacarita, vikramacarita, prabandhakosa (researcher, rengeii institute of buddhist Studies) 財団法人仏教伝道協会英訳大蔵経翻訳叢書 VoLUME1 (正法眼藏第一卷) Translated by Gudo nishilima &amp; chodo coss (Reprint ofthe book published by windbell publications in994. B5変形判・定価6,500円  
</root>
