<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies 〓0)journal ofindicnad buddhist studties vol.56,no.3,march a minimal model of viruddhovyabhicarin u〓danoboru [〓1introduction as is well known, a viruddhovyabhicdrin or antinomy can be caused by two inferences each of which satisfies the three conditions of logical reason (linga, hetn). The following inferences a ad b which are given by dignaga give rise to an antinomy, while each in-ference by itself is valid by the criteria of the three conditions stipulated in his prcmona-s0mtccqyq. (a) sound (sabdd) is non-eternal (amipya), because of being produced (krtakatvat), like apot (ghata). (B)sound is eternal (nipya), because of being audible (sravanatvut), like sound-ness sabdatva). forong svho scmrs ssrmsleniycr s, hos bena oroonrecdmss ,bng adib-nss make Because both inferences a and b are valid according to the three conditions (1.hetu exists in the paksa, 2. hetu exists in only sapaksa, 3. hetu does not exist in vipaksa), it is impossible to determine whether a sound is non-eternal or eternal1.here, however, the example (drstanta) esound-ness"" in the inference b is not accepted by buddhists but by nyaya-vaisesika schools (cf. kitagawa, p.194).dignaga states as follows: for one who accepts eternal universals, both being-produced-ness and being-audible-ness make  inconclusive reasons about whether a sound is eternal or non-eternal Then, is it necessary that although the inference a is considered valid by both buddhists and their opponents, the validity of the inference b, namely the antinomy, is approved only by those who accept the eternal universals" fact, kitagawa (p.36,fn.49)says that the antinomy "can arise only when there is something wrong in the outlook on the universe," and concludes that the metaphysical standpoint-there exists a universal, and it is perceived by a sense organ-, which is supposedly required to establish the eternality of sound, is wrong.  The japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies however, we can make a mathematical example of viruddhavyabhicarin.this fact leads us to the conclusion that the phenomenon of viruddhavyabhicorin has its logical root in the dignaga's logic of the three conditions of hetuthe present paper shows a necessary condition of viruddhanyabhicorin and presents a minimal model of viruddhapyabhicurin. The model will gives us a clear view of the logical structure of uiruddhavyabhicarin. [1]anecessary condition of virnddhovyabhicorii Let us suppose that the following pait of two valid inferences results in a viruddhavyabhi-cdrin. (a1)there exists Sinp, because of h. (a2)There exists Tinp, because of g here the properties h and g satisfy the three conditions of hetu in the inference a1 and a2respectively, and the properties S and t are incompatible (virodha), that is to say, s and Tcannot exist in pat the same time. then we can prove that the paksap is the only locus (dharmin) that has bothhand g. before going into the proof, some remarks are to be made. In dignaga's pramanasamuccaya whether the basis of inference is the second condition of hetu, the third condition, or the hetu-sadhya relationship (yatra.. tatra.. ) is not so clear. J.F. staal (took the hetu-sadhya relationship, which he terms vyopti, as the ba-sis of inference and formalized it ash,x〓,x)), which reads: for any locus xif hexists in x then s exists in x.although staal dealt with dharmakirti's logic, we can safely apply his formalizations in essence to dignaga's logic. in the following, i use the chinese- Japanese buddhist traditional term "example-body(喩体)"instead of "yapti" sice digna-ga's meaning of"pyapti" is, it seems to me, ambiguous. Staal proved successfully that the third condition of hetu logically implies the example-body oyatra. tatra..), but failed in the proof of the implication of the example-body by the second condition of hetu. The present paper will show the implication later. for the pres ent, we also take the example-body as the basis of inference〓 , and try to obtain anecessar condition of viruddhoyabhicorin. anecessary condition of virudchavyabhicarin is that the paksa pis the only locus (dharmin) that has bothh ad g. The proof is as follows Since s and Tare incompatible, formulas (1)〓sx→a, x))and  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 02)aminimal model of viruddhovyabhicarinn. uda. (2)x→(s,x)) hold. here a(s, x) means that the property (dharma) s exists in the locus (dharmin) x. the symbol" denotes the propositional negation, and (x) the universal quantifier. then the formula() reads: for any locus xif s exists in xthen tdoes not existin the locus x, and (2) reads. for any locus xif texists in x then S does not exist in the locus x. Next, we formulate the example-bodies ofadaa(3)and(4)respectively: 3)(〓〓,x) (4)(〓x〓x The formula (3) reads: for any locus xif x has the property h then the locus x has the prop-erty S on the condition that the locus x is not the paksa. read the formula(4) in the same manner. From(),(2),(3),and(4) we obtain anecessary condition of viruddhoay'abhicarin: paksapis the onlylocus hanmin) that has bothhand g. &lt;proofV suppose that there are some loci that have both properties h and G besides the paksa p. that is to say, suppose that the following proposition holds: 〓ah, x)a(g, x)),(〓denotes a conjunction) and name one of such loci "a". then the following formula holds: (5)a〓)a(h,a)ag,a). It is easy to see that(3) and (5) yield(S,a), and(4) and (5) yield (t, a), hence,a) 〓a(,a) holds. but the propositios,a)at,a) and(1)or(2)contradict each other. consequently itmust be the paksa that has both hand g.&lt;q.d.&gt; [2]minimal model considering the necessaty condition obtained in the section[1], we can make aminimal model of viruddhovpabhicarin. The following table exhibits the model. (Table 1) paklocus (dharmin) that has h, g and others. HScus that has  and Stbut has neither g nor t Gcus that has G adT(but has neitherhnor s sand tare incompatible properties dharmcs)  The japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies (M1)there exists Sinp, because ofh, like hS. m2)there exists Tinp, because of G, like GT lt is easy to see that both hetus h in ml and ginzsatisfy the three conditions of hetu. The universe of discourse comprises three loci (charmins)hg., hS,gT}, where "hG.." is identical with the paksa. we can extend the above minimal model to any size. The following table shows a model ir which any pair of the references gives rise to a viruddhouyabhicarin. (Table 2) pakGkJ. universe of discourse〓, hs, gT, kU, tv,…} The sadhya-dharmas s, t, u, v, etc. contradict each other, that is to say, they are incompatible It is easy to see that any pair of the inferences in the table 2 tesults in a antinomy ( virud-dhavyabhicarin). for example, ml and m3 give rise to an antinomy while the logical rea-sons hand k meet the three conditions of hetu in ml and m3 respectively. aminimal model represented by concrete tetms is given as follows. suppose that the fol. lowing statement holds as to the baseball players, nomura, nagashima and ou: Nomura is aplayer-manager, nagashima is a manager, and ou is aplayer. Given a universe of discourse  nomura, nagashima, oa real baseball game requires more than three members, of course-, let us make the inferences m1 and m2. (M1)nomura (p) is not able to stand in the batter's box (s), because ofbeing amanager (h), like nagashimahS). (M2)nomura (p) is able to standin the batter's box(, because of being a player (G), like 〓uGT).  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies (Table3) Since the table 3 is obtained by substitutions of concrete terms for the table 1, itis eviden that the inferences ml and m2in the table 3 result in an antinomy (nomura,not able to standin the batter's  able to standin the batter's anagei,playei,ngashim 〓S,. [〓1deduction of example-body from the second condition of hetu In the previous section, we constructed a minimal model of viruddhapyabhicorin on the basis of the necessary condition(of viruddhavyabhicurin) derived from the example-bodies in the inferences. however, the phenomenon of viruddhovyabhicorin arises from the pait of inferences each of which is valid according to the three conditions of hetu. Therefore, it is required to derive logically the example-body from the second and third conditions of hetu. The formal deduction of example-body (vyapti) from the third condition of hetu was essen-tially made by J.F.staal (198pp.93-108,especially pp.93-97).only a slight modifica tion of staal's formalization suffices to derive the dignaga's example-body from the third condition of hetu. So, we leave it aside now The second condition of hetu spaksa eva sattuam [het] exists only in sapaksa) was formal-ized by staalas h,ypaksa)).and he made use of arestricted-variable to de-note sapaksa, with the result of the following formalization ofthe second condition of hetu (staal, 1988,p.94 〓a(s,x)) (In general, the restricted-variable a fx is made use of to denote any of the values of x such that fx). staal used the restricted-variable to handle sapaksa as a term in a proposition.) he intended to deduce the formula of the example-body vyopti)-yh,y,y))-from the above formula. but his proof was defective (cf. staal,1988,introduction,p.23,uea,pp.98-99). Now, we present a formal deduction of the example-body from the second condition of hetu. in the following, the next symbols are used. 〓S-, x)～as, x),(s-denotes the absence ofthe property S)  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies 〓 K(S, xa(s, x) K(h, x)〓ah,x) S,h: variables to denote properties. 〓:biconditional, namely, logical equivalency. we formalize the second condition of hetu as (x)(k(h,x〓paksa),namely, 6)h,x〓(S,z)).(this reads: for any locus xifhexists in adxis not the paksa, then x is sapaksa.) The foimula to be derived is: 3)(x. sectio[) we introduce an axiom. (xs,z)〓(S-,). [ntuitively, this axiom means that sapaksa is neither vipaksa nor the paksa, and that a locus which is neither vipaksa nor the paksa is sapaksa. The deduction is as follows: (6)(x(h,〓(s,z)) 〓h,〓S-,)v(above axiom) 〓)(～k(h,xvS-,(equivalency: 〓〓)〓 v(x) de morgan's law). ithink we can conclude that((x))is equivalent with(x g(x))in general.intuitively, both formulas mean that there exist some loci that satisfy both f and g.) hence, we derive～(h,z)(k(S-,z)v)from( 〓((h,z)S-,)v) く(h,z)a(k(s-,z)v 〓く(h,z)k(S-,h,z)(distributive law) 〓(,z)k(S-,,z)〓(〓( z)fz((z 〓く(h,z)k(S-,z)((h,z)means( 〓ah,z)〓, and the truth value of this formula is evidently false) 〓(z)(～kh,z)v～k(s-,z))(～(fx)〓(x〓, and de morgan's law) 〓(h,z)〓〓S-,z)xflx〓～(xfx,and  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies Incidentally, we can derive the formula (3) from the following fotmalization of the second condition of hetu. (8)〓S, z))8). In the formula (8),a zh,z) is a festricted-variable to denote any of the loci which are hetu-similar-instances and are not the paksa. chinese-japanese buddhist logicians termed a locus that has hetu "hetu-similar-instance(因同品)".(alocus that has sadhya-dharma was tetmed "sadhya-similar-instance(宗同品)", which is sapaksa in fact. cf. murakami sakaino, p17 The deduction of (3) from(8) is stated in the note9) 〓る 〓(z)h,〓k(S-,z))(～〓zv(z)〓) Here k(S-,z) meansa(S-,z),namely,()八～a(s,z), therefore, ～k(s-,z〓as, z)〓〓s,z). Hence, (〓)(k(,〓(S-,〓()hs,z). Replacing k(h,z) witha(h,z)in theright side formula, we get the formula (7)(z)ah〓,z)). (7)〓(z)ah→〓S,z)〓〓く〓 〓(z)a〓z))(～〓x)〓) 〓(〓)(〓 Replacing the variable z with x, we obtain the formula of the example-body (3)(xx)cf. sectio[) 〓 [4]concluding remarks we have obtained a necessary condition of viruddhavyabhicarin on the basis of the exam-ple-body (vyapti), and made a minimal model of viruddhopyabhicarin using the condition. and we have shown that the second condition of hetu logically implies the example-body (the implication by the third condition of hetu was already shown by staal), therefore we can safely say that the above necessary condition applies to the dignaga's logic of the three condi-tions of hetu. in connection with our argument, note that we do not need the concept of class or set to interpret the second (and third) condition of hetu. Bibliography. kknakavarman's version of pSv. pvrmanasamuccay-vrtti  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies Kitagawa1965.rosser, j.b.1953,logic for mathematicians, McGRaw-hLL. staal, j.F. 1962,contraposition in indian logic,ilogic, methodolog d philosophy of science proceedings of the 1internatinal congress, pp69, stanford (reprinted in staal 1988.93-108). staal,1988, universsstudiesiindicgic ad linguistics, The uni versity of chicago press. kitagawa196, stucies of ancient indticn logic-the systemo dignags logic in japanese)(北川秀則『インド古典論理学の研究-陳那の体系-』鈴木 学術財団(臨川1985)).Murakami/sakaino 1932,buddhist logic in japanese)(村上専精・境 野黄洋『仏教論理学』丙午出版社第三版(first published in18).ueda, dignaga, his logic and apoha-fheory japanese)(上田昇『ディグナーガ,論理学とアポーハ論』山喜房). 1)cf. pSv. p.495k. 2)rtg pahi spyi khas blais p l mnm pr bya ba nid d bys pa nid sra lc rtag gam mi rtag ces the tshom gyi rgyu i no. psvp.5k 3)according to基's『因明入正理論琉』,the inference ais conducted by the vaisesika-schoo. against the sound-produced-school(声生論),while the inference b is conducted by the lattei against the former (cf. taisho4,123-7). incidentally, the inference b-the example ""sound. ness"" is replaced by "self-admitted sound-ness(自許声性)"-as is conducted by the sound-produced-school against the buddhists is considered to be ofno effect (cf. ibid., 1127) 4)we define a universe of discourse as a set which comprises (1)the paksa (natural number60) (2)multiples of which are not multiples of3, and (3) multiples of 3 which have the property Sand are not multiples of 5. here, S means the property of being anumber whose remainderis 1 when dividedbyThat is to say, the universe of discourse20,40,80,100,140…} 〓{9,21,33,57,69,81,93,117…. Then, it is easy to see that the following inferences cand dgive rise to a viruddhopyabhicarin. (c. ueda,p.82) (c)60is a multiple of, because of being a multiple of5, like 20. sapaksa,4,80,100,140 vipaksa:9,21,33,57,69,81,93,117… (d)60has the property s, because of being a multiple of3, like9. sapaksa9,21,33,57,69,81,93,117… vipaksa,80,100,140… 5)kamalasila denies, following dharmakirti, that there occurs a viruddhavyabhicarin wher inferences are basedon fact (vastu ).ad dharmakirti admits that there can be a viruddhayya-bhicarin when inferences are made for the super-sensible objects based on the traditio gama) cf. ueda,p.79,n.57. 6)it seems to me that dignaga and the chinese-japanese buddhist logicians consider the exam ple-body in the inference of three parts to be identical with the second condition of hetu cf. ps ch.3観喩似喩品,k.1c. kitagawa, p.23"two conditions (the second and third con-ditions) are shown by dstonta",基『因明入正理論疏』taisho27「陳那已後.説因 三相即摂二喩.二喩即因.倶顕宗故」,ibid.114「喩体実是因」;善珠『因明論明燈抄』  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies <ref><canon>Taisho</canon><v>68</v>,<p>289</p><c>c</c><l>1</l></ref>「軌師云.因後二相.即是二喩」). 7)in the following, the symbol a stands for z.(x)〓( 〓ga(since 〓,g(x)〓ga〓,x and a are two names of the same object Therefore(ameans(.and( 〓a〓(fx)g(x)(cf. rosser19,p.166,〓.1.7(a)), hence,( 〓〓(xgx)).(rosser, chapter6 〓the restricted predicate calculus" deals with the testricted-variables under the notations other than those usedby staal.) 8)although the meaning of the formula (8) is rather much different from the original meaning of the second condition of hetu. the formula (8)is decisively different from the formula()in that (8)contains the notion of similarity (-similar-instance) while (3) does not. we findan-like interpretation of the second condition of hetu in a japanese monk's work:不離宗同.必有因 同.故云定有性.所以爾者.因第二相.其体即是(善珠『因明論明燈抄』taisho68 267a2-6).here,宗同and因同mean宗同品and因同品,respectively. 9)if the equivalency of()with(xgx))is shown in general, then the formula (3)can be derived in the same manner with the deduction of (3) from(6).to show the equivalency, we use two rules concerning restricted-variables cf. staal, p.9〓tule1),(〓(ule 2).the deduction is as follows.(〓〓( 〓〓z))〓. we tedefine 〓adas 〓x)ad qx, respectively. Then,～x〓)〓〓x)〓)rule 1)〓( xx)〓( .since the last formula means that among loci which satisfy p there exist some loci that satisfy g, we may conclude that(xa〓( xx)ax(this equivalency is obtained when we restrict x and y to the loci which satisfy p in the schema of the rule2.)( a a )〓(x)(x))see* below)〓(〓x). and, as is stated in the note7,(x)〓(山xx)). *(x)x)〓(〓〓x))〓〓～x))〓) く〓)(rule l)〓(ax). (keywords)相違決定,同品,喩体,遍充,sapaksa, staal professor, mejiro university, d.litt.)  
</root>
