<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies Summation of Theravada-tradition versions and proof of linkage to the northern textual tradition MatSumuRa Junko Introduction The narrative of dipankara buddha's prophecy is told in many buddhist texts both northern and southern, and because there is a plethora of different versions, itis not easy to grasp the historical correlations between them. although many scholars have examined nu-merous studies by others and done research on this narrative,1) as fat as the versionial literature is concerned, it seems that they have paid almost a11 their attention only to the one in jataka nidanakatha, as if they regarded it as representative of the traditional Thera-vadin narrative. however, even the narratives of dipankara buddha's prophecy, commonly called the sumedhakatha in pali literature and narrated in many pali texts, are not really uniform as has been supposed, but have many discrepancies. Therefore, in this article, by making a detailed survey and summation of the sumedhakatha inpali literature, this author will attempt to show to what length the discrepancies of different texts go, and, what is more, to indicate that there also exist versions which have close links to the northern texts 1.list of the sumedhakatha inali Literature The following is the list of Pali texts which natrate the sumedhakatha: (1)buddhavamsvii. v87.(2)buddhavamsa-atthakatha bv64,6-119,26). (3)jataka nidanakatha i2,13-28,7).(4)apadunatthakatha p-a.2,2031,5)this text is identical with(3.(5)atthasulini, or dhammasongani-atthakatha s-a32 para-graph68) says "here the durenidana chapter of the jataka commentary (fausbol'a Jatakai. pp.2-47) follows", and the whole text of the narrative is omitted. in the Thai royal edition (pp.4-70), however, the textis not omitted. but the prose sections are only included up to the part corresponding to ja i,27,and thereafter, only the verses of bvii. vv.33-188 follow. (6)cariyapitaka-atthakatha p-a12,14,28).(7)dhammapadatthakatha  The japanese associationof Indian and buddhiststudies (dhp-a83,9-84,2:this is a very concise summaty of the sumedhakatha.(8) 〓ahubodhi-vamsaMhbv2,-10,9).(9)Thpavasthup ed. jayawickrama148,8-153,18).(10)j-nocarita by vanaratana me-dhankara (jina-c ed. by h.w.d.rouse, jptv.8-62).(11) j〓inulankara (inal ed. j. Gray, vv.15-21). 〓 spite of minor deviations, the sumedhakatha in the above listed texts has exactly the same main plot. however, two stories found in the apadana exhibit fairly different ver-sions of the sumedhakatha. They will be discussed belowin Section 2. structure of the sumedhakatha The most well-known sumedhakatha inpali literature is the one in the jataka nidana-katha(3),and this seems to be regarded by scholars as tepresentative of the sumedhakatha of the Theravadins. however, amongpali commentary editors, the most authentic version seems to be the metrical versionin bv together with the prose rendering foundin bv-a. it must be noted that the author of Ja declares as follows "in order to make the full significance of this statement explicit, the stoty of Sumedha should be narrated here. even though it occurs in full in the buddhavamsa, on account of the fact that it is handed down in metrical form, it is not quite clear. Therefore we shall narrate it with frequent state. ments explaining the stanzas." ai2,2933,trans. by n.a. jayawickrama, pp. 3f.) and also, icp-a too, the following statement is found at the end of the sumed-hakatha. 〓i order to know [the story] here in detail, the whole buddhava-ali must be narrated. however, for the people who would be put off by the myriad of details, the story is not narrated in whole. Those who wish to know [the full account of the stoty] should consult the buddhavomsq. The story which should be narrated here is also found in the atthasalini, the commentary on th phammasangaha, andin the jjatakatthakatha." (cp-a16,8-14,trans. by author) This statement signifies that the author of cp-a meant to give an abbreviated version' of the story. it would seem that the metrical version of bv and the prose version in bv-a comprise the legitimate and detailed sumedhakatha. however, this idea did not receive great attention by scholars, even though i. b. horner published a romanized text and an English translation of bv-a. it may be because in the bv-a version of sumedhakatha, the narrative fow is intertupted by constant explications of and commentaries on vocabulary and phrases. so, itis rather unapproachable as it does not have a readable form like the ja  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies version. Therefore, this author extracted only the prose narrative parts in bv-a, correspond-ing to ja structure, and created the first Japanese translation. as a result, it became cleai that the two texts, bv-a and ja, which, at first glance, seem to be almost the same text, are differentin many details. in some parts of Ja there are descriptions not found in bv-a, and vice versa. on the other hand, the bv-a version as a whole aims at being perfect" and complete", containing a11 information about the sumedhakatha. it is noteworthy that in the bv-a prose there are metrical verses ofunknown origin. The synoptic structure of the sumedhakathainbv-a (pages and lines of bv-a text are given in round brackets) is as follows: (〓)a brahman youth, Sumedha, inherited wealth from his parents(67,12-24).(〓) sumedha contemplates the right path(68,30-69,2).(〓i) sumedha contemplates the ight path(69,-70,6).(〓) sumedha contemplates the right path(70,23-71,6).(v) sumedha determines renunciation(72,13-73,12).(vi) sumedha offers a11 his property to people, enters into the Himalayas to practice asceticism and attains supernatural pow-rs(74,13-33).(vi)*sumedha abandons a hut made of leaves and lives under trees(77, 7-14).(vii)*sumedha abandons alms tours and lives on fruits in the forest (78,5-10) (〓)*sumedha attains supernatural powers, dipaikara buddha appears in the world(78, 29-33).in this place q fuil account of dipankaras birth and attainment of enlightenment is inserted. (x) sumedha does not notice the appearance of dipanikara buddha (83,18-20) (xi) dipankara buddha reaches Ramma city; the residents of the city prepare for a great offering, sumedha comes to the city and asks the reason for preparations(84,11-85,2) (xi) sumedha takes on the task of repaiting a muddy road. but before he completes the work, dipankara buddha approaches. Sumedha spreads his deerskin and bark garment on the mud and lies down on it, also spreading his hair over the mud (85,35-87,23).(xii) Sumedha hopes that dipankara buddha and his disciples will walk on his back in order to keep their feet unsullied by not stepping in the mud, and makes a vow to gain perfect en-lightenment by this sacrificial deed (90,1-8).(xiv) eight conditions to become a buddha (91,16-20).(xv) dipaikara buddha prophesies that Sumedha will be a buddha named Gotama (92,23-93,5).(xvi) (a)residents of Ramma city and dipankara buddha honor sumedha, thereafter, they enter the city, and dipankara buddha and his disciples receive great food offerings. (b)sumedha trusts dipankata buddha's prophecy and rejoices, he becomes cognizant of the perfections which he must accomplish, and the gods of the whole  the japanese ociationof Indian and buddhist studies universe praise him9,23-95,23).(xvi-a)*a11 the gods and other beings honor sumedha and leave (99,49).(xvi-b)*sumedha exults at the prophecy and the great brahmas dis-play marvels(99,27-32).(xvii) sumedha trusts in his future enlightenment (102,16-23). (xvili) sumedha examines the conditions contributing to enlightenment, and becomes cognizant of the perfection of generosity (3,31-104,4).(xix) the perfection of moral-ity(5,15-21).(xx) the perfection of renunciation,20-29).(xxi) The perfection of wisdom07,17-25).(xxii) The perfection ofeffort(108,15-21).(xxili) the perfection of patience (109,4-12).(xxiv) the perfection of truthsaying(110,6-14).(xxv) the perfec-tion of resolution(,9-16).(xxvi) The perfection of amity(,33-112,6).(xxvii) the perfection of equanimity(112,27-113,2).(xxvili ) sumedha becomes aware of the whole thirty perfections, and thereupon the earth trembles (13,18-114,2.(xxix) residents of Ramma city ask dipankara buddha the reason for the earthquake(115,1).(xxx) residents of Ramma city reioice (116,34-39).(xxxi) being honored by the gods, Sumedha returns to the himalayas(17,10-24). *These events do not appearin Ja. 3.the sumedhakathaincp-a, Thup, and mhbv The cp-a version contains the concise prose narration corresponding to (i),(v),(xi), (xi),(xii) and (xv).the story ends with dipankara buddha's prophecy, and not ever the account of sumedha's returning to the himalayas is related. This seems to mean that these six parts are the important core of the story, and the detailed version' is just a greatly enlarged story. The important fact is that the text shows wordto word coirespondence with the prose narration of Ja and bv-a, as if it were an excerpt ofthe latter. The Thup version contains (i),a very short description corresponding to (ii)～(v) (〓),(xi),(xii),(xi), (xv),(xvi), a simple enumeration of the ten perfections corre-ponding to (xix)～(xxvii) and ends the stoty with the return of sumedha to the himala-yas. at the end of xv),the verses from bvvv.60-69)are cited. most of the prose text shows a striking agreement with bv-a. concerning mhbv, although there is no helpful translation for buddhist researchers, such asenglish translation, there is, for this text portion, a japanese translation by ki-yotaka minami.) The sumedhakatha in mhbv contains(i),(vi), an abbreviation of (v) く(〓x)with a short account of dipankara's biography, (xi),(xi),(xi),(xv), (xvi-a),  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhiststudies (xvii)～(xxvii), and (xxxi). it is obvious that the mhbv version is far closer to the ja and bv-a version than the two texts discussed above. Especially important is the paragraph (xii), where sumedha's vow to become a Buddha is narrated. when this paragraphin mhbv is compared with the corresponding paragraphs inbv-a, ja, cp-a and Thup, the following facts are noticeable: bv-a90,1-8, Jai13,3-1,5and thup150,25-30are almost identical, while cp-a14,1-2s much shorter and does not have such close literal agreement. however, it does report Sumedha' s introspection as "sacuham icchissami imss bhagavato sovako hutva aii' eva hi-lese ihapessami, kim mayham ekaken' eva samsaramahoghato nittharaneng? (what would happen if i wished to become a disciple of this great master, and today, having thrown awa) a11 worldly desires, i alone escape the sea (cycle) of transmigration),and Sumedha wishes no only to save "mmany human beings' but "the whole of living beings, including gods'. This thought, which has a connection with the mahayanistic idea of bodhisattvas' vow, is no foundin bv-a, ja or Thup, but onlyin mhbv, which has exactly matching phrases. indeed, Mhbv gives a more elaborate description of the vow of sumedha. it is interesting that in Mhbv sumedha's introspection is expressed as pannakannoya codito. minami interprets this expression as汚れなき智慧が訴えかけたのだった[pure knowledge appealed o him],,4)but the corresponding text in the simhalabodhivamsay1,5reads "bud-dhasriya daka praina namati purudu kanyava visin meheyanu labanne (having witnessed the splendour of a buddha (sumedha was) urged by a mnaiden known to him, called prajna) . this means that the sinhalese buddhists understand the word pannokannu literally as the image of a maiden. would it be too much to assume that, there is an echo of the female bodhi-sattva of mahayana esoteric buddhismin this phrase? 4.The sumedhakatha in the apadonq because of the great diversity in the northern buddhist telling of the accountof dipai-kara buddha's prophecy, it cannot be discussed in detail here. however, the greatest dis-crepancy between the northern transmission and the above-treated Theravada version may be the motif of the preexistence of sakyamuni buddha, whose name is Sumati, megha, etc., at the time of dipankara buddha, who honors dipankara buddha by throwing lotus flowers in his path(散華供養).The early visual expression of the account of dipankara Buddha's prophecy can be confirmed in the Gandharan architectural bas reliefs, and free-  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies standing statues. many of them show the story with dipankara buddha in the middle, Bodhisattva buying lotus flowers froma young girl, bodhisattva throwing the flowers, the flowers floating around the head of dipankara buddha, bodhisattva prostrating himself on the ground and spreading his hair under dipankara buddha's feet, and bodhisattva wor-shipping dipankara buddha high in the air. however, the sumedhakatha, the pali version of the account of dipankara buddha's prophecy, is generally believed not to inchude the motif of honoring dipankara buddha with lotus flowers. it was minoru seki who looked at the apadana, and pointed out that there is a Sumedha story which has the honoring of dipankara buddha with lotus flowers.5 The story which Seki alluded to was Theri-apadana no.26Yasodhara" ap584 12-590,30).Yasodhara was, as is known, gotama buddha's consort before his renuncia-tion of worldly life. She revealed that she became his wife in innumerable former lives and served himin various ways. in wv.41-57,is the following narration. in the dipankare Buddha's time she was a young brahman girl called Sumitta. when she saw the ascetic, sumedha, repairing the road upon which dipankara buddha was approaching, she had feelings of devotion for him, and gave him five of the eight lotus flowers in her hand. with these flowers sumedha honored dipaikara buddha, upon which dipaikara buddha proph-esied the other's future. dipankara also revealed to sumitta, that she would be sumedha's wife in his future life (in which he is gotama buddha), and would inherit and guard his teach-ings. 〓p, there is another text which is also obviously related to the sumedhakatha, name ly, no.486, "the confession of elder dhammaruci" 9,20-431,15).when Sumedhe received the prophesy fromdipankara buddha, elder dhammaruci was sumedha's school-mate, whose name was megha. He became a disciple of dipankara buddha together with sumedha, but later he was led astray by an evil friend and committed matricide and other heinous crimes. as a result of those, he had to transmigrate through lowly lives, and, in the present kappa, he became a big fish, timingala, which approached a ship to get food. how-ever, when he heard the name gotama, which the merchants on the ship uttered for help. he recalled his former life and died. He was reborn in a brahman familyin savatti and was named dhammaruci. at the age of seven, he became a novice at the jetavana monastery, and there he approached Gotama buddha three times, each time, buddha addressed him, " it has been a long time, odhammaruci", at which he also responded, "it has been really a  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies long time since i've seen you?. 〓 Itis obvious that the above-mentioned two texts have close relationship with the north-ern version of the narrative of dipankara buddha. in the story of Yasodhara, the theme of honoring with lotus flowers is seen, and in the case of the dhammaruci story, the link with the mchovastu is obvious. asummary of the dipankara buddha story in the mahavastu 193,12-248,5; ed. by e. senart) is as follows:6 dipanikara was born as ason of a cakravartin king, arcimat, and his consott, sudipa, in the capi-tal city, dipavati. after he attained enlightenment he returned to visit dipavati out of mercy for his parents. atthat time, the previous existence of sakyamuni was a brahman youth called megha, who was one of 5students learning brahman studies. and who had a schoolmate called me-ghadatta. when megha completed his studies, he traveled around seeking the treasure to give his teacher in gratitude, and he obtained 50 puranas. on the way back, he wanted to see the calra-vartin king's capital, dipavati, and there he saw that people were bedecking the capital. then he met a young brahman maiden called prakrti who had seven lotus flowers in a vase, and from her he learned that the buddha had appeared in the world. he asked her to sell him five lotus flowers at the price ofpuranus. she gave him five lotus flowers on the condition that he would take her as his wife in future existences until he attained perfect enlightenment. Then, having seen dipankare buddha, he made a vow to become a buddha and threw the five lotus flowers. These towers stayec in the air surrounding dipaikara buddha's face. prakrti also threw her two flowers, and they also stayed in the ait. furthermore, megha bowed at dipanikara buddha's feet, and, wiped the buddha's [eet with his hait, wishing to attain perfect enlightenment. knowing his wish, dipankara buddha redicted that megha would become sakyamuni buddha in the future, after innumerable asankhye-yas. megha told dipankara buddha's words to meghadatta and asked him to enter dipaikara bud-dha's order with him. but meghadatta refused. meghadatta had an affair with another ma's wife. and killed his own mother who remmonstrated with him about it. he also committed other grievous crimes, and he had to spend a long time in many hells. later, when megha attained perfect enlight-enment as the sakyamuni buddha, meghadatta was reborn as a huge fish, timitimimgila, and was about to swallow a large ship with〓 merchants. caught upin fear, the merchants called out the lame, 〓buddhal" and at that moment meghadatta recalled the words of dipankara buddha which he heard from megha. he died at that place calling the name, buddha. he was reborn ina brahmar family in sravasti and was named dharmaruci. he entered sakyamuni buddha's order and com-pleted priestly training. one day, when he approached the master (Sakyamuni buddha), he was addressed by the Master, "it has been a long time, odharmaruci.' he replied, 'o master, indeed it has been a long time.' This was repeated three times. to the other monks, who wondered at this cit-uumstance, the master told the history of megha and meghadatta and revealed: "i was the brahmal youth, megha, and this dharmaruci was meghadatta (aham c megho mnanavo namena asi eyc c dharmaruci meghadatto, mvui27,12). although there is confusion about the names, megha and Meghadatta, it is very obvi-  the japanese ociationof Indian and buddhist studies ous that the story of dhammaruci in ap is closely linked with thatin mvu. the story of dharmaruci is also found in the divyavadona, no.18"harmaruci", and in the zeng-yi-a-han-jing増壹阿含經,vol.11(2,59722-599c4), and a very short version is found in the jing--yi-xiang經律異相(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v>,<p>190</p><c>c</c><l>15</l>-<p>191</p><c>a</c><l>7</l></ref>).〓 div, dharmaruci was the big fish timimgila in the life which he had just finished; and at the time of dipankara buddha, sa-kyamuni was a young brahman called Sumati, and dharmaruci was his friend, Mati. the young woman who gave lotus fowers to sumati was king vasava's daughter. she came to the capital of king dipa, dipavati, in disguise, and she was said to be an earlier incarnation of Yaso-dhara. The stories in the zeng-i--hn-jing and in the ling--yi-xiam differ even more from those in mvuor div. 5.conclusion as examined above, the sumedhakatha, or the Theravada traditional version of the narrative of dipankara buddha's prophecy, is by no means only one narrative as has been generally believed. especially inp, there are stories which show clear relationships with northern versions. it may be that only the flower-offering and prophecy story without the hair-spreading motif also existed in the northern tradition. in a version of the story found in the guo-qu-xian-zai-yin-guo-jing過去現在因果經(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>3</v>,<p>620</p><c>c</c><l>23</l>-<p>623</p><c>a</c><l>23</l></ref>),dipankara Buddha gives the prophesy at the miracle of floating flowers, and then, with supemnatural power, he makes the mud on which bodhisattva lies and spreads his hair, and dipankars buddha again gives the prophecy. in some other texts, the Prophecy is given after the hon-oring by flowers and the spreading of hair. as narratives, the order and contents of these components are quite unnatural and difficult to explain. even in Gandharan art, the comm-plexity continues: there are stone reliefs of the dipankara buddha's prophecy without the motif of spreading of hair, for example, plate lin isao kurita's The gandharc, (to-kyo: nigensha,〓003).in addition, plate649,ibid, is given as unidentified", but it does have the scene in which a man wipes a buddha's feet. which seems to be the scene from mvu ( the gray schist is damaged).in fact, there are many other visual representations of the story in other regions from various periods which show these two motifs plus a variety of different details. Seki argues that the original dipankara buddha prophecy narrative includes both honoring with fowers and spreading hair motifs, and that in the theravada tradition, one of these two motifs is accidentally or intentionally omitted.however, when read with  The japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies careful textual analysis, it is more logical to postulate that the two stories, one of flower offering and one of hair-spreading have independent origins, and that they were combined at a later date. 1)for ex.: chizenakanuma, "nentobutsu no kenkyu [ study on dipankara buddha]", bukkyokenkyu, vol.6,no.3(1925),pp.317-340 kaijo ishikawa, "nentobutsu shiso ni kansuru kosatsu," shimizuuz sensei koki kinenronbunshu90),pp.4-66, ryugen taga "nentobutsu ni tsuite," kanakura hakushi koki kinenindogaku-bukkyogaku ronshu (kyoto: Heirakuiishoten,1966),pp.81 2)junko matsumura, "The sumedhakatha in the buddhavamsatthakatha," kobe kokusaidoigaku kiyo (kobe international university revien), no.72(june 〓07),pp.15-32. 3)kiyotaka minami, 〓nnotated translation of the mahabodhipams,"kacho tankid. aigaku kenkyu kulletinofkacho junior college),no.32(dec.1987),pp.31-4. 4)k. minami, ibid, p.38. 5)minoru seki, "tooi innen konidanakata nentojukimonogatari no tokuisei," indog-aku buklyogaku kenkyujournal of indian d buddhist studies), vol.20,no.2(1972), pp.336-340. 6)an annotated japanese translation of the dipankaravastu in mvu was published by setsuryo Fukui: the mikkyo bunka, no.135(Sep.1981),pp.128-99,no.136(dec.1981),pp.104-72, No.137(feb.1982),pp.90-51,no.14ec.1982),pp.102-69. 7)m. Seki, dbid, pp.833f. (The research for this article was supported by the grant-in-aid for scientific research (c no. 195208 from jSPs) (key words) sumedhakatha, dipankara, buddhavamsatthakatha, apadana, mahavastu (professor, kobe international university, ph.d.)  
</root>
