<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies journal ofinciam ad budchist studies vol.56, no.3,march 8(14 〓n kukai's "mysteriously arranged mind"" Sania jurkovic "Mysteriously aranged mind""(秘密荘厳心),the tenth abode in kukai's works himitsu mandara jniushinron ad hizo hoyaku, represents the state of awakening of the shingon practitioner. in this last abode, kukai attempts to indicate the ground common of a11 varie-ties of mind. he refers to it as a retumn to the primordial state of one's mind(自心源底), which manifests in the form of an infinite number of the four kinds of mandalcs and the four wisdom seals. he then introduces the way of Shingon practice as a distinguishing feature of the tenth abode. kukai gives the reader a glimpse of the meaning of the yogic process of "mystical identification"smaya) through the correspondences he fotms in the text, such as the establishment of relationships between Sanskrit syllables and various teachings. based on this relation, he generalizes his esoteric view oother teachings intro-duced in the previous abodes. Kukai's tenfold model is textually based primarily on the mahavairocanabhisambodhi sutra and putixi lun(菩提心論)of the vairasekhara tradition. particularly, the tenth abode of himitsu mandura jurushinron has a special emphasis on the chapter intercorrespond-ence with the result ofthe hundred letters(百字果相応品)from the mahovairocanasutra. whereas the tenth stage of Hizo hoyaku extensively quotes the part on "bodhicitta of eso-teric samudhi"(三摩地の菩提心)of putixi lun. The tenth abode has a qualitatively distinct place within the model of the ten abodes, whilst at the same time it is also related to the eighth and ninth abodes. each of these three abodes reveals another important aspect of "knowing one's own mind as it really is"7(如 実知自心).a11 three are considered to be related to the attainment of the state of the sixth fearlessness(一切法自性平等無畏),the last step in the process of the realization of empti-ness and the establishment of fully developed bodhicitta. this paper will summarize some of the distinguishing features of the tenth abode, such as the concepts of samoya and eso-teric samadhi. at first, i will focus on kukai's unique synthetical approach, which is most  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhiststudies 46)〓n kukai's 〓 mysteriously arranged mind" (s. jurkovic) learly visible in the text of the tenth abodeinhimitsu mandara jniushinron 1.synthetical approachin relation to the mind and other teachings 1.1.central to the mahavairocanasutra is the question and answer, "what is bodhi? it is to know one's own mind as it really is." This phrase is also the central topic of himitsl mandara juiushinron, which kukai interprets from two perspectives: This one phrase encompasses infinite meanings. vertically, it expresses depth of [the mind]in ter layers. horizontally, it indicates a vast number of meanings, equal to the number of grains of sand. In order to elaborate the vertical approach that enables him to establish the model of ten stages, kukai uses the idea of the " evolving of the mind"(心続生),which appears in the first chapter of the mahayairocanasutra. this emphasis on the vertical approach is the primary focus of hizohoyaku. in relation to the horizontal approach, prominentinhimitsu mandara jujushinron, kukai uses other chapters of the mahovairocanasutra related to yogic practice. in the textof the tenth abode, he frequently refers to the chapter intercotre. spondence with the result of the hundred letters, quoting itno less than five times. based on this chapter, the tenth abode is defined as the state of infinite body and mind, which is qualitatively different from the previous abodes. kukai states: The two vehicles of the  five] aggregates only' and of eradication of karma' know only six[kinds ofl consciousness. The teachings of others as obiect' and realizing the mind" both indicate only eight minds. The one way' and transcending no [self nature]'both know only nine [kinds of con-sciousness. shimohoyenun(釋摩訶衍論)explains ten consciousnesses and the king [of sutras] 〓ahavairocanasutra explains infinite minds, consciousnesses, infinite bodies, andso on. to know this utmost of the body and mind [in this way]means to realize "the mysteriously arranged abode' (秘密荘厳之住處).2) The paragraph of the mahovairocanasutra, which kukai interprets as the horizontal ap-proach to understanding of "knowing one's own mind as itis"" reads "next one seeks the state of complete enlightenment. by knowing that minds are infinite, one knows that bodies are infinite. by knowing that bodies are infinite, one knows that wisdom is infi - nite. by knowing that wisdom is infinite, one knows that sentient beings are infinite. by knowing that sentient beings are infinite, one knows that space is infinite.' This is the horizontal meaning.〓 The mahovairocanasutra actually doesn'texplain a quantitatively infnite number of con-sciousnesses or an infinite number of minds but it does refer to a qualitatively infinite state of mind, body, wisdom, and so on that occurs as a result of complete awakening. There-  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies fore. kukai synthesizes the two-dimensional vertical approach that differentiates between the number of various kinds of consciousnesses, and the horizontal approach of a single infinite consciousness, thereby creating anew dimension called ""the mysteriously arranged abode." in this way, the last abode encompasses a11 ten kinds of consciousness, whilst at the same time maintaining its own infinity. in relation to the definition of the mind of the tenth abode, this method of combining qualitatively different aspects may be interpreted as Kukai's synthetical approach. 1.2.another aspect of the synthetical approach apparent in the text of the tenth abode re-lates to kukai's final interpretation of various teachings. itis based on establishing a mysti-cal correspondence between Sanskrit syllables and various teachings, again theoretically placed in the context of the chapter of intercorrespondence with the result of the hundred letters. This chapter, namely, refers to the attainment of bodhi, attained through the recita-tion and meditation on the "mantra which shines everywhere with one hundred light rays (百光遍照真言),which is the syllable am. a11 knowledge (on various infinities) emanates from the mantra itself. kukai quotes the beginning of the chapter related to entering intc the state of three samoya, which is the core of the Shingon teaching. it says: If one enters the stage of the great wisdom initiation' of the enlightened world-honored one, he will himself realize and abide in the state of three samaya. Kukai doesn't specifically mention the syllable am, but instead uses this context to intro-duce the mantra teachings on the basis of the twenty-nine sanskrit syllable gates(十九〓 字門)from the second chapter of the mahovairocanasutra. in this way, he identifies the attainment of bodhi with the knowledge of the twenty-nine syllables. The list of the twen-ty-nine syllable gates in the mahavairocancsutra indicates that the total of a11 the syllables and words arising from them cannot be ascertained (anupalubdha), as they a11 ultimately come from the syllable a, which represents original non-arising. the sutra states: what is the shingon mantra) teaching ? the teaching (gate) of the syllable 〓a', because a11 phe-nomena are originaly unarisen nuppuda). the teaching of the syllable 〓 ka", because activity of a11 phenomena (karya) cannot be ascertained. The teaching of the syllable "kha", because a11 phe-nomena, such as space, cannot be ascertained..  the teaching of the syllable "s" tya), because no truth can be ascertained in a11 phenomena. the teaching of the syllable ha" (hetu), because the 'auses cannot be ascertained inall phenomena. Within the context of the ten abodes, syllables are very impottant for kukai, as he identi-fies them with different buddhist teachings. for example, in the text of the seventh abode,  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhiststudies Kukai correlates the syllable ma with great emptiness, the bodhisattva manjusri, and the teaching of Sanlun(三論).〓in the same way, these twenty-nine syllables represent en-trances to different teachings (dharmaparyayas).kukai mentions twelve transformations (十二轉)of each syllable out of which the four syllables ( the first two and the last two) always indicate the initial mind of awakening(発心),the stage (s) of practice(行),the realization of bodhi(證)and the entrance to buddhahood(入),respectively.〓 for kukai, although any teachings based on words and their combinations, are unobtainable and empty, they can nonetheless heal certain illnesses and bring a practitioner to buddhahood. In the latter part of the text. kukai refers to the possible combinations of syllables, which ead to anumber exceeding ten thousand.9) this suggests that whatever number of syllable combinations exist, they a11 form the samadhi and dharani gates of deities, and manifest various exoteric and esoteric teachings. with such reasoning, kukai expands his approach. developedin previous abodes, to reveal that a11 the teachings are essentially and practically equal. Kukai assigns to the mind of the tenth abode, particularly to its expression in the form of dharmamandala, the knowledge of the twenty-nine syllables and their implications in relation to the other teachings. although through the samadhis of different deities shingon teaching embraces other buddhist teachings, it distinguishes itself from a11 others by re-placing common language with the language of mantras. similar to that described in1, but now in a different context, kukai's synthetical approach builds up the tenth abode in such a way that it encompasses a11 other teachings, maintaining at the same time its own qualitatively different dimension. samaya, esoteric samadhi and the practice of the three mysterious activities(三密行)are the key words for the tenth abode. 2.esoteric samodhi and the state of samayq Kukai defines the infinite body and mind attained at "the mysterious inexhaustibly ar-ranged abode"(秘密無盡荘厳之住處)interms of the four kinds of manddlas. 〓ahavairocanasutra clarifies the realm of such infinite bodies of four kinds of mandala and be-nefits of buddha's teaching. this is mysteriously arranged, inexhaustible realm. Seeing the world and one's own existence in terms of mandalas represents a cognitive change appearing for the practitioner of this esoteric method. itis a result of replacing the old static identity with a dynamic changing of roles, which, within the context of the  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies 〓 Shingon teaching, cotresponds to an identification with mandula deities. this process of perceiving oneself and other practitioners of any time, as the only deities that could ever existed, takes place in "this very body"(即身),after a11 obstructions have been removed, to the great astonishment of the practitioner himself.11 In sokushin jobutsu gi, kukai explains that awakening in "this very body" is possible because of the principle of the interconnectedness of a11 bodies, specifically, buddha bod-ies and the bodies of sentient beings, illustrated by the simile of indra's net. within this context, kukai introduces the "mantra of nonobstruction of three equals", which is actually the vidya called " entry into the buddhas' samad""(入佛三味耶持明)that is quoted in the second chapter of the mahavairocancsutra: e asame trisame samaye svaha .12 as one of the explanations of triscme, kukai mentions equality of the mind, buddhas, and sentient beings. This identity of the three is essential for theoretical and practical aspects o1 Kukai's teaching. one of the sources for this premise is the huayan view that "mind, bud-dhas and sentient beings. these three are without distinction"(心仏及衆生是三無差別).13. The mantra " entry into the buddhas' samayd"" stands as the representative mantra for the whole system of esoteric practice. kukai mentions itin the tenth abode as well. if one car concentrate on it, one can immediately realize identity with the buddha. The state of samaya is often translated into chinese as "sequality"(平等)14),but actually it has a wider meaning. more profoundly, it refers to the method of "mystical identifica-lion" of the practitioner with a reality based on some concrete thing or image. it refers to the process of reaching a state of unity and has a similar meaning to the term yoga.1 the esoteric method described in the mahovairocanasutra is based on the process of samayd, which is, for the purpose ofrelating to it, divided into three aspects, as samaya of the body, speech and mind. The name of the tenth abode "mysteriously arranged mind" is based on subhakarasimha's interpretation of the state of the " inexhaustible adorned treasury of the samapa of the body, speech and mind""(身語意平等無尽荘厳蔵)displayed by buddha in front of his audience before exposing the teaching of the mahavairocanasutra. " arranged" (荘厳)refers to the samoy of the three mysterious activities(三密)of the body, speech and mind of the practitioner, which come into intercorrespondence(相応)or "perfect alignment"" with the three mysterious activities of the deity in the esoteric samodhi. after realization of identity based on the process of samaya, there is no longer a search for an  the japanese sociationof indian and buddhist studies ideal state. when one is in the state of alignment with one's original mind, a11 things come to be in the perfect position just as they are. This refers to the "mysteriously arranged mind", which is actually the practical and ultimate realization of "knowing one's own mind as it really is""(如実知自心). Kukai's understanding of samaya is vety close to the meaning of " esoteric samodhi" and specifically refers to the term"nyuga ganyu"(入我我入),aphrase he coined by imself.1) The whole of the tenth stage of hizo hoyaku is a quotation on esoteric samadhi foundiutici lun. through the realization of samudhis of different deities, a11 of the prin-ciples and teachings of the previous abodes are actualized in the tenth abode. 3.conclusion Kukai's method of combining elements of a different nature and thereby obtaining an out-come of a new quality was considered in relation to his approach to the mind of the tentl abode and to his view on other teachings. This synthetical approach comprises in itself a mystical aspect as it calls for certain degree of understanding of the experiential reality that is beyond the descriptive realmof the words. if one does not understand the fact that kukai points to the non-dualistic experience at the tenth abode as the result of Shingon practice, then his mystical approach, visible in various examples in the text of the tenth abode may sometimes seem to be oversimplified or even illogical. i find it is necessary to outline Kukai's way of reasoning, whichi have termed his "svnthetical approach", in order tc understand his perspective as written froman esoteric point of view. The actual state of  the mysteriously arranged mind" is the state of practicing samodhi, which is the reason why the concise text of hizo hoyaku quotes the respective patt of putixi lun in its entirety. For Kukai, samodhi refers to the state of trisamaya, the concept brought to attentionihimitsu mamdara juiushinron. through the process of experiencing the realization of emptiness at the eighth abode, thereby opening the place for the manifestation of suchness at the ninth abode, and finally experiencing the mystical process of samoyq at the tenth abode, one can attain the dynamic position in the four kinds of mandalas, which characterizes the state of "awakening in this very body. 1)himitsu mamdora ruiushinron. teihon kobo dishi zenshu『定本弘法大師全集2,秘密曼茶 羅十住心論』(hereafter abbreviated as z.2,koyasan1993,pp.07-308.  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 〓 kukai's "mysteriously atranged mind"(s. jurkovic)( 2)TZ.2,p.08. 3)ibid. quotation is from t.18,p.40b. 4)ibid. 5)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>18</v>:<p>10</p><c>a</c><c>b</c></ref>. on the twenty-nine syllables list see北條賢三「大日経言語形成の源流」,『イ ンド密教の形成と展開』,法蔵館,1998,pp.189-191. 6)t1810ab.t.,pp.310-312. 7)Ia similar way, he relates the syllable sa to the " truth of a1 tharmas" and to the teaching of liantai. ka is related to huayan teaching, ad at faxiang teaching. tz.2,pp.238,257,271, 295. 8)tz.2,p.310. 9)TzZ.2,p.323. 10)Tz.,p.311 11)one of the characterizations of the state of samaya is astonishment. See fn.14. 12)z3,p.28. 13)this refers to the "verses on cittamatratd "(唯心偈),in sixty volumes buddhavatamsaks-itra. <ref><canon>T</canon><v>95</v>-<p>466</p><c>a</c></ref>. see chisho mamoru namai: shingonmon, The way of Shingon buddhism, Bulletin of the research institute of esoteric buddhist culture, Special issue ii, october-0 p.285. 14)subhakarasimha refers to the four meanings of the word samquality(平等),vows(本 誓),eliminating obstacles(除障)and astonishment(驚覚).he also states that the gateway of samaya(平等法門)is the main meaning of the mahovairocanasutra. t883a. 15)Namai chisho: searching for identityin diversity: from the viewpoint of mandala, presented at icbs, koyasan university, september6,p.2printing). 16)村上保壽:「空海の開題を読(5)一三味耶と入我我入」,『密教文化』209,2002 〓 &lt;Key words)秘密荘厳心,samaya,十住心 (researcher, koyasan university Research institute for esoteric buddhist culture)  
</root>
