<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese associationof Indian and buddhist studies acomparative study between the womb and the lotus sutra. Miraculous stupa apparitions, two simultaneous buddhas and related extraordinary narations Elsa legittiMo Introductory notes This paper is related to the one i presented last year at the〓57 congress of the Japanese association of indian and buddhist Studies"1)while last year i discussed how and why the authors of the womb sutrahad exploited motives and ideas from the vimalakirtinirdesa, this year i wish to trace some of the parallels existing between the "stupa chaptet" of the lotus and the womb sutra. whereas the lotus is certainly one of the best known buddhist sutras, the womb belongs to a once influential but now rather forgotten kind of buddhist sutras. 3)the womb pretends to be sakyamuni's first and last exposition, held when he was a fetus in his mother 's womb and then again shottly before his nirvana. Influences from the lotus sitra in the womb sitrg The text commparative analysis I conducted on these two texts reveals that the lotus precedes the womb, that the lotus was known to the authors of the womb and that these were inspired by certain elements or even full chapters of the lotus. despite certain minute thematic resemblances and amazing similarities the borrowed themes appear in the womb under a vety different light. partl of the comparison-from the appearance of the stipa till the setting of the audience In the womb the motives related to this first part are scattered in various chapters: nine,4) eleven,5)thirteen6) and sixteen.7) the " stupasandarsanaparivarta" of the  otus starts with prabhutaratna tathagata's stupa coming out of the earth. the stupa then remains suspended in the air andis magnificently described. in chapter eleven of the womb Sakyamuni buddha lets usnisa-raia bodhisattva witness the miraculous apparition of sikhin  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies Tathagata's seven-treasure stupa. he then lifts up the stupa and places it within the womb. In this text too, the stupa, its fence, ponds, and parks are minutely depicted. Further, ir chapter sixteen of the womb a multitude of buddhas, a11 emanations of sakyamuni buddha, create an elevated seven-treasure altar over a pond and place a high seat on it. again, the altar's decoration is beautifully depicted. we see that by means of sikhintathagata's stupa the authors of the womb try to compete with the fantastic stupa of prabhutaratna. The monument portrayals were probably standardized and therefore have only a limited comparative value. noteworthy is that whereas the stupa of the lotus appears by itself and vithout the intervention of sakyamuni, the one of the womnb appears and is brought into the womb by virtue of sakyamuni's volition. prabhutaratna tathagata's universe called Ratnavisuddha is located far away in the nadir direction. in ancient times the tathagata expressed the wish that he wants to be present every time the lotus sutra is preached. the auditors of the lotus request to see this Tathagata. The womb too narrates a unique nadir cosmology in the first part of its chaptei nine that is even titled 〓complete body relic". ten ksetras located undemneath the eartl are described: the oth and 1 abound in complete body relics (ekaghama sariras全身舎 利),and the 7=in fragmented body relics (vaistarika relics碎身舍利).it is significant that both stupas are from the nadir, that both contain ekaghana relics, and that the nadir is itself related to relics.The authors of the womb clearly inflated the relic issue. In the lotus sakyamuni then fills the universe with multiple tathagatas created from his own form. with their bodhisattva retinues these shall be present at the following events. also chapters sixteen and thirteen of the womb start with Sakyamuni buddha showing extraordinary apparitions. in chapter thirteen he transforms a11 present bodhisattvas into fully equipped buddhas who preach by different mouths, but with the same voice. the emanation of countless tathagatas is however of minor comparative relevance as it alsc appears in other sutras. Next, in the lotus sakyamuni emits a light ray from between his eyebrows enlightening the previously created tathagatas. in chapter sixteen of the womb sakyamuni first emits light from his joints and pores. every light ray has one billion buddhaksetras. every buddhaksetra has a buddha. next he emits light from his usisinto countless billions of buddhaksetras. This light is seen by the Ratna tathagata(寶如來).sakyamuni then performs a third light emission, towards the East into the 〓hot world"(炎世界)where there  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies is the country called 〓extraordinary'(奇特)of the deep meaning" tathagata(深義如來). light emissions and multiple buddhas created from light are also seen in other texts. here we notice that the authors of the womb have strongly enhanced the attractive motive of physical light emission. Itmight not surprise that the reasons for the " foreign' bodhisattvas and tathagatas) arrival ior near) this world vaty in the two texts. in the lotus the tathagatas say"we should gc to the saha world of the tathagata sakyamuni to see and worship the stupa containing the body of prabhutaratna." upon seeing the light emission the ratna tathagata of the womb tells his bodhisattvas 〓down there sakyamuni tathagata is now staying in his mother's womb, broadly explaining the deep and essential most superior dharma treasure(深要 無上法藏)."the "deep meaning" tathagata of the womb when he sees the light tells his bodhisattvas: "with a great appearance you should go to that world of sakyamun Buddha and listen to the endless dharma-treasure which is difficult to be conceived. the bodhisattvas of that land will a11 become buddhas in one life." The double focus of the Lotus lays on the worship of prabhutaratna and on the hearing of the lotus sutra. but ir the womb the bodhisattvas of two 〓preexisting' tathagatas (not emanations) afe sent to heat sakyamuni's exposition of the deep and essential supreme dharma treasure. this clearly confets an aura of superiority to sakyamuni's teaching. basically both sutras do not accept more than one tathagata in the same world. in the lotus prabhutaratna is the exception to this rule. The other tathagatas are in fact seated allover in surrounding space. the exposition of the womb takes place in the womb and serves the putpose of highlighting the buddha sakyamuni. the " foreign' tathagatas were eclipsed from the scene of the dharma exposition. both sutras further mention the greetings and wishes the various Tathagatas request their bodhisattvas to express in front of sakyamuni. in the lotus the tathagatas send their issistants to sakyamuni with fower baskets and jewels telling their assistants: " bow to the Buddha and wish him in our name few sufferings, fewillnesses, strength and the benefit to live among nice people. bring the best wishes to him, the bodhisattvas and the srayakas.' The first group of bodhisattvas of chapter sixteen of the womb is told by ratna tathagata: eyou a11 should go there, worship sakyamuni with respect and bring your greetings, also give my personal greetings to him." The second group of bodhisattvas is requested by deep neaning" tathagata to ask the following: "is your virtue converting the beings day after  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies day? are you striving forwards and constantly walking around? are you in good health and strong? are the living beings of your land easy to convert?" These formulas of politeness represent indeed attractive narratives. it is uncertain whether in this case the authors of the womb were directly influenced by the lotus, or whether the formulas reflect ancient standard greeting expressions. Moreover, the bodhisattvas of the lotus are requested to say : "the tathagatas espectfully inform you about theit wish to see the opening of this great stupa." chapter sixteen of the womb mentions the undisturbed minds of the auditors and their wish to hear the tathagata's secret essence(祕要).again, the authors of the womb set the focus on sakyamuni's unique "womb exposition Partiiof the comparisoThe two buddhas and the expostion of the law In the lotus the opening of the stupa takes place under great pomp. sakyamuni separates the stupa into two parts by the index finger of his right hand, and opens it like a grea gate. prabhutaratna appears seated, crossed legs, with dried out body members, like in a meditative state. he offers half of his seat to sakyamuni inviting him to sit down next tc him. sakyamuni follows his invitation and explains how in ancient times he obtained the lotus sutra from a rsi. the stupa section ends with a final speech' o the merits of the lotuis sutrq. In chapter sixteen of the womb the gods produces music and praise the tathagata sakyamuni tells manusti: " stop this heavenly music! i want to expound the dharma The buddha arises in the world once every trillion kalpa. when this happens, it is like a udumbara flower."11)again, the authors of the womb underline the uniqueness of the womb exposition which was never expounded before by some other buddha or rsi. Nevertheless, the authors of the womb sutra do not exclude, as it might first seem, the possibility of two buddhas in one world. The " stupasandarsanaparivarta" exerted its influence also on chapter twenty-seven of the womb sutrawhich relates the event of two buddhas appearing in this world. The "core expositions' of the two chapters have little incommon. The narrative of the womb differs from that ofthe lotus. its assembly does not witness a past buddha's sudder appearance in sakyamuni's world. on the contrary, sakyamuni first explains maniusri's past buddhahood and then explicitely invites maniusri to show his past buddha body.  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies without separating from his seat Maniusri fetches his 'Flower world'(華世界)13)b his supernatural powers and brings it to the saha world into sakyamuni's mother womb assembly. the two buddha worlds do not bear signs of mutual obstruction. manjusri shows on his body a11 the marks ofa buddha and is seated under the bodhi tree expounding the dharma. The bodhisattvas of his land become familiar with the buddha sakyamuni and render homage to him with fragrances, flowers, banners and canopies. on the other hand, sakyamuni's bodhisattvas render homage and make offerings to the buddha manjusri. The teaching expounded by one buddha is echoed by the other. They both stand up' for rather conventional early buddhist themes: non-arising, the smrpyupasthanas, the path to awakening, sufferings, and emptiness. whereas in the lots prabhutratna appears by his own volition and his seat offer might also show that he ranks above sakyamuni, in the womb there is a clear shift of authority, as in chapter sixteen sakyamuni buddha purposely emits light for calling exterior auditors, and in chapter twenty-seven manjusri is explicitly invited by sakyamunito show his buddha body. PartiIThe events after the expostion of the law In the "stupasandarsanaparivarta"" the narration continues with the sudden intervention of prainkuta(智積)bodhisattva who had come fromprabhutaratna tathagata's nadir world. he suggests to "his' prabhutaratna buddha:" let us go back to our land." but Sakyamuni asks him to have a talk with his bodhisattva manjusri. prajnakuta is skeptic whether anybody could have grasped manjusri's previous expostion of the lotns sitra and asks him whether anybody was able to attain full buddhahood. here begins the story of how the little naga princess became a buddha. it is generally acknowledged that the "stupasandarsanaparivarta" originally consisted in two distinct parts and with prajnakuta's intervention begins the second part. The princess is said to transform herself into a male bodhisattva who attains buddhhood seated under a bodhi tree in a universe called vimala. Three thousand beings presentin the assembly receive the prediction of future buddhhood. In the womb sutra prainakuta bodhisattva appears in the chapter following the one on Maniusri's transformation. he is introduced with a remark that he produced the roots of a11 merits and defeated the devil's fury under a past buddha. after worshiping sakyamuni buddha he inquires about the six destinies and theit relation to the defenses. the text then continues with an ancient indian mythological story on naga and garuda. the narrative has  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies been greatly transformed to fit the buddhist defense of non-killing. although prajnakut. bodhisattva of the womb does not appear in the same chapter as the two simultaneous Buddhas, he emerges right after this event. both texts thus display a similar sequence Further analogies are that in both texts prainakuta is an active figure 14)and the disciple of some past buddha. the following stories both have a naga as protagonist, and in both cases the narrations are witouth direct connection to the event of the two buddhas. The differences between the fespective passages are also remarkable: despite the fact that both sutras focus on release, the lotus strongly underlines the aspects of faith and duna, for example by the jewel offered by the little princess to the buddha, whereas the womb focuses on the eight defenses and on moral conduct. moreover, the lotus does not inform us whether prabhutaratna tathagata and his opened stupa returned to their respective previous states, but the womb tells us that maniusri returns to his previous form reappearing as a bodhisattva of Sakyamuni buddha. his country too returns to its previous quantity. the most striking difference is probably the fact that the role of the second buddha is held by a personage who is a bodhisattva of sakyamuni, and not by some unrelated ancient relic tathagata. The authors of the womb sutra probably felt that the importance given to prabhutaratna tathagata in the lotus sutrd was incompatible with their sakyamuni-centered world view. Final remarks The comparative textual investigations presented in this paper relate to only a fraction of the available data. The analysis is intended as an example of how literary and ideational processes can be demonstrated and interpreted. i hope that the present study could clarify, at least partially, why a certain buddhist community reacted to the lotus sutra the way it did. in many instances we see that the authors of the womb are striving to confer a different message to the data they borrowed from the lotus. one of their central concerns must have been to reinforce faith in sakyamuni buddha and to fully restore his supreme authority. For this purpose they intentionally exploited and transformed narrations of the lotus, as well as of other earlier sutras, which they thought were undermining sakyamuni's prestige.  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies acomparative study between the womb and the lous sztra(.legittiMo) KotsUkI, haruaki(小槻晴明),sanskrit lotus sutra muscript ffiom universipy of okyo Generol library.,2003,tokyo. legittimo, elsa, anabysis ofthe pusa chutai iing菩薩處胎経(〓12,no.384), intemnational college for postgraduate buddhist Studies, Phd thesis, 2006, tokyo, (publication planned in the series melonges chinois ef bouddhiques of the institut belge des hautes Eudes Chinoises. bruxelles, in8). Toda, hirofumi(戸田宏文),sanskrit lotus sutra mamuscript from the nationlarchives of Nepal ,1991,tokyo. 7)for the citations from chapter sixteen of the womb sztra discussed in this first part of the 1)"The yimalakirtiniresa's Narration on the amrta distribution and its exploitation by the pusa chutai jing's authors", jjournalofindicn ad buddhist studies,〓07,tokyo. 2)the sutra heldby the bodhisattva within the womb, the pusa chutai jing(菩薩處胎経),<ref><canon>T</canon><v>12</v>, no.<w>38</w>p.<p>0125</p></ref> 3)The sctipture was translated around the year4dby zhu fonian(佛念).inmy doctoral hesis (cf. lgittimo,206)inoted that there is sufficient internal and external evidence that indicates that the work is not a chinese composition. 4)for chapter nine of the womb sutra cf. p.101b26. 〓for chapter eleven cf. p.103b1-23. 6)for chapter thirteen cf.122. comparison cf. p.103a. 8)for the sanskriti have mainly used to191and kotsuki.cf. also burnou1925. 9)The origin and formation of this triangular motive association certainly deserves a detailed future study comprising a11 available sources 10)The text says肉響which literally means "tlesh-chignon'. 11)cf. <ref><canon>T</canon><v>12</v>,no.p.<p>105</p></ref>. 12)The chapter on maniust〓s metamotphosis(文殊身變化品),cf. p.140b19. 13)inapreceding passage the same world is called "floral light"(花光世界). 14)prainakuta, the "summit of wisdom' bodhisattva is a famous bodhisattva who appears already in archaic sutra translations as well as in later texts. except in the lotus, the womb sitrq and the uahakaruncnirdes ai jing大哀經,<ref><canon>T</canon><v>13</v>,no.<w>398</w></ref>,tr.by dharmaraksa) in which he plays protagonist roles, he is a passive and silent figure. (key words)初期大乗仏教,竺佛念,lotus sutra,『處胎経』,二佛 (ludwig-Maximilians-universitat munchen, post-doctoral reseacher)  
</root>
