<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies Relics, Relic worship and stupas in the chinese Translation of the ekottariko-agamd Elsa lEGittiMo Introductory notes The present paper focuses on relics and stupas fromm the point of view of an indo-central akottarika-agama a) version that has only survived ia chinese translation of the fourth century a.d. this collection is nominally equivalent to the pali anguttara-nikaya but differs partly from it in substance. The chinese and the pali "numerical commpendiums" represent the only two know complete versions. The chinese ea preserves references to early buddhist teachings, some of which have not survived in other versions, as well as numerous traces of doctrinal evolution. These seemingly contradictory aspects are not mutually exclusive and most likely indicate that the collection was transmitted orally for a long time, possibly up to the time of its translation into chinese at the end of the fourth century.a lng oral transmission process could account for the "natural growth" of the collection. this supposition goes hand in hand with the hypothesis that the extant Ea might still be the translation made by buddhasmrti (Zhu Fonian佛念)inchang'an(長安)ina.d. on the basis of the exposition recited by Dharmanandi(曇摩難提),2) possibly from memory.) the ea often bears the imprint ol Buddhasmrti's translation style and terminology. inconnection with the topic of this paper, ts particular transcription for stupa should be noted.4) like most buddhist scriptures the eacontains prescriptions that applied to the religious community to which it belonged. as we will see, stupas and relics must have played an impottant role for themm. The passages discussed in this paper have, with two exceptions, no pali parallel. siupas and the merit or demerit related to their constructions In ancient india up to thecentury a.da stupa containing real of symbolic relics was built as a compact monument. aa sutra prescribing formalities related to certair  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies (58)relics, relic worship and stupcs in the chinese translation of the ekottarika-aguma lecittimo) seremonies incidentally gives an interesting architectural detail.) the buddha expounds the filve occasions when monks should not face or turn towards a ceremony or rite(向禮): "when staying within a stupa(在偸婆中),in a crowd of people, on the road, ill and bedridden or at the time of drinking and eating(飲食時).? as walk-in stupas have never been discovered, "to stay within a stupa" certainly refers to the construction around a stupa, a locus commumis of early buddhist monastic architecture: the building in which a stupa was placed as a symbol for the buddha's presence. as such stupa halls developedin buddhist monasteries and temples after the buddha's mirvana, the passage and eventually the whole sutra is a later addition. In another easutra the bhagavat expounds the four brahmanical merits (brahma-punya 梵福).6)I quote the first two: "if believing good men or good women build a stupa in a place where there was none, the fact ol having been able to build such a stupa corresponds to the first brahma-punyd. further, if they re tore an ancient temple(補治故寺),this corresponds to the second brahma-pumya. The express request to build a stupa where there is none appears in a nearly identical way in abhidharmic treatises translated after the ea, for example, in the abhidharma (maha ) vibhasa. both extant chinese translations of this work state that there are four ways people 〓an produce brahma-punya: "The first [ way] is to build a stupa in a place where there is none yet, for the relics ofa buddha/tathagata." according to another sutra, merit can also be acquired by taking care of a stupa in accordance with afive-fold prescription:8 〓 The eatth should be sprinkled with water, stones and [broken pieces of] eatthenware should be removed, its suirounding ground should be leveled, the ground should be swept with propel attention/with a proper mind(端意掃地)and dirt and evil should be eliminated(除去穢惡).by these five modes the person cleaning a stupg will acquire merit. 〓 contrast, destroying a stupa causes great demerit. asutra on the eight great hells,9  filled with sordid details on the pains inflicted to the beings, explains the causes leading to such unfottunate destinies. " one of the hells is called avici. beings who kill their parents, who damage a buddhist stipa(壤 佛倫婆),who create schism in the samgha, or who follow evil, decadent views acting according to these evil doctrines, a11 [these kind of sins andor a11 the people who commit them] can not be cured or washed."  The japanese sociationof indian and buddhisstudies Relics, relic worship and stupas in the chinese translation ofthe ekottarika-agama (. legittimo)(59) as we will see in the next section, merit in connection with stupa worship always derives from the worship petformed with regards to its factual or symbolic relics. Relics among the extant nikoycs and agamas only the ea contains a sutra entirely devoted to Maitreya's future buddhahood.i this sutra the future buddha maitreya expounds in verses what people should do to come close to him. The fifth gotho is: Sakyamuni's followers(釋種)11)who are goodinconverting [the beings], by worshipping a11 the 〓lics(供養諸舍利)[and] performing ceremonies and dharma related worship, [they] now com to where i amn. 〓n a sutra explaining the eight reasons for great earthquakes,) relics are mentioned in a very peculiar place. The text has several parallels, two ipali (dighanikoya and anguttara-ikaya) and severalin chinese.13) the parallel versions explain the first cause for an earth-quake in approximately the same way:This great earth rests on water, the water rests or wind and the wind exists in space. when great winds blow they shake the water and the shaken water causes the earth to shake." The ea however says. 〓this Jambudvipa measures from south to north20yojanas, from east to west 7yoianas, and it is8yojanas thick. The thickness of the water is 84yojancs. The thickness of the fire is8yoranas. underneath the fire the thickness of the wind is68yoianas. underneath the wind there is the boundary with the diamond circle (vairacakra金剛輪).14)the totality of the relics of a11 the past buddhas is in that space. when the winds move, the fire also moves, when the fire moves, the water also moves, and when the water moves, the earth will also move. The voiracakrq refers to the lowest layer of the world and to its outermost circle and is not a typical concept of early buddhism. This layer of relics is reminiscent of the relic land (vajraksetra金剛刹)of the womb-sutra that contains a11 the buddhas' relics which consist of a single solid mass (ekaghama sarira全身舍利).15 The parallels know no such vairacakra layer. The cosmological expansion we see in the eA,i.e. the vairacakra full of relics underneath the other, more traditional layers is certainly an interpolation. The other texts of the ea which mention stupcs and relics refer to relics of particular Buddhist disciples or ancient buddhas. alg sutra of the ea is dedicated to sariputra's (shelifu舍利弗)nirvana and more precisely to his relics.1)The text says that after sariputra's mirvana, his relics are taken care of by ananda and the buddha himself.  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studie (60)relics, relic worship and stupas in the chinese translation ofthe ekottarika-agama  legittimo) of particular interest is the sutra on mahapraiapati's da'aidao大愛道)nirvana, the stepmother and aunt of the buddha.1 The narration exists in various versions.18)whel Mahapraiapati hears that the buddha will shortly enter mirvana, she wishes to enter nipvand before him. a group of five hundred nuns, and later two sramaneri(沙彌尼)follow her example and also enter nirvana. Thereafter, when the gods want to handle the relics of these holy women and perform the necessary rituals, the buddha announces he will do this himself: 〓 [Regarding ] the mothers of the past buddha-bhagavats who previously obtained nipvana, the buddha-bhagavats a11 performed the worship and the cremation(蛇旬)of the relics by themselves."19 the buddha then orders the construction of stupos over the relics of a11 of these holy women and adds that four types of people deserve to have stupas built over theit remains. tathagatas, cakravartin kings, sravakas, and pratyekabuddhas. Those who build stupas for them will receive immeasurable luck. Three sutras of the eanarrate stories about past buddhas' nirpana and inform us about their relics. although the sutras were expounded on different occasions and the persons names as well as certain components of the stories differ, the frame is very similar. The first passage refers to a tathagata called dengguang(燈光)whose sanskrit name might be pradipa. 0) king prasenajit (bosini波斯匿)is the main interlocutor of the buddha throughout the sutra. The buddha tells him the story of a king called 〓lord of the earth" (dizhu地主).to this king a son is boin with the 32signs of a great being. when the son grows older he leaves the palace and practices the path until he becomes a buddha called pradipa tathagata. when the tathagata enters nipvona his father, the king, builds a stupa (神寺)over his relics and 8,0,0,0arhot temples. at that time he is 700,00 years old and he lives another 700, years during which he worships the tathagata's relics. after hearing this story prasenaiit converts to buddhism. 〓n the occasion ofa great donation from king ajatasatru sheshi阿閣世),the buddha tells ananda and the monks the story of a ancient king called " good government" (shan-huaihi善化治).〓1)to summarize: this king has a son called 〓Thoughts of love""(ainian愛 念),who leaves the household and becomes a buddha. when he passes away, his father takes the relics, performs the funerary rites ye wei耶維),〓) builds a great divine shrine (stnpa大神祠)there and regularly pays worship to his son. this story has a partial parallel 〓ali: the buddha's previous name is susima and his father is not a king but a brahmin called Samkha. the stupa is not built by the father but by pratyekabuddhas and other  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies Relics, relic worship and stipas in the chinese translation of the ekottarika-agama (.legittiMo)(61 people. when looking for his son, the brahmin finds the freshly erected stupa, takes car of its surroundings and worships it. The third related passage tells the story of a king called "repercussion" or " echo of Sound" (yinxiang音響)who named his son subhuti (xuputi須菩提).〓4)the son leaves the household, becomes a buddha and enters nipvana. his father, the king, is then instructed by sakra devanam indra to perform a cremation ceremony in the same way as for a cakrg. vartin king, and to erect a stupa(倫婆)over the buddha's relics. The three narrations have a similar progression. whether they originally referred to one and the same story must be left undecided. Final remarks stupas are monuments that should be erected and well maintained. Such deeds product great merit, and, of course, stupas should not be willfully destroyed, except one wishes to be reborn i one of the worst infernal abodes. within the knogamanikoya literature the idea that building a stupa leads to immeasurable merit in the brahma-heaven occurs only in the eA. whether there should be any relics in the newly constructed stupa, and if so, exactly whose relics, is left to our imagination. likewise. relics are neither mentioned in relation to the merit acquired through stupa maintenance, nor in the singular passage that refers to a monk staying within a stupa hall. in contrast, the poem expounded by Maitreya makes o reference whatsoever to stupcs but states that devotional worship of the Buddhas' relics leads to rebirth at the time of his buddhahood. despite these peculiarities, stupas and relics are not dissociated. The sutras that narrate the stories of buddhist disciples' and ancient buddhas" nirvana clearly illustrate the triangular connection, which exists between stupas, relics and their worship. of particular interest is that the buddha handles sariputra's and his stepmother's relics himself. The above passages itrefutably show the narrative and philosophical importance of relics and the monuments enshrining them from the perspective of the ancient holders of the ea. Nots 1)The zengyi ahcn jing(増壹阿含經,<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,no.<w>12,</w><p>549</p>-<c>b</c><l>830</l><c>b</c></ref>) 2)The buddhist canonical tradition handed down a different text transmission history and viewed the present collection as the second translation made by gautama Samghadeva(曇僧 伽提婆)in397a.d. The issue of the ekottarik-agama's translation has been discussed by  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies (62)relics, Relic worship and stupas in the chinese translation ofthe ekottarika-ogamg (. legittiMo) several Japanese scholars, see for example: mzuno(1956,1989),unebe(1968), wart (1973),okayaa(984)and enomoto(984,1986).the buddhasmrti-hypothesis is corroboratedby a forthcoming case study lgitti28). 3)In the zengyi aham jingxu daoan says that dhatmanandi knew two agamnas by heart, one of them the ekottarik-agama (cf. <ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,no.<w>125</w>,p<p>412</p></ref>). 4)stupais never translated as tg(塔),but always as toupo(倫婆),arather uncommon teim for which buddhasmrti had a predilection as it is also found in other translations by him buddhasmrti also uses the term shensi(神寺),literally "divine temple" or "gods' shrine"", foi Buddhist temple andor stupa. 5)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>699</p><c>c</c></ref>. 6)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>656</p>-<p>656</p><c>c</c></ref>. 7)for the abhicharm (maha) vibhasa cf. <ref><canon>T</canon><v>27</v>,no.<w>1553</w>-<p>21</p></ref>(tr. by xua ang玄奘in the middle of the 7th century) and <ref><canon>T</canon><v>8</v>,no.<w>154319</w><p>1</p>-<p>22</p></ref>(tr. by buddhavarman浮陀跋摩 between739), 8)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>688</p><c>b</c>-<p>688</p><c>c</c></ref>. 9)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>778</p></ref> 10)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>787</p>-<p>789</p><c>c</c></ref>. This sutra is identical to the " Sutra on maitreya's coming down to birth""(彌 勒下生經,〓1,no.453.see legittio 2(forthcoming).from the time of its translation into chinese the sutra formed part of the ea. it was translated by buddhasmrti, and only later uirculated also as a separate text that was then wrongly attributed to dharmaraksa(竺法護). 11)lit. the seeds of sakya, i.e. the sakya clan, but also the followers of sakyamuni's teachings. 12)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>753</p><c>c</c>-<p>754</p><c>a</c></ref>. 13)a. vi.70bhumicul, d.1. parinibbana s.30,the chinese ma(1,no.7778b), the chinese d1,no.1,15-16a), and the vinaycksudrakavast of the mulasarvastivadins, cf. waldtscHidt1951,212d <ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,no.<w>14,388</w><p>a</p></ref>. See also leGittiM,2-26,67. 14)The chinese term might be atranslation of vajrc-cakra or vairo-mandala. 15)cf. lgittio5,69,and the pus chutai jing(苦薩處胎經,<ref><canon>T</canon><v>12</v>,no.,<w>1026</w></ref>) 16)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>639</p><c>b</c></ref>. 17)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>821</p><c>b</c>-<p>823</p><c>b</c></ref>. 18)a11 the extant versions on mahapraiapati gautami's nitvana have been discussed by sylvair Levisvaghosa, le sutralamkara et ses sources", journl asiatique, vol. xii, paris19, p.117 19)she 〓um(蛇旬)is found eleven times in to sutras of the ekottorik-agama and nowhere else. it might be a repeated copyist's error for ye xun(耶旬),a transcription for the act of performing a cremationhyopita). fot an overview on the indic and chinese terms used in Buddhist texts for cremation, cf. sei's entry in the hobogiyin8,57-585. 20)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>609</p><c>a</c>-<p>611</p><c>c</c></ref>. this king seems to be unrelatedto candapaiiota whose name in chinese trans-lations is also dengguang. 〓 〓 21)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>,<p>728</p><c>a</c></ref>.  The japanese ociation of indian and buddhis studies Relics, relic worship and stupas in the chinese translation of the ekottarika-ogama (. legittimo)(63) 22)Note the different transcription. 23)cf. the " gangarohanavatthu", pali: noran112, vol.ii,p.4449,english: burlingamE 1921, vol. iii, p.168-176. 24)<ref><canon>T</canon><v>2</v>.<p>81</p><c>b</c>-<p>817</p><c>a</c></ref>. abbreviations jb.journalofindiam ad buddhist studies『印度学仏教学研究』 bSR. budclhist studies review 〓js sengokuyaa .journalofbuddhist stdies『仙石山論集』 〓a transactions of the asiatic sociepyofjapcn bibliography buingamE, eugene watson, buddhist legendhammapad commentary, vol. ii, harvard oriental series, vol.3, cambridge, massachusetts 1921. Legittimo, elsa, "The natural surroundings of the buddha's last trip. notes o environmental Topics in the mahaparinirvana-sutra", sbs, vol. i, sept.〓,p.1-72. -,"synoptic presentation of the p chu tai jing-I(chapters1-14,sjbs, vol. ii, septemmber5,p.1-11. -,Reopening the maitreya files-two almost identical early maitreya-sutra translations in the Chinese canon. wrong attributions and text-historical entanglements", sjournal of the jnterna-tionl asociationofbudchist stucies, vol.29,no.2,08, [p.1-4, forthcoming. Makl, tatsugen牧達玄,a study of the devaduta-sutra of the ekottarika-agama 3-,「『増一 阿含経善聚品32-4・天使経』考」,bs, vol.34,no.1, dec.1985,p.148-153. Mayeda, egaku, "japanese studies on the schools of the chinese agamas", heinz bechert (ed.), zur schulzugehorigkeit von werken der hiayan-literatur, erster teil, gottingen198, p.3. Norman, h. c., the commentryo the dhammapadd, vol. ii, ptS, london191 Seidel, anna, "dabi茶毘",hobogirin, vol. iv,1983,p.573-585. Shizutani, masao静谷正雄,"The school affiliation of the ekottarik-ogumd's chinese trans-ation"「漢訳『増一阿含経』の所属部派」,〓bs, vol.21,no.2,1973,p. &lt;Key words&gt;初期仏教,増一阿含経,竺仏念,舎利,塔 (postdoctoral researcher)  
</root>
