<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies *parikalpa used in the mahayanasamgraha MaTSuda Kuninori 1.Introduction As is well known, parikapa(遍計,能遍計,etc.) plays an important role in the thoughts of the Yogacara school, as is represented by the phrases parikatpita and abhutaparikalpa. However, the significance of parikapaitself, its position in the yogacara doctrine, its rela-tion with vikalpa, and so on, do not seem to have been clarified through reviewing each piece of literature. In fact, porikalpa means, roughly speaking, to imagine incorrectly that which does not exist as it is. This interpretation would hardly cause any problem, but it seems important to examine it philologically and to determine its meaning in each context. In this paper, i would like to start by clarifying something about the temm*parikalpa used in the mahayanasamgraha (MS) through the descriptions of the MS and its com-mentary mahoyanasamgrahopanibandhana (mSU). 2.basic characteristic of parikatpa We can find the description of parikalpa below in the mS, where it is directly explained ・MSI.16 yang kutu rtogpyod cing kuntu brtgs par byaba yod na kun brtgs pa'i ngo bo mid do de la kuntu rtogpa mi gang yin kutu brtags par bya bamicizhig/ kuntu brtgsp'i ngo bo nyid ni ggzhe n/ yid kyi rnam pr shes p mi kuntu rg ste/ rnm pr rogp gyipbyir ro de mi rang briodpa'i bag chogs byi sa bo byung ba dang/ rnmpr rigpa thams cd kyi briod p'i bg chags kyi sa bo byung ba'ode lta bs na rnm mtha'ys pa'i rnmpr rogp dg gis 'byung ste  thams cdu rogpas kutu rtogpzhes bya bas na kunu rtogpzhes by'o …nagao ed. and when * parikalpa exists and when * parikalpya exists, then *parikalpitasvabhava exists. Question: among them, what is * parikalpa, what is * parikalpya, and what is *parikalpitasv-bhava?  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies answer:* manoviinana is * parikalpa because it is associated with*vikalpa. [d] it is [of twc kinds]:that which has arisen from the seeds of*vasana of own words and that which has ariser from the seeds of*vsand of words of a11*viinaptis. Therefore, it arises from*vikalpa of infnite kinds. [That is to say], because it supposes in every respect, it is said to imagine(*pari-vkip Therefore, it called * parikalpa.. The MSu comments on this passage as follows ・MSu ad mSIi.16 yang kuu ogpayod cing zhes bya bss pa kun brigs pdpyod dot yid kyi rnampar shes pmi ku rto ste/ rnmpr r cm gyi phyir rozhes byba mi nges par rtogp dang yies su dri rnam par rtog p dang 'brelpi phyir ro/ rang briodpa'i bag chags kyi s bon ls byung bzhes bya ba mi yid kyi rnm pr shes yi kyi rnm pr shes 〓zhes thog ma med pa'i 'khor ba ma tha snyd u biodp ste de 'i bag chags mi 'diii sa boo rm par 〓ig  thams cd kyi briodpi bg chags kyi sabo byung b hes bya ba mi 'di liar gzugs ss p mtha 'ys par snang ba'i rnampor rigpa brjodp'i bag chags kyi  byung ba ste/ der snang bar 'byung bai ishul ci phyir rode'i phyir yid kyi rnmpr shes pa mi rnm mtha 〓p rmpar rgpa thams cd his 'bymng b'odi26b3ff./pli277b1ff. [The passage]"and when*parikalpa exists, and."explains * parikapita.* manovinana is tparikatpa because it is associated with*vikaipa, because it is associated with*abhinirupand-vikalpd and * anusmaranavikatpa. [as for]"that which has arisen from the seeds of*vasana of own words," there are verbal ac-tivities, such as"*manoviinana""*manoviinana," in the beginningless transmigration,* vosana of which are the seeds of this[*parikalpa/*manoviinana]. [The phrase] "that which has arisen from the seeds of*vasano of words of a11*iinaptis' [means] that which has arisen from the causes of*sand of words of*iinaptis, which appear as such like*rupa of infinite kinds, because it has the way of arising with such appearance. Therefore, *manovinana arises with a11*vikalpa of infinite kinds First, in this context, the reason that * parikalpais regarded as* manoviinana is, briefly speaking, being accompanied by* vikalpa, and its meaning is the same as that used in the Abhidharmic context, as kata1975:p.13of., n.1」points out. Second, porikolpa is classifed into two types from the viewpoint of 〓 which*vsano of words has it arisen from", that is to say, that which is related to* manovijnana itself and that which is related to*iynapti. we will separately examine these two points below.  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies 3.being accompanied by*vikapa 3.1.The case of abhidharma literature First of a11, we confirm the abhidharmic understanding of two ( three) vikalpas that are concerned with the reason that * parikalpais accompanied by*vikalpa. These are described as follows in the akbhadakI,k.33, where the reason that the five viinanakoyas are said "not to be associated with vikalpa" is explained akbh aaKI.k.3ab: trividhah kil vikalpah/ svabhavabhinirupananusmaranavikalpah/ td es svabhavavikalpo sti netarau/ tasmad avikapaka ipyucyante/ yathaikapadako svo 'padaka iti/ ejima ed.35.6f. The meanings of these three vikalpas are as follows: tatra svabhovavikalpo vitarkah/ s caittesu pascan nirdeksyate/ itarau punah kimsvabhavau/ ltis said that vikalpais threefold, viz., svabhava [vikalpa], abhinirupanal vikapa], and anusmara novikalpa. Then, these [five vinanakoyas] have svabhavavikalpa, but not the other two. Therefore [these] are said "not to be associated with vikalpd" just as a one-footed horse is said "not to be as-sociated with a foot." The meanings of these three vikalpos are as follows akbh adakI.k.33: yathakramam 〓u prqjina manasi vyagra smrtih sarvaiva manasi/ manoviinanasamprayukta projna manasity ucyate/ asamahita vyagrepy ucyate/ sa hy abhinirupand-vikalpah/ mansyev sarva smrtih samahit casamahito canusmaranavikalpah/ ejiMa ed.35.9ff. among them, the svabhavavikalpa is vitarka, which will be explained later in the place where cait-tas [will be explained]. on the other hand, what do the other two have as their nature? successively, those two lphrases] are the distracted mental praina and a11 the mental smrti. The praino associated with manovinana is called "mental." That which is not concentrated is saic to be " distracted." This is the abhinirupanavikalpa. the mental and a11, [namely] concentrated and not concentrated, smrtiis the anusmaranavikalpa. Because this explanation is derived from the concern of how to put each vikalpa into the Abhidharmic system of dharmas, it is not necessarily self-evident what role each vikalpa plays. still, at least as far as we follow this explanation, these two vikalpas are defined from the beginning as those that are associated with manoviynana, and for that reason manoviinana is said to be associated with vikalpa. therefore, there is no problem with the fact that manoviinana is associated with vikapa, but on the other hand, it is not obvious what the relation is between parikalpa and its being associated with vikalpa.4)  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies 3.2.Yogacara literature Next, we examine how these three vikalpas are treated in the Yogacara literature. The [ollowing passage ofaSbh is comparatively well arranged: ・aSh1(v): samnam vijnananam kati viinanani savikalpakami kapy avikalpakami/ tribhis tovad vikalpaih manovi jnanam ekam savikapakam/ trayo vikalpah svabhavavikapo 'nusmaranavikalpo 'bhinirupanavi-kalpas ca tatra svabhavavikapah prapyupannesu smskaresv anubhuyamanesu yh svalaksanako. ro vikalpah/ ausmaranaviklpo yo 'nubhutapurvasams karakorah/ abhinirupanavikalpo y 'titanagataprapyutpannesu viparoksesv abhyuhanakaro vikappahf1. tala ed.16.ff. among six vinanas, how mamy vinanas are associted with vikapa and how many are not associat-ed with vikalp? First, only manoviinana is associated with vikalpa with three vikalpos. yikalpa is threefold, viz., svq bhavavikapa, amusmaranavikalpa, and abhinirupanavikalpa. among them, the svabhovavikapa is the vikapa that has the form of its own characteristic of present samskoras that are being experi-enced. The anusmaranavikalpa is that which have the form of previous samskoras which have bee1 experienced. The abhinirupanavikalpais that which has the form of conjecture toward previous, fu-ture, and present lsamskoras」 that are imperceptible.. This explanation, because there is no abhidharmic restriction of the classification of dharmas, makes it very easy to understand that there are three vikalpas according to the objects or forms of vikopas. Nevertheless, its relationship with*parikalpa is not more clear than that is in the abhidharma literature. The descriptions usedin both of the texts only show that the reason, "being accompanied by vikalpa," which is applied with three vikalpas in the MSu c lead to the fact that that which is accompanied by vikalpa is* manovijnana, but do not show its relationship with *parikalpa. 4.*manovipiinon and*vasano of words 4.1.*vaisaa of words Now, we will examine the classification of parikalpa from the viewpoint of " which *レsana of words has it arisen from? First of a11, we confirm how vasana of words(名言熏習)is treated in the MS. The mSu ad MS I.58, where three types of*vasanas are explained as a classification of *〓layaviinana, reads as follows:  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhiststudies ・MSU ad MSi.58 …mngonpar briodpa'i bag chags kyi bye brag ces bya ba mi bdag dang chos dang/ bya bar mngon par briodpa th snyad btgs p rnams te/ iha dang mi dang mig dang/ gzugs dang/ 'gro'ozhes bya bssp'i bag chags sna tshogs yin te us pai khydpar gng ls bdg dang/ chos dang/ by ba'i mngonpar briodpar 'byung ba'ori27b5ff/pi26b5ff. …a variety ofvosand of words means that various*vusana of words, viz., verbal activities, of the self, dharmas and actions, lthat is, for example], 〓deity,' chuman,' 'visual organ,' "fom,' 'o and so on, from which[*vosana], viz., a particular ability(*saktivisesa)the verbal activities ot the Self. dtharmas and actions arise. according to this commentary,*vasana of words exist as [a part of]*layavijnana, which is caused by verbal activities about something and at the same time causes future verbal activities of the same kind. 4.2.Relationship with*maoviinong Second, we examine the relationship between the above-mentioned*vasana of words and*manoviinana, which is mainly explained in the latter half of the mSii.2, where 11 *vijnaptis which is * paratantralaksana are related with three* vasanas. The following is the passage concemned with*vasana of words: ・MSIi.2 de l lus dang lus c dzbapo't rnam par rig p gang yip dang/ des mye bar spyad p 〓ya ba'i rnmpr rigp gang 〓i dang/ de l mye bar spyodpa'i rnmpar rigp gang yi dang/ dus dang/ grangs dang/ yul dang/ tha snyad kyi rnampar rig pa gang yinp de mi mngonpr biodpa'i bag chags kyi sabos byung ba'i phyir ronaao ed. That is because among them(1*vinaptis), the*vinaptis of body, body-holder, and enjoyer, the *vinapti that is enjoyed by it, the* vinapti of its enjoyment and the*viinaptis of time, number, place, and verbal activity, they have arisen from the seeds of*vasana of words. According to the tibetan translation of the mSU,*manovinana is considered as*vi-jnapti of enjoyer. to sum up these descriptions, we can fnd that* manoviinana has arisen from the seeds of*vsana of words. 4.3.position of*iinapti Here the important point to note is the position of* vinaptis from the beginning. ・MSI.2 de l gzhan gyi dbang gi mtsh nyid gg zhe na/ gang kun gzhi rnam par shes pa'i sa bon yang dgpa ma yinpa kun rogpcs bsdus p'i rnampar rigp'o. nagao ed. Question: among them, what is * paratantralaksana.  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies answer: itis* vijnapti that has * alayavijnana as seed andis connoted by*abhutaparikalpa..  Thus, we can find that the two descriptions given in the MSii.2and the MSii.16are parallel: in the former case,*viinapti arises from the*alayaviinana and can be thought to be [a part of]*abhutaparikalpa, in the latter case,* manovijnana arises from the*vosana of words and can be called e parikalpa."as is mentioned above,* manovijnana is a kind of *viinapti and*saa of words is a kind of * alayaviinana. according to this correspon dence, we could say that * parikalpais a kindof *abhutaparikalpa in this context. 5.conclusion So far, we have outlined the descriptions o parikalpa given in the MSIi.16and its commentary MSU. The following conclusions are drawn the reason is mainly being associated with*vika-lpa that* vikolpa is considered as*manoviinana in the MSii.16,but that is based on the relationship from the first between*layavijnona and*vijinaptis explained in the mSii.2. And it is thought that the mS selected*manoviinana, which can have some conceptual function, from1*viinaptis. iwould now like to go on to examine its relationship with four and five kinds of *parikalpas that appear in the MSii.19,20and the position of *parikapa used in other Yogacara literature that we could not address in this paper. 1)the mahopanasamgrahabhasmSBh) does not directly comment on this passage. 2)This sentence is a bit diffcult to understand. kaano[197:p.129]seems to conside1 *manoviinana as tha smrad du briod pa, butit seems that this intetpretation is dubious 3)these three vikalpas also appearin the  apitun雜阿毘曇心論(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>28</v>.<p>88</p><c>a</c><l>27</l></ref>ff.),api-damo  piposha lun阿昆達磨大毘婆沙論(<ref><canon>T</canon><v>27</v>.<p>219</p><c>b</c><l>7</l></ref>ff.), and so on. in those cases, their basic understanding is considered to be the same as that of the akbh. 4)this fact may be, ina sense, a matter of course because these texts are abhidharma literature and have different contexts, however, at least we ca confirm that there seems to be no descrip-tion that makes clear the relationship between pari-vkip and vikolpa. 5)it might be natural to translate this as something like"… that various*vsana, viz., a particu lar ability,… from which.."if we supporse the original sanskrit text, but follow the tibetan word order for the present. 6)The explanation appearing in the mSbhad MSI.58seems to show a similar situation. 7)as is well known, the tibetan translation, the chinese translation, and MSbh show different  orrespondences of11*viinaptis to six*viinanas and so on. See kaa197:pp. 53ff.n.  the japanese association of indian and buddhist studies 円 and so forth. the latter two consider* manovijnana as* vinapti of its enjoyment. Texts andabbreviations: 〓 MS. mahayanasamgraha. d.4048p: no.5549;g. M. Nagao ed., tokyo,1982. MSU mahayanasamgrahopanibandhana. d n.405no.5552. Akbh abhidharmakosabhasya, y. ejiMa ed., tokyo,1989. ssbh abhidharmasamuccayabhasya, n. tatia ed., patna,1976. bibliography : katano. michio [197] indo bukkyo mi okeru nishiki shiso no kenkyu(インド仏教における唯 識思想の研究),bun'eido, kyoto in japanese) sucuRo, shinjo and ShiMOkawabE, kiyoshi [2007]:sho daijo roseshin shau, genjo yaku)(摂 大乗論(世親釈,玄奘訳)),daizo shuppan, tokyo in japanese). 〓 &lt;Key words&gt; parikapa, manovinana, vikalpa research associate, institute for advanced Studies o sia, university of tokyo)  
</root>
