<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecyin Northern buddhist Texts. 〓attempt at classification MatSuMura junko 1.Introduction The story of the bodhisattva receiving the prophecy that he would become sakyamuni Buddha is narrated in both Southern and Northern buddhist literature. precisely for the reason that the story explicitly gives clear thematic emphasis to the importance of becoming a buddha rather than becoming a arhant, it may be regarded as marking a turning point from early buddhism to mahayana buddhism, because in Mahayana buddhism embarking on the ages-long bodhisattva path is far more highly recommended and praised. however, the story is so popular and importantin both northern and Southemn buddhism that there is a plethora of many different versions, so that, if we were to include short references and mentions of the motif, the number of related texts would be almost uncountable. althougk Akanuma, Taga and lamotte made lists of appearances of the story in buddhist literature. and the former two scholars tried to classify versions ofthe story, mainly by comparing the )rder of occurrence of plot elements, their attempts do not seem very successful. The present author has recently examined Pali versions of the story, which is usually known as the sumedhakatha in the Theravada tradition, and so has traced the relationship of the Apadana versions (the dharmarucyapadana and the yasodharapadana) with northerr Buddhist texts.  Following up on that work, the author attempts in this article to list the Northern versions of the story and classify them according to a plausible and rational method, thereby attempting to get a bird's eye view of the different versions in both Southemn and northern buddhist literature. however, because of the diversity and complexity of the story-cycle connected to dipamkara buddha, the author confines herself to treating only texts containing the main plot elements of the story, i.e., dipamkara buddha's appearance in the world, the bodhisattva offering him fowers, the bodhisattva spreading his hair or the mud to stop dipamkara buddha's feet getting soiled, the bodhisattva making a vow to  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies 4)The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecyinnorthem buddhist texts(J. matsuMura become a buddha, and dipamkara buddha giving his prophecy to the bodhisattva. 2.The Three types of dipamkara prophecy story when we examine the northemn versions of the story, they can be classified into three types according to the name of the bodhisattva (the former incamnation of Sakyamuni buddha) Type l, in which the bodhisattva has no proper name, type2, in which the bodhisattva's name is Megha, and Type 3, in which the bodhisattva's name is Sumati. although Sumati is equivalent to Sumedha in the Theravada version, so far no evidence has been found to suggest that the name sumedha existed in the northern buddhist versions. Type1)in which the bodhisattva has no proper name: 1a) The xiuxing benqi jing修行本起經,translated by Zhu dali竺大力and kang Meng-xiang康孟詳,197ce, t18446a17-462c9. 1b)The Foshuo taizi ruiying benqi jing佛説太子瑞應本起經,translated by zhiqian支 謙,222-228ce,t1853472c473b11. 1c) the yicha benqi jing異出菩薩本起經,translated by nie daozhen攝道眞,280- 313cE. <ref><canon>T</canon><w>1883</w>.<p>617</p><c>b</c><l>18</l>-<p>617</p><l>029</l></ref>. Type2)in which the bodhisattva's name is Megha: 2a)the mahavastu, ed. Emile senat, i.1-2484the bodhisattva's name is Megha. 2b)the zengyi aham jing増壹阿含經(the ekottarikagama, hereafter abb. ea),scroll 11, translated by僧伽提婆(sanghadeva) or曇摩難提(dhammanandin) and Zhu fonian 空佛念,)34-38,t12529715-5992The bodhisattva's name is Yunlei雲雷 " cloud-thunder").cf.2b)eascroll13,dipamkara buddha's biography is independently narrated in the " dizhu pin"地主品:t1252024-61a13. 2c)The vinaya of the dharmaguptaka, sifenli四分律,translated by佛陀耶舎(bud-dhayasas), zhu Fonian竺佛念and others,4412,8)〓14282.782a-785c229the Bodhisattva's name is Mique彌却(*Megha). 2d) the fo benxing ji jing佛本行集經,translated by闍那崛多(jnanagupta),587-591 CE,t1903664a12-6693the bodhisattva's name is Yun雲("cloud").11) 2e) the puzg hui菩薩藏會(bodhisattvapitaka) in the maharatnakutasutra大寶積 經,translated by xuanzang玄奘,〓) sometime between45-64, t3101117a16 319b221the bodhisattva's name is Miga迷伽(*Megha). 2e')the foshuo dasheng puszg hengfa jing佛説大乘菩薩藏正法經,translated by  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecy in northem buddhist texts(j. MatSumuRa)(6 法護(dharmapala) and others, llth century (an independent translation of the bodhisatt-vapitakasutra), <ref><canon>T</canon><v>316</v>:<p>11882</p><c>b</c><l>6</l>-<p>884</p><c>a</c><l>8</l></ref>: the bodhisattva's name is baoyun〓雲("jew-el-cloud"). 〓e and2e'were not includedin the lists made by akanuma, taga and lamotte. Type 3) in which the bodhisattva's name is Sumati: 32)the divvavaduna, No.18dharmarucyavadana, ed. cowell and neil, 246The Bodhisattva's name is Sumati. 3b)the bodhisattvavadanakalpalata by ksemendra, No.89dharmarucyavadana, ed. Candra das and chandra vidyabhusana,772-821,vaidya, iiThe bodhisattva's name is Sumati. 3c) the guoqu xianzai yinguo jing過去現在因果經,translated by求那跋陀羅(guna-hadra).435-44E. 〓18930c15-623The bodhisattva's name is Shanhui善 慧("good wisdom"). 3d) The fo benxing jing佛本行經,translated by Shi baoyun釋寶雲,early sth century, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>193</w>-<v>7</v></ref>the bodhisattva's name is Shansi善思("good thought"). The original Sanskrit for the chinese words善慧and善思could be sumedha, as in the Pali version, but there is no evidence to support the supposition that the original Skt word was Sumedha. however, there is evidence to show that the original Sanskrit was Sumati , passages such as the following examples from the dazhidulun大智度論show that Sumati was the name widely knownin northern buddhist texts:"須摩提菩薩,秦言妙意,見然燈 佛無供養具"(〓150922762-3)and"又如須摩提菩薩,見燃燈佛從須羅娑女,買 五莖花不肯與之"(316b2-21). there is no doubt that Megha and Sumati are derived from Sumedha, it is not possible that both remaining forms could be derived from either megha or Sumati. however, this fact does not necessarily mean that the northern versions are derived from the Pali version, the sumedhakatha , it can be supposed that the core of the story was formed somewhere in India, and then developed independently in different areas, or in different sects. type1 versions, where the bodhisattva has no proper name, obviously belong to the older stratum The early dates of their translation into chinese also support this supposition. 3.dipamkara buddha's birth, enlightenment and visit to the capital city Inorder to establish whether the classification of the Northern versions into the above three  〓he japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studie )the story of the dipamkara buddha prophecy in northerm buddhist Texts (J. atsuMuRa 〓 types can be also verified by differences between other elements in the story, we will1 examine the frst part of the story, i.e., dipamkara's birth, his enlightenment, and his visit to king's capital city where the bodhisattva is to receive the prophecy that he will become Sakyamuni buddha. The pali version of dipamkara buddha's birth story, narrated in bv-a 78,4-83,18(Eng. tr.: homner11-121),is obviously a later stereotyped fabrication imitating Gotama buddha's birth story. it will therefore not be taken into consideration. in the following, a summaty ofeach version will be given. 1a) the xinxing benqi jing修行本起經 Long ago, there was a cakravartin king called dengsheng燈盛.his kingdom was called tiheyi (o1 Tihewei)提和衞(*dipavati), and his crown prince was dengguang燈光.the king transferrec he kingdom to the crown prince on his demise, but the crown prince, having realized the imperme nence (of the world), handed the kingdomover to his younger brother, renounced the worldly life, and became dipamkara buddha(錠光佛).having wandered through various countries in the com-pany of 620,00monks, he returned once to his homeland to save its people. however, the king of his homeland (i.e. dipamkara's younger brother) thought that his brother would usurp the kingdom, and so tried to prevent his visit. dipamkara buddha then, with supematural powers, created a second capital city. Seeing that, the king was terrified and relented, and asked dipamkara buddhe to visit his capital seven days later, and to accept offerings from him.(461b16-c16) In this text the bodhisattva's name is introduced as follows. "at that time there wase brahman youth called wugouguang是時有梵志儒童,名無垢光"(461c17).however he name無垢光," pure light," appears only here, and in the latter part of the story the Bodhisattva is only mentioned as rutong儒童which corresponds to Skt manava. since無 垢光seems to be unusual as a word translated from Skt, we may suppose that the worc was addedby the translators, or later in the chinese textual transmission. 1b)the taini ruiying benqi jing太子瑞應本起經 Long ago, when dipamkara buddha appeared in the world, the cakravartin king zhisheng制勝 ("victorious" ) ruled over a great kingdom called bomo鉢摩(*padma).1(472c18-19). The bodhisattva is called rutong儒童. 1c) the yica benqi jing異出菩薩本起經:In this text, although the story of dipam-kara's birth is not related, the following informationis important for comparison. The bodhisattva met dipamkara (tihanjieluo題宏竭羅)1〓 buddha in the capital city, bomohe鉢 摩詞(*padamaka) , of the king qiye耆耶(*Jaya. 2a) The mahovastu. dipamkara was born in the capital city, dipavati, as the son of the cakravartin king arcimat and  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecyin northern buddhist Texts (j. atsuMuRa)( his consort Sudipa. 2b)the zengyi aham jing増壹阿含經:Inthe main story in scroll 11,the biography of dipamkara is not narrated, dipamkara buddha定光如來is invited to receive offerings by King guangming光明of the great kingdom bomo鉢摩(*padma). however, in scroll13 (〓-b'),dipamkara buddha's biography is independently narrated Long ago, there was a king named dizhu地主("lord ofthe earth") ruling over Jambudvipa(〓浮 里地or〓浮地).the king gave half of his kingdom to his minister, Shanming善明("good-light' *sudipa?).king Shanming's capital city was called yuanzhao遠照(" far-shine"),his queen's name was Yueguang月光("moonlight"), and a crown prince was born and named dengguang燈光. The crown prince renounced the worldly life at the age of29,and on the same night he attained Enlightenment and became dipamkara buddha(燈光如來).when his father, the king, found out that his son had become a buddha, he visited him withkotis of people, they listened to the Buddha's sermon and the 4kotis of people became arhants that very day. The great king, dizhu also visited dipamkara buddha withkotis of people and listened to the buddha's sermon, and the4 kotis of people likewise became arhants. the great king, dizhu, invited dipamkara buddha and 80 kotis of arhants, decorated the city and made a great offering. The great king, dizhu, at that time, wasI (Sakyamuni) myself. (<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1254</w>-<p>6</p><c>a</c><l>13</l></ref>) It is obvious that the story in the scroll1has a different source from the one in the scroll11, and the fact that the Chinese words for dipamkara buddha are also different ma indicate that the present Chinese ea was not translated at one time by one translator. in scrolls 38 and,too, there are stories connecting to dipamkara buddha.8) this means that these stories were originally related independently, and were later compiled into one integrated story. 2c),2d),2e) and 2e'although there are some important differences among these versions, the main plot runs similarly to la and 2b'.because of limitations of space, the corresponding proper names only will be given in the synoptic table below. 3a)the divyavadana: dipamkara's biography is not narrated. he came to king dipa's capital, dipavati, to receive offerings.9)king dipa also invited the king of the neighboring country, vasava. 3b)The bodhisattvavadanakalpalata: since the text's main source is ja, its content is essentially same. however, Vasava is the king of kasi. 3c)the guoqu xiamzai yinguo jing過去現在因果經: Many innumerable ages ago, there was a king called dengzhao燈照(*dipa), and his capital city 〓as called tibopodi提播婆底(*dipavati ).The crown prince was born to the king, and given the  The japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies the story of the dipamkara buddha Prophecvinnorthemn buddhist texts(J. Matsumura) name puguang普光.the crown prince renounced the world when he turned29,000years old. anc after600 years of ascetic practice, he became a buddha called puguang rulai普光如來.his father, the king, rejoiced at his son's achievement, had the roads repaired and decorated, and sent his ministers to invite him to visit.(6226) 3d) the fo benxing jing佛本行經:dipamkara's biography is not narrated. dipamkara's lameis dingguang定光,and he enters the capital city huayan華嚴out of mercy for living beings. (918-b5) 4. Synoptic Table of Proper names In order to show the relationships between the various versions, the proper names featuring in each are shown in the table below. itype 2 versions, dipamkara buddha's father was originally aminister (brahman) ofa powerful king, and was himself made a king by being given a half e, one fourth) of the kingdom. Therefore, the king who gave half of his kingdom to his minister (dipamkara's Father) is, for convenience, given as suzerain king' in the table.  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecyin northern buddhist Texts (J. MatSuMuRa)(6 5.Remarks on the versionin the bodhisattvapitaka of the two chinese versions of the bodhisattvapitaka, dharmapala法護's(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>316</w></ref>)is close to the tibetan translation. inib., asin316,there is no break between chapter 1and12 and chap12has no title, in contrast to xuanzang's translation310),which gives the title:大自在天授記品.the king's name, dgra thul(* jitasatru?, lokeshchandra s.v. fitari) corresponds to chinese勝怨or降怨,but it is natural enough that dharmapala would have understood the word to meaajatasatru阿掲世.the capital city's name, padm c corresponds to盛蓮華(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>310</w></ref>)and蓮華具足(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>316</w></ref>),which may be a translation of Skt Padmaka or padmavati. according to the Tibetan translation, the king's brahman minister was called mar me bdg(dipavat?), and was " as rich as a large sala tree"" (shing s chenpo lta bu).shing s chen(mahosala, or mahasala) corresponds exactly to Dharmapala's大娑羅(according to v.r. ming,in t,大婆羅).23)dharmapala, however understood incorrectly that Mahasala was the name of the king, and therefore he translate( mar me bdog as the king's son,具足燈.〓n3, the king gives his minister only one fourth of his kingdom, but this is a unique reading, and this author surmises that it is a embellishment by xuanzang (703.4)… sari"i bu 'di lta ste/ dkon mchog yan lag tshun chad bskal pa (5) grangs med pa na/ de bzhin gshegs pa mar me mdzad ces bya ba 'jig rten du byung ngo/ yang de'i tshe rgyal po dgra thu zhes bya ba zhig byung ste/ sari'i bu rgyal po dgra thul gyi grong khyer padma ca6)zhes bya ba 'byor pa/ bde ba/ rgyas pa lo legs pa dga' ba/ skye bo mang po dang/ mis gang ba zhig mod do ari'i bu rgyal po dgra thul gyi bramze mar me bdag ces bya ba shing sa la(7)chen po lta bu phyug pa/ nor mang ba/ longs spyad che pa nas/ mdzod dang bang ba"i bar du yongs su gang ba zhig byung ba de/ rgyal po dgra thul la dben cing 'phangs/ sdug cing yid du 'ong (704.1) ste,  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies mthong na mimthun pa med de/ sari'ibu bramzemarme bdag shing sa la chen po lta bu la rgyal srid phyed byin no ari'ibu 'di lta ste/ rgyal po mar me"i bdag po rgyal po'i(2)phyed byed pa chos kyis byad de/ chos ma yin pas ni ma yin no yang sari'i bu dus gzhan zhig na/ rgyal po mal me'i bdag po las bu gzugs bzang po/ mdzes pa.. (tog ed. vol.37,cf. p. vol.37,90.3-4) 6.Conclusion The above comparison of versions of the story of the prophecy of dipamkara buddha shows that between the three types classified according to the bodhisattva's name, there are also clear differences in the story's plot.inType 2versions, in which the bodhisattva's name is Megha, the story-flow can be summarized as follows: a cakravartin king (ie. King of jambudvipa) gives half of his kingdom to his minister and makes him a king, the latter's son becomes dipamkara buddha, when the cakravattin king fnds out about this, he requests his former minister to send dipamkara buddha to his capital, padma (ka), accompanying the request with a threat, and dipamkara buddha, out of mercy, goes to the capital city, padma (ka).type l versions, judging from the story-flow(1a) or the correspondence of proper names (1b and 1c), may represent an early stage of type2 versions. on the other hand, type 3 versions, in which the bodhisattva's name is Sumati, show a clear contrast with the other two types, the detailed story of dipamkara's birth is not related. However, from the fact that in and 3b sumati's1miraculous dreams are narrated, andin c, ina similar manner, the bodhisattva's s dreams, we can also see close affinities among these three versions. Thus, the above examination has at least succeeded in vindicating the classification into three recensions. in future publications, the present author will further continue to examine other plot-elements of the story, and thereby elucidate the formation and relation of various versions of the dipamkara prophecy story. References akanuma chizen赤沼智善.1925."nentobutsu no kenkyu燃燈佛の研究,"bukkyokenkyu佛教研 究[publisher unknown], vol.6,no.3,317-340 Bareau, andre.19-74."le dipamkarajataka des dharmaguptaka," melanges de sinology offeris d Monsieurpudemieville. 2 vols. Paris: institute des hautes etudes chinoises.11-16. Beal, Samuel.1873."The legend of dipaikara buddha. Translated from the chinese (and intended to illustrate plates xxIX. and l., "tree and Serpent worship,'"the journal of the royasiatic society of gret britain d ireland, new series, vol.6377395. -・the romantic legend of saky buddhaatranslationof the chinese versionof the abhinisk-ramanasutra. london trubner, repr. delhi: Motilal banarsidass, 1985  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies 「he story of the dipamkara buddha prophecy in northern buddhist Texts (J. MatsuMuRa)(、 Hirakawa akira平川彰.1993.nihyakugoiikkai no kenkyui, hirakawa akira chosaku shu.14, to-braarvig, jens and Pagel, ulrich.2006."Fragments of the bodhisattvapitakasutra," Manuscripts in the Schoyen collection, buddhist Manuscripts, oslo: hermes publishing, vol.311-88. Fukui setsuryo福井設了.19-1982."Mahabasutsu nentobutsujiki shiyaku4),"mikkyo bunka, No.13(Sep.1981),15;6(dec.1981),1-1,no.137(feb.1982),1-18,no.14dec. 1982).1-7. kyo: shuniusha. Hiraoka Satoshi平岡聡.2007.buddga nzo toku snze no monogatari , diviavadanazemyaku.2 Vols. tokyo: daizoshuppan. -budda no oinaru monogatari, bonbu ahauasutsuyaku, 2 vols. tokyo daizoshuppan. jones, J. J.1941956. the mahavastu , translation from the buddhist sanskrit,3 vols. (Sacred books of the buddhists xvi. Xvil and xIX).london: TS, Lamotte, etienne.1949-8.le traite de  grande veriu de sgesse, 5 tomes. louvain: institute Orientaliste. Matsumura junko松村淳子.2007.6." butsushuiokyo chu no sumedakata (The sumedhakatha in the Buddhavamsatthakatha),"kobe kokusai duigaku kiyo (kobe international jmiversity review) No.72,15-32. -005"the sumedhakathainpali literature and its Relation to the northern buddhist textual tradition," journalof the international college fstgraduate buddhist studies,14,1-133. Mizuno kogen水野弘元.1989."kan yaku no chu agonkyoto zoitsu agonkyo," bukkyy'o kenkyu, 1-42ukhyo bunken kenkyu mizuno kogen chosaku sensh, tokyo: Shunjusha, 1996,41 471, pagel, ulrich.1995.the bodhisattvapitaka: js doctrines, practices ad their positioninahoyana literature, buddhica britannica series continua v, Tring. institute of buddhist studies. Strong, john S.2001.the buddhc short biography, oxford: one world. 〓.Relics of the buddha, princeton princeton university press. Taga ryugen田賀龍彦.1966."Nentobutsu jukinitsuite [on the dipankarabuddha prophecy story]," kanakura hakushi koki kinenindogaku-bukky'ogaku ronshu kyoto: heirakuiishoten, 89-08. Takasaki jikido高崎直道.1974"bosatsuzokyo ni tsuite : Genio yaku daibosatsuzokyoochushin to shite," bk.2-254. unebe toshihide畝部俊英.1970.a study of chu Fo-nian inconnection with the chinese Translation of the Ekottaragama," nagoyadoigaku bungakubu kenkyuronshu: tetugaku,51,173-38. 1)akanuma1925and taga1966.taga's list of the story is so far the most exhaustive one. in some ter texts Sakyamuni's path is pushed back further: See strong 1123,lamotte 194-8 2)Matsumura76and13)about the fact that the bodhisattva's name in Skt is known as Megha or sumati, see strong,n.9.4)[eng. tr.」 Jones1949jp. tr.]Fukui182,hiraokai12-162.5)onthe translators of Ea, see Mizuno 198 f. unebe19706)[jp. tr.] hayashi goho林五邦1929。國一阿含部8174-18.7)[jp. tr.]  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies 〓The story of the dipamkara buddha prophecyin northern buddhist Texts (j. atsuMura Hayashi goho, ibid.,208)on the translation date of the sifenlu, hirakawa19938-29. 9)[jp. tr.] sakaino oyo境野黄洋1929,with revision by takemura Makio竹村牧男1975.國- 律部2:357-368,[fr.tr.」 bareau166-74.1)[jp. tr.] tokiwa daijo常盤大定and mino kojun 美濃晃順.1931.國一本縁部2:23-46[Eng. tr.] beal1873and1875.for detailed analysis of <ref><canon>T</canon><w>190</w></ref> see tokiwa and Mino國一本縁部3:1- they exemplify that T19belongs to the dharmaguptaka. but it also use material from the kasyapiya, the Mahasanghika, the Mahisasaka and the Sarvastivada. 11)abridged version is cited in金剛經纂要刊定記(〓1702:3.21618-b17)and註華嚴經題法界 觀門頌(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>188</w>:<v>1</v></ref>;there, however, both Megha雲童and Sumati善慧are given. 12)on the bodhisattvapitaka, see takasaki1974, pagel1995, brarrvig and pagel06.3)[jr tr.] nagai Makoto長井真琴.1930, revised ed.2003.國一寶釋部3186-195.14)[ed.] vaidya, p.l.(1959).divyovadana, buddhist Sanskrit texts no.20(darbhanga: mithila institute), pp.142- 161,[jap.tr.] hiraoka7-469.15)[jp.tr.]昭和新纂國譯編輯部編.1929,repr.名著 普及会1977.昭和新纂國譯經典部12:1-11, tokiwa daijo常盤大定.1929.國一本縁部4:11- ・16)the punctuation of the text should be:至于昔者,定光佛興世,有聖王名曰制勝,治在 鉢摩大國instead of 〓…名曰制勝治,在鉢摩大國"inT.17)similar phonetic translation for dipamkara buddha are,提和竭羅佛in the般舟三味經(t41813915c10),提忿竭inthe佛説阿闍 世王經(t62610405a18).Many other instances of similar transcriptions also exist, and include提 和竭羅佛<ref><canon>T</canon><w>125</w>,<v>2</v>.<p>768</p><c>c</c><l>2</l></ref>(this is very interestingl iaelsewhere there is a translation name.),提 租竭,〓1543072,提和竭羅佛t17141,提和竭羅佛<ref><canon>T</canon><w>169</w>-<v>21</v></ref>;提忿竭佛/提 和竭佛;提和竭羅佛<ref><canon>T</canon><w>196</w></ref>,<ref><canon>T</canon><w>2218</w>.<p>43</p><c>b</c><l>5</l></ref>,91220;提忿竭羅<ref><canon>T</canon><w>362</w>:<p>1</p><c>b</c><l>21</l></ref>,提忿 竭佛<ref><canon>T</canon><w>632</w>:<p>143</p><c>c</c><l>23</l></ref>,提忿竭/提和竭t101319.66b19,687622(and parallels in5),and so 18)eA scroll 38t1252.756c16-758c11when dipamkara buddha燈光佛visited a big country, Padma鉢頭摩大国,the king of jambudvipa was提波延那(*dipayana?), the bodhisattva's lame is彌勒(v.r.彌怯in〈&gt;may be right). dipamkara buddha received the prophecy from寶藏 如來in his fommer life, Scroll,"若我昔日不與善知識從事,終不爲燈光佛所見授決也.以與善 知識從事故,得爲與提和竭羅佛所見授決.以此方便知其善知識者,即是全梵行之人也."(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>125</w>. 〓.<p>768</p><c>2</c><l>24</l></ref>)19)〓 vaidya's edition, the king's name is sometimes misprinted as dvipa, and the capital city's name, dvipavati(152,5-7).20)the name as crown prince is deng-guang燈 光.21)at822.782b5 appears the word,提閻浮婆提,which is, however, an unique reading only found here in the whole taisho.22)"挺主,以施反八挺之主也漢書音義曰八挺地之八際 也"in一切經音義(t2128678b18).So,墺主may mean lord of eight boundaries,' ie. cakravartin king.23)〓大娑羅,樹名也是大富貴家義也案西國大官貴大富兒弟昏呼為娑羅也"in一切經 音義(t2128766c24).see also mws.v. mahasala. (The research for this article was supported by the grant-in-aid for Scientific research(b)no. 2132015 from JSPS) &lt;Key words) dipamkara, Megha, Sumati, bodhisattvapitaka (professor, international college for postgraduate buddhist studies. ph.d.)  
</root>
