<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies How did the indian masters Read the lotus sutr? MochizuKI kaie 0.Introduction The lotus sutra (ddharmapundarikasutra)is one of the most popular scriptures in East asia and many scholars have been studying on it. They discuss the complex develop-ments of its compilation orits philosophical themes like the idea of one vehicle (ekayana). but these attempts seem to be independent from the history of Indian buddhism. So i will try to put the lotus sutra into the stream of lndian buddhism again, comparing its citations as they appearin commentaries by later indian masters. 1.commentary on the lotus sutrg There is a commentary on the lotus sutra attributed to vasubandhu, the*saddharma-pundarikopadesa(妙法蓮華経憂婆提舎)3)in the chinese buddhist canon, but we have no informationon it in indian sources. Therefore i do not confirm its authority to vasu-bandhu in the history of indian buddhism. 2.citations and references of the lotus sutrainIndian literature 2.1.madhvamika literature 2.1.1.nagariuna 〓.11.1.*mahaprainaparamitopadesa(大智度論) This cites the lotus sutra most frequently and the numbers of citations or references come to23 it refers to various chapters of the sutra and considerably depends on this scripture. but this made a strange impressionon us because later commentaries never refer to this text and their references are different from those of this text. 2.1.1.2.*bodhisambhara(菩提資糧論) The author refers to the lotus sutra twice in this small text which exists only in the chi-  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies nese translation. both references are in the context on the prediction vvakarana) of the two vehicles to become a buddha, therefore he could acknowledge it as one of the main themes of the sutra. and they come to be recognizes as the oldest references to the sutra ir the indian buddhist literature. Though the compiler of this anthology seems to be different from the author of the mad-hyamakakarika, it has a great infuence on later indian masters. we can see four citations from the lotus sutra in it, that is to say, in the theme on the utmost rareness of a bud-dha's apperance, twice on the utmost rareness of beings who are truly and resolutely intent on the tathagatas" completion, and on the utmost rareness of beings who are resolutely in-tent on the vehicle of oneness. especially, the last citation of this text is also referred to in later tibetan buddhism, so this would be the first example of the reference to the theory of one vehicle in the lotus sutra. of course we must not forget the third citationon the im-measurable lifespan ofthe tathagata. 2.1.2.bhavva: tarkaivdlg In the fourth chapter of the tarkajvala, the commentary to his madhyamakahrdaya, the author cites the lotus sutra8 and jikido takasaki has already discussed this context and  oncludes 1)bhavya admits the theory of the three vehicles of Yogacara as the teaching of the great vehicle (mahoyana),2)teaches also the theory of one vehicle in the buddha na-ture, 3) depends on the literature of the Yogacara, and 4)cites the scripture in order to prove the theory of the one vehicle. bhavya seems to acknowledge the main theme of the sutra as the theory of the one vehicle. and the citation of the famous phrase, "there is only one vehicle, not two nor three(ekayana phrase)," begins here in the Madhyamika liter- 2.1.1.2.Sutrasamnccavq ature. 2.1.3.avalokitavrata: prainapradipatiko Though bhaviveka (or bhavya?) does not cite the lotus sutra in the prajnapradipa, Avalokitavrata cites it in its commentary. in the commentary on the loth verse of the 〓2nd chapter on the tathagata he refutes those who do not accept his omniscience and re-fers to the sutra in order to exclude his humanity because the scripture says that he had a1- ready been the buddha long ago.  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 2.1.4.candrakirti 2..4.mudhyamakovatarabhosya Candrakirti refers to the lotus sutra three times in his mudhyamakovatarabhasva.10i the first verse of the first chapter he cites the verse of its fourth chapter in order to explain the meaning of the word of sravaka. in the 3oth verse of its 12th chapter he cites the eka-yana phrase of the sutra in order to prove the one vehicle theory as truth and to negate the three vehicles theory as intended meaning and in the 38th verse he refers to the simile of a visionary castle in the sutra. Candrakirti also seems to acknowledge the main theme of the sutra as the theory of the one vehicle. There is a sub-commentary named madhyamakava-taratika by jayananda and he also refers to the sutra.11 2.1.4.2.catuhsatikafiko Candrakirti refers the lotus sutra also in his catuhsatikatika again.he explains here the wisdom of the tathagata and says that we must acquire the supreme wisdom frst be-cause an enlightened mind as its seed does not disappear not only from bodhisattva but also sravaka and Pratyekabuddha. 2.1.6. jnanagarbha anantamukhanirhoradhoranifiko Jnanagarbha who is well known as the author of the satyadvayavibhanga refers to the lotus sutra in his tantric commentary named anantamukhanirharadharanitika.3In its last section he discusses on the prediction of sravaka and refers also to the dasadhar- 〓strq. 2.1.7.kamalasila 2.1.7.1.madhyamakolokq Kamalasila discusses the one vehicle theory and criticizes the three vehicles theory of the yogacara school and refers to the lotus sutra five times.14)The first two are cited in the section ofthe opponent. That is to say, they consider the lotus sutra as a sutra express-ing the intended meaning on the basis of the hahayanasutralamkara and the prediction in the sutra as to only two special kinds of sravaka. Then kamalasila criticizes them and cites the ekayana phrase of the sutra in order to assert the one vehicle theory as truth. he obvi-ously acknowledges the sutra as having definitive meaning. further there is a reference to the sutra also in his prainaparamitovairacchedikatika. 2.1.7.2.tattyasamgrahapanjiko In the commentary to the tattvasamgraha of Santaraksita kamarasila seems to refers to  the japanese ssociatio of indian and buddhist studies the lotus sutra without its title.1/ he considers the Madhyamakavadin as a wise person of the great vehicle and cites the passage, "only the one vehicle is the great vehicle." he ad-mits the one vehicle theory as the ultimate teaching, as seen in his madhyamakuloka. 2.1.8.Santideva: siksasamuccaya This is an anthology of scriptures compiled also by santideva and we can see four cita tions in it.1The first is cited for those whom bodhisattvas consider undesirable, the sec. ond for the possibility for a11 beings to be enlightened and the last two for the gift of teach-ing the dharma. therefore he never refers to the one vehicle theory of the sutra in this text. 2.1.9.dipamkarasriinana: mahasutrasamuccayo Dipamkarasrijnana (atisa) also cites the lotus sutra in his anthology, the mahasutra-amuccaya.18) This citation is the same as the first reference in the siksasamuccaya, but it is longer than that of santideva. This means that he cites these verses not from it but from the sutra directly though he must have read the siksasamuccaya. and he also never refers to the one vehicle theory of the sutra in his works. 2.1.10.堅意:*nahayanavatarasastra(入大乗論, we can find eight references19)to the lotus sutra in the* mahoyanavatorasastra. there is no reference to the author of this work in indian buddhist literature.〓In the third refer-ence the author refers to the meditation of the lotus sutra(法華三味),a phrase whichi can not find in indian buddhist literature. Further he never refers to its one vehicle theory, therefore it does not seem to have been writtenin india. 2.1.10.堅意:*mahoyanavatorasastra(入大乗論) 2.2.yogacara-vijinaptimatravadin literature 2.2.1.maitreya: ratnagotravibhdgq There are not so many references to the lotus sutra in the Yogacara-viinaptimatravadir literatures as in the Madhyamika literatures. we can see a context of the one vehicle theory in the 11th chapter of the mahayanasutralamkora of Maitreya and two further references to the sutra in the ratnagotravibhaga attributed to him,1 which seems to be a later text. The first is a reference to the simile of the visionary castle in the sutra in order to explain the identification of buddhahood and nirvana. The second is a reference to its title and he clas-sifies beings into two, those who are entered into the nirvana and those who have entered into nirvana with the sutra. here he admits the three vehicles theory and considers the sutra as the teaching for the bodhisattava.  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies 2.2.2.vasubandhu 2.2.2.1.mahayanasamgrahabhosya In the last chapter of the hahayanasamgraha asanga discusses the one vehicle theory with a citation from the mahayanasutramkorakariko. its commentary vasubandhu considers the one vehicle theory as intended meaning and refers to the lotus sutra. Therefore he considers the three vehicles theory as the ultimate meaning 2.2.2.2.*buddhadhatusastra(仏性論) lts authority to vasubandhu is doubted, but we can find a reference to the lotus sufra in *buddhadhotusdstra. he says that the lotus sutra and so on have the true teachings but he does not discuss its thought.24) 2.2.3.*asvabhaba uahoyanasamgrahopanibandhana As the citation in the mahoyanasamgraha,*asvabhava also refers to the lotus sutra ir his commentarylike the references of vasubandhu's commentary. he classifies the sin-gle statement of the buddha into two, namely for sravakas who have become convinced of identification with the buddha and for bodhisattvas who receive the same prediction. Therefore he also thinks of the three vehicles theory as truth. in the 11chapter of his com-mentary to the mahayanasutralamkara he refers to the lotus sutra. 2.2.4. sthiramatis mahayanasutralamkoravrttibhosya In the qth chapter of his commentary to the hahoyanasutralamkara he refers to the lo ts sutra in order to explain the merit of the sense faculties, not the context of the one vehicle nor the prediction of sravaka. in the one vehicle context of the l1th chapter he crit-icizes its one vehicle theory on the basis of the mahayanasutralamkara. it seems to be the lotus sutra and he acknowledges it as a sutra of the intended meanings. 2.2.5. Ratnakarasanti: prainaporamitopadesa Ratnakarasanti refers to the lotus sutra as the provisional meanings in his prajna-paramitopadeson the one hand, he explain the one vehicle theory of the sutra in his commentary on the sutrasamuccaya. 2.3.abhisamaya literatures 2.3.1.arya-vimuktisenaabhisamayalamkaravriti lt became popular in later indian buddhism to read the prajnaparamitasutra based of a knowledge of the abhisamayalamkorasastra by maitreya, but there seem to have been two streams, namely, the Madhyamika reading and the yogacara reading. Regarding the lotus  the japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studie sutra, the former actively cites it in the context of the one vehicle theory. arya-vimuktise-na explains the various aspects of the nirvana on various stages and cites the lotus sutra to explain the nirvana of sravaka.1/ but he says that these nirvanas are expressions of the in-tended meaning. and there is a reference to the sutra in the abhisamayalamkarakorikovar-tika of vimuktisena.2) 2.3.2.haribhadrabhisamayulamkardloka lt is well known that haribhadra criticizes the three vehicles theory of the Yogacarava-din in his commentary to the abhisamayalamkara. this context he cites the lotus Sutra to prove the one vehicle theory as the truth. therefore he obviously acknowledges the three vehicles theory as the truth by Yogacara and reads the abhisamayalamkora from the standpoint of the Madhyamaka. 2.3.3.abhayakaragupta: munimatolamkora abhayakaragupta also cites the same passage of the lotus sutra as haribhadra does.4 He criticizes the opponents who consider the one vehicle theory as the intended meaning and says that they do not follow the ultimate one vehicle theory of the lotus sutra. 2..4.dharmamitra: abhisamayulamkaraprajnaparamitopadesasastratiko prasphuta-pada The above-mentioned commentaries refer to the lotus sutra in the context of the one vehicle theory or the prediction of Sravaka, but references indharmamitra's commentary give us a different impression. There are three citations in it.he refers to the buddha's dharma in every aspect.or teaching dharma with compassion, but not to its one vehicle the-ory. Further there is a reference to the sutra in the bhagavapyomnyayanusarinivyakhya of *jagaddalanivasin.36 feuotberihoysi erneio tesiua mhie ehisowynonsyaihaof 3.conclusion In the Madhyamika literature, without the siksasamuccaya, the lotus sutra is cited in the context of the one vehicle theory or the prediction of Sravakas and these references de-velop into the criticism of the three vehicles theory of the Yogacara. in the Yogacara litera-ture the one vehicle theory in the lotus sutra is also referred to, but it is as intended mean-ing, not as the ultimate meaning. therefore they do not seem to acknowledge the lotus sutra as an important scripture. in the abhisamaya literature haribhadra criticizes the three  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies vehicles theory as truth by the Yogacara on the one hand, but Dharmamitra never refers to he one vehicle theory on the other hand. Therefore we can see different readings of the sutra in the abhisamava literature. 1)h. kem and b. nanjio, saddharmapundarikasutra, st. petersbourg,198-1912. 2)See also kaie Mochizuki(望月海慧),"adoption of saddharmapundarikasutra in madhya-mika literature(中観派文献における法華経の受容),"inRyugen taga(田賀龍彦)ed., the lotus sura: iis adoptiodevolution(法華経の受容と展開),1993, kyoto, pp.3569 lonathana. Silk, "The place of the lotus sutra in indian buddhism," the journal of orient studies, 11,2001,pp.87-105. 3)<ref><canon>T</canon>. nos.<w>1519</w>.<w>1520</w></ref>. 4)Shinio suguro(勝呂信静),"ancient indian buddhists" comments on the lotus sutra(イン ドにおける法華経の注釈的解釈).ides ad the formationof the lotus sutra(法華経の思 想と形成),2009,tokyo, pp.529. 5)t. no.1509,vol.25,1)p.122-2(chap.11,2)p.12chap.26),3)p.19 (chap.22),4)p.242chap.15,5)p.2812chap.1),6)p.29chap. 7),7)p.3-1(chap.11),8)p.327chap.14,9)p.37title),10)p 3391722chap.18),11)p.339c1-1chap.6),12)p.39410title),13)p.4 26(chap.1),14)p.45-6(title);,15)p.61chap.2,16)p.64chap.3, 17)p.8-11(chap.22),18)p.712-2chap.2),19)p.7131c(chap.2),20)p. 717chap.1)21)p.711(chap.7),22)p.754-8title);23)p.756b6- 10(title). See also keisho tsukamoto(塚本啓祥),"The daichidorond the lotus sutra(大 智度論と法華経),"in Yukio sakamoto(坂本幸男)ed., The lotus sutra d chinese bud-dhism(法華経の中国的展開),kyoto,1972,pp.611-660. 6)chin. t. no.166,1)p.52;2)p.55. See also yukihiro okada(岡田行弘), "nagarjuna and the saddharmapundarikasutra(ナーガールジュナと『法華経』)," sunyato 〓d reality: bolume inemoryofprofessor eiima yasunori(江島惠教博士追悼論集:空と実 在),tokyo,200, pp.36382. 7)bhikkupasadika, vaguriuna 's sutrasamuccayriticl edition of the mdo kus btus pa, kobenhavn,1989(cf. tib. d. no.3934,p. no.5,chin. t. no.1635,1)p.1(Kern ed., p.319),2)p.121(kern ed., p.13),3)p.121(ker ed., p.318),4)p.126(kern ed. pp.13).see also shoshin ichishima(一正真),teachings of saddharmapundarikasutra observedin sutrasamuccya『スートラサムツチャヤ』の法華思想),"intaga, op. ci., pp. 475-499. 8)d. no.3856,1732-6(Kern ed., p.46).See also jikido takasaki(高崎直道),"controver-sies over the tathagatagarbha theory: from bhavaviveka's auto-commentary on his hudhya-maka-hrdaya-karika," collected works of fikido takasaki 6: the tathagatagarbha o buddha nature theory(高崎直道著作集6如来蔵思想・仏性論〓),tokyo,20,pp.541and Honshu nakai(中井本秀),"bhavaviveka's view on the prediction of Sravakas' attaining  the japanese ssociatio of indian and buddhist studie: buddhahood in tarkaivala(『法華経』「声聞授記」の受容と変容),"in taga, op. cit., pp. 〓 519537. 9)d.no.3859,194-6(kem ed., p.323). 10)louis de la vallee poussin, madhyamakovatora par candrakirti, st. petersbourg,1907-191 1)pp.118-119(kem ed., pp.118-119),2)pp.399-400(kern ed., p.133);3)p.402chap. 7) 11)d. no.3870,1)6b7(title),2)35a2 (kem ed., p.65). 12)d. no.3865,221b-222a1 13)hisao inagaki(稲垣久雄),the anantamukhanirhoradharani sutra and jjnanagarbha's com-mentorywy ad the tibetext, kyoto,1987,pp.29-291. 14)d. no.3887,1)147b6(kem ed., p.46),2)d.14723(title);3)d.2-2392(kern ed., pp.43-46),4)d.23-5(title),5)d.2(Kemn ed., p.43).cf. Shiro matsumoto (松本史朗),"a study of the "ichijo" Thought in madhyamakaloka(i)(madhyamakalokaの 一乗思想)," journal of soto 〓hu research fellows(曹洞宗研究員研究生研究紀要)14, 1982,pp.(1)7). 15)d. no.3817,2265(title). 16)d. no.4267,103b7-l 17)cecil bendall, sikshasamuccaycompendiumof buddhist teaching, st. petersbourg, 1897-19021)pp.47-4(kem ed., pp.278-80,2)pp.9294(kem ed., pp.52),3)pp 352-34(kemed., pp.2-84,4)p.4(kem ed., p.286). 18)kaie mochizuki,a study of the mahosutrasamuccayof dipamkarasrjinana n, minobu, 〓004,pp.184-186(kem ed., pp.278-81).cf. kaie Mochizuki, "oa passage from the sad-tharmapundarikasutra in the mahasutrasamuccaya of atisa(ディーパンカラシュリージュ ヤーナの『大経集』に引用される法華経),"in Shinjo suguro ed., the lotus sutra: is Thought ad developmemt(法華経の思想と展開),kyoto, 201, pp.29-324. 19)chin. t. no.1634,vol.32,1)p.4-21(title),2)p.45b1-21,3p.46b-21(title);4) p.47-14title),5)p.47-1(chap.15,6)pp.478-48a5;7)p.4,8)pp 〓8-49a5. See suguro, op. cit. 20)Sugro considers him as a Madhyamika master because the author says nagarjuna, aryadeva and Rahulabhadra as the great masters and cites their texts. 21)e.H. johnston, ratnagotravibhaga mahayonottaratantrasastra, patna,1950,1)p.56(chap. 7),2)p.859. 22)see Shiro Matsumoto, "The ekayana theory of the viinanavadins(唯識派の一乗思想につ いて),"journalo buddhist studies(駒沢大学仏教学部論集)13,1982,pp.12. 23)paul J. Griffiths, Noriaki hakamaya, johnp. keenan, and paul l. Swanson, the realm of awakening: chapter eofasangas mahayanasangraha. oxford,1989,pp.365. 24)chin. t. no.16,vol.31,p.813-4. 25)Griffiths, op. cit., p.365. 26)d. no.4029,1)71(title),2)18b3-4(kem,p.46).  The japanese association of indian and buddhist studies 27)tib. no.403,126(kemn ed., p.354). 28)Tib.d. no.403,196-7. 29)d. no.4079,135b7(title) 30)kaie mochizuki, " Ekayana Philosophy in ratnakarasanti's ratnalokolamkara (ratnakarasanti による一乗思想の解釈),"bukkyogaku(仏教学)33,1992,pp.49-68. 31)corrado pensa, lhhisamayalamkaravrtti di ry-imuktisena, roma,1967,p.35. 32)d. no.3788,14(title). 33)unrai wogihara, abhisamayalamkar dlokprajinaparamitavyakhyo, tokyo,1932,pp.13- 134(Kemn ed., p.46).See also gadiin m. Nagao(長尾雅人),"aspects of the ekayana and tripana argument with particular reference to india(一乗・三乗の論議をめぐって),"〓d-hyamaka ad yogucara(中観と唯識),tokyo,1978,pp.524 34)d. no.3903,1)144Kern ed., p.65),2)179b3(title).See also david Seyfort Ruegg, "The gotra, ekayana and tathagatagarbha theories of the Prajnaparamita according to dharmami-tra and abhayakaragupta," lewis lancaster ed., prainaparamito and related systems: studies in honorofdward coze, berkeley,1977,p.295. 35)d. no.3796,1)2-b2(chap.2,2)36b6-7,3)89b5-7. 36)d. no.3811,26b3(title). (Key words&gt; saddharmapundarikasutra, the lotus sutra, ekayana, sastra (professor, Minobusan university)  
</root>
