<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies criticism of entity Theory and the acceptance ofdlayavijnana The investigation of the Sautrantika for vasubandhu Horiuci Toshio 1.Introduction The study of the sautrantika has recently made great advances, mainly because of the discovery ofa relationship between the abhidharmakosabhosykbh) and the yogucara-bhumi (Ybh).1in this regard, some scholars argue that Vasubandhu was already a Yogacara when he wrote the akBh. although it is true that from this point of view the study of the Sautrantika is of great importance, i cannot agree with this opinion when one considers the following two situations. First, Vasubandhu defines the Mahayana as a teaching that pos-sesses seven greatnesses(saptavidha-mahattva) in the vyakhyayukti (vyY), a text writ-ten after the akBhby the same author. These seven are, in short, summarized as the inter pretation of dharma and buddha.  with regard to buddha, he declares that sakyamuni is manifestation. with regard to dharma, on the other hand, he emphasizes the ineffableness of a11 dharmas. These are Mahayana doctrines that he himself clearly articulates. Second. the interpretation of dharma on the basis of the tenets of the Mahayana, that is, the inter pretation that a11 dharmas are ineffable, can be regarded as an innate yogacara doctrine based on the description by sagaramegha. in his yogacarabhumivyakhya, sagaramegha describes the position of Yogacara in the history of buddhist thought as follows. after the Buddha's nirvana, many of the buddhist sects adhered to the view of existence. Then, Na-garjuna countered this by expounding the teaching of emptiness. however, some of his followers misunderstood this teaching, adhered to emptiness, and fell into nihilism or the view of non-existence. Therefore, Maitreya/asanga taught the Ybh. Such is the gist of his account. The key tetms of the doctrine are " not existent, not non-existent" and ineffable-ness, which are assumed to have been first clearly propounded in the "tattvapatala" of the bodhisattvabhumi. The point is, things do not exist as expressed (namely, are not exis-tent) , however, they are not non-existent in every way. dharmas of ineffable nature exist,  〓he japanese asociation of indian and buddhist studie or rather, a11 dharmas are ineffable. This emphasis on the ineffableness of a11 dharmas can be regarded as one of the consistent or penetrating mahayana-Yogacara doctrines since it is foundnot only in several layers of the Ybh, starting from the bodhisatnvabhumi, but alsc 〓asanga's mahayanasamgraha and vasubandhu's vyY and vimsiko vs).3) Tumning back to the relationship between the akbh and Ybh, as far as i can see, theil corresponding passages do not contain these two doctrines that vasubandhu himself defines as the teachings of the Mahayana. neither is it related to the penetrating yogacara doctrine of the ineffableness of a11 dharmas, which is also regarded as distinctive of vasubandhu's thought in that it is found in both the vyY and vs. Thus, what one can safely conclude is that vasubandhu was aware of the existence of the Ybh when he wrote the akBh and bor-rowed some ideas fromit, However, it is also true that a development of ideas is found in the traiectory of Vasu-bandhu's thought and Sautrantika theories whose relationship with the Ybh has been re vealed by previous studies play important roles. one of the most important terms among them is, as is well-known, samtatiparinamavisesa, which is found in the akbh, karma-siddhi (kS),and pratipyasamupadavyakhyavy) and finally developed into the temm vijnanaparinama in the same author's Vs and trimsika. another theory, although it can be traced back to the " darstantika" in the hahovibhasa, is criticism of the entity dravya) theory of the Sarvastivada. In this paper, i would like to first point out that one of the most important or at least most frequently mentioned Sautrantika theories in the akbh is criticism of the entity theory of the sarvastivada. Then, i shall argue that this criticism, especially that of the existence of jivitendriy(life faculty) and nikayasabhagato (homogeneous character) as entities, be-came one of the stepping stones whereby vasubandhu came to accept dlayaviinana in his later works. 2.The Sautrantika for vasubandhuin the akbh Since there remains no text that summarizes sautrantika doctrine by Sautrantikas them-selves, one must rely heavily on what later commentators or opponents such as Samgha-bhadra say. however, there are two problems. First, their opinions cannot always to be tak-en at face value since it is sometimes the case that not only in later commentaries on the Akbh but also in commentaries on the kS and vs the opinions of the commentators differ:  The japanese associationof Indian and buddhist studies 〓 according to kato1989, the sautrantika theories in this sense in the akbh number sev. theories that some attribute to the sautrantika are attributed to the abhidharmika, etc., by others. Therefore, it is questionable how much of what they say reflects the actual state of the sautrantika (if there was any such thing).Second, i have reservations about the useful-ness of relying heavily on the attributions of commentators or opponents when investigat-ing the meaning of the Sautrantika for vasubandhu. Thus, one of the safer methods for investigating the position of the sautrantika for vasu-bandhu would seem be to confine oneself to materials that he himself declares to be of the Sautrantika. enteen. They are as follows: criticism of the sarvastivada theories that l. prthagianatva, 2. four characteristics of conditioned forces, 3.asamskrta, 4. samsthana or form, 5. koyavijnapti,6. avijnapti,7. samvara, and 8.past and future are entities dravya).9. interpretation of the term kamara-ga.10.the problem of the maintenance of the mental continuum in the immaterial world (I will pick up the tenth argumentin section3,9and 1are also related to criticism of the entity theory).11.how visual consciousness arises. 12.the buddha's knowledge about the future ddharma.13.the reason that some gods have different images.14. interpretation of dependent origination.15. Interpretation of nutriment of volition.46. The state wher one obtains the avijnapti of samvara and asamvara.17.Fa11 from arhatship. As can be seen in the above list, as many as about 1of the seventeen or sixteen) sau-trantika theories are criticisms of the entity theory of the sarvastivada. Further, the importance of this criticism in the akbhis also attested by the fact that Va subandhu himself mentions this when he refers to his akbhin his later pSvy. PSVy (muroji ed.),10 Forces not associated with the mind (cittaviprayukta-samska-ra) are not entities (rovya). they are just names for another state [of existing elements] "as for the way in which these do not exist as entities, you should understand it from [the descriptionin] the abhidharmakosa. In the following sections, i would like to show that this Sautrantika doctrine of criticism of entity theory foreshadows vasubandhu's introductionof dlavavijnana in his later works. 3.Criticism of entity theory and the introduction of dlayaviinana In this section, i would like to take a look at the function of jivitendriy (life force) and  〓he japanese sociation of indian and buddhist studies nikoyasabhagata (homogeneous character), members of the cittaviprayukta-samskaras (forces not associated with the mind), as described in the akBh. These two dharmas, life force and homogeneous character, are discussed in detail along with other members of the forces not associated with the mind in the second chapter of the AKbh. they are further discussed in the first part of the third chapter (akbh[pradhan ed.],112).The argument is, in short, as follows. The abhidharmikas (Sarvastivada) state: in the kama- and ripa-dhatu (world),minc and mental states are supported by rup (formvisible matter).although there is no rupo in the drupy-dhatu (immaterial world), mind and mental states have life force and homo-geneous character as their basis since, being arisen from special absorptionsmapatti), they have strong power. Further, life force and homogeneous character support each other. The Sautrantikas criticize: if that is so, since mind and mental states themselves are also arisen from special absorption in the immaterial world, they are strong enough to suppor each other. Therefore, there is no need of another basis such as life force or homogeneous character. as previous studies have pointed out, this argument by the Sarvastivada can, of course be traced back to the mahavibhas27137a).it states that in the immaterial world where there is no rvpa, the mental continuum, etc., exist with their bases in just the same manner as in the kama- and rupa-dhatu. and in the kama- and rup-dhatu the mental con-inuum, etc., are supported by rupa too.In the immaterial world, on the other hand, the basis of the mental continuum, etc., is merely forces not associated with the mind, such as life force, homogeneous character, and attainment( * prapti). In this way, the abhidharmikas assume the existence of the support for mind and mental states in the immaterial world (arupy-dhatu), whereas the sautrantikas do not admit its existence. however, if one further investigates the state of existence in the immaterial world, this sautrantika position turns out to be illogical. and that illogicality is solved by the introduction of alayaviinana. 4.proofof the existence of dlayaviinanq The kS proves the existence of dlayavijnana by pointing out four illogicalities that arise if one does not admit its existence. in the third and fourth arguments, the kSpoints out the illogicality that occurs in the maintenance of the mental continuum in the immaterial  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies riticismof entity theory and the acceptance of dlayavijnana (t. horiuchl)(14 world. KS(Muroii ed.),4(19b(i))when non-returners in the summit of existence who try to termi-nate impurity arouse the pure mind that belongs to the sphere of nothingness, what is the body that is another entity by the existence of which it is said that they do not die from this [world?There is no other entity such as homogeneous character or life force at a11. They are designations for the mere similarity and continuing force of aggregates of retribution. there is no other entity such as similarity or continuing force. This text also points out that there is the problem of the existence of goti, realms of re-birth, if one does not admit the existence of alayavijinana kS,411b(〓i)). The reason that vasubandhu had to deny the existence of homogeneous character and life force as entities immediately after this argument seems to be that if one admits them as entities, this illogicality will not occur. it is the kS, which does not admit theif existence as entities, that would face this illogicality. in this sense, the negation of the Sarvastivada en-tity theory is closely related to the introduction of dlayavijnana. 5.Sautrantikain the kS Vasubandhu refers to the sautrantika only once again in a text later than the akBh. in the kS, he supports the argument by "some Sautrantikas"" that asserts that dlayavijnana ex-ists even in the absoiption of cessationnirodhasamapatti)(kS,37(18)).The Sautranti-ka to which vasubandhu himself refers is thus associated with the introduction of alayavij-nana in the kS. In the akbh,on the other hand, many of the sautrantika theories were negations of entity theory. on the basis of the above, then, i would like to point to the sau-trantika as a factor in vasubandhu's close connections with the introduction of alayavipna-na. it may also be possible to assume that he had in mind the existence of dlayaviinanc when he denied the existence of jivitendriya and nikayasabhagata in the akBh. 6. later abhidharma texts In order to reinforce the point that the criticism of jivitendriya and nikayasabhagata was closely related to the introduction of layaviinana, i would like to take a look at the proof of existence of these two dharmas in later abhidharma texts. the point is that the argument that the later Sarvastivada uses in order to prove the existence of these two as entities is similar to that which the Yogacaras or sautrantikas used inorder to prove the existence of  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies criticismof Entity theory and the acceptance ofalayaviinana (T. horiuchi) dlayavijnana. samghabhadra's nyayanusara 458c) cites and criticizes the above sautrantika po-sition (sectionof this paper), namely, the negation of the two dharmas. it states: when one who is born in the immaterial world(*arupy-dhatu) arouses the mind of another stage (ie., of a lower stage) or pure(*anasrava) [mind], if there is no dharma at a11 tha becomes a basis for the mental continuum, to what stage does this one belong? The abhidharmadipa, on the other hand, argues as follows: ad(Jaini ed.), 89.the jivitendriya that is the material cause of denominating realms of rebirth (*gati) exists as an entity. since, otherwise, how can one assume that which arose as maturation by Nhich existence this one will not die from the realm of rebirth (ie., arupya-dhatu) We find a similar argumentin the abhidharmavatara too. Since these points can, as far as i can see, not be found in earlier abhidharma texts, one may even speculate that they boirowed this argument from those who tried to prove the ex. istence of dlayaviinana. 7.conclusion In this paper i have pointed out the close relationship of the sautrantika for Vasubandhu in the akbh to the introduction of dlayaviinana by pointing out that the negation of the Sarvastivada entity theory, which is the most frequently mentioned Sautrantika positionin the akbh, especially that of jivitendriya life force) and nikayasabhagata (homogeneous character), requires the existence of dlayavijnona since they performa similar function. &lt;notes) 1)For details. see kritzer5. 2)These points are not discussed in detail here since i have dealt with themioriuchi09. For reasons of space, reference should be made to this earlier work for the abbreviations and a detailed bibliography ofthe present paper. 3)according to kao845,"vimsiko seems to be the original" title of vasubandhu's twenty verses. 4)iam skeptical about counting this as a Sautrantika theory since although the sanskrit text and xuanzang's chinese translation have "sautrantika" here, it is missing inZhendi, tib. (akbh (t),pGu12b3f., dku1f.), and commentaries such as the abhidharmakosavyakhyo (wogiwara ed., 318.4),laksananusarinju3b4f.), and tattvarthaTho 91a1f.). 5)They are also supported by forces not associated with the mind.  The japanese ssociationof indian and buddhist studies 6)vasubandhu negates the sarvastivada definition of these two dharmas. Miyashita2 points out that sthiramati, having seen that this position is criticized by Samghabhadra in connection with the problem of the maintenance of the mind and mental states in the immaterial world. in-troduced dlayaviinana in order to defend vasubandhu. 7)*avedha. compared to the shooting ofan atrow. 8)this point has already been made in Muroii1986and Schmithausen87.The latter (249-50 n. 36)states:〓The arguments are, of course, valid only on the assumption that a metaphysical aiman or pudgala and hypostatized entities like the jivitendripa and the mikoyasabhagata of the Vaibhasikas do not exist." In this paper, i have tried to take a further look at the argument about these two ddharmas in abhidharma texts, show the importance of criticism of entity theory in the sautrantika theories as found in the akBh, and trace a connection between the Sautrantika position in the akbh and the introductionof dlayaviinand. 9)<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>14</w>,dno.<w>407</w>(nyu38-<p>319</p><c>a</c>),pno.<w>5599</w>(Thu)</ref>. (bibliography) Horiuchi toshio 〓,seshino daiio bussetsuron. shakkiroh diyonsho wo chushino shite, The Sankibo press. kano kazuo8, "two short glosses  yogacara texts by vairocanaraksita: vi-msikatikovrtti and dharmadharmatavibhagavrtti," samskrit texis from giuseppe tuccis collection Part i, roma. kato junsho1989,kyoryobu no kenkyu, Shuniusha. kritzer, robert, 〓0, vasu-bandhu and the yogdcarabhumi: yogocur elements in the abhidharmakosabhosya, the intemnational Institute for buddhist studies. Miyashita seiki2002, "The fault does not Reach the Sutrakara: o arguments about fpitendriya in the abhidharmakosabhasya," early buddhism ad abhichormg Thought,2773, heirakuji Shoten. muroji Yoshihito1986,"kusharon, jogoron, engikyoshaku," 〓fikkyo bunka, 156-i,899.Schmithausen, lambert,1987,tlayavijnana: 〓n the origin amd the eary development of central conceptof yogocara philosophy, 2 vols., The intemnational insti-tute for buddhist studies. (Key words)  Sautrantika, dlayaviinana, Vasubandhu, entity theory (Research fellow, The university of tokyo, ph.d.)  
</root>
