<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies Bhaviveka on the yogacara theoty of anyopoho TAMuRA masaki 0.the fifth chapter of the madhyamakahrdayakarika is meant for opposing yogacaras view of emptiness (unyata) as the emptiness of hypostasized subject-object duality (grahyagrahakadvayasunya/-dvayabhova). according to the yogacaras, empirical factors, characterized as a subiect or an object, are constructed through concepts and language and as such they exist only nominally or conventionally abhilapamatra). therefore, empti-ness as conceived of by them is also defined as 〓emptiness of an effable intrinsic nature (abhilapyatmasunyatva). The present paper deals with mHkV60-68,in which bhaviveka, in order to dispute this view of emptiness, has to argue against dignaga's apoha theory. 1.In mHKV60bhaviveka presents the yogacaras' view of a word meaning and points out that, in formulating the principle that everything is ineffable, they are violating the same principle. 〓Kv60samanyam abhilapyam hi samanyamc na* kimcan  nabhilapyotmasunyatvam** vamy mpapadate //*ana] h, S, sg, ms, na cal1, l2, ec.**nabhilapyatmasunyatvam]l1, L,, s, SG,ms, nabhilapatmasunyatvamh, ec)"[Yogacaras] indeed, a universal (samanya) is what is to be denoted [bya word] abhilapya).but the universal is something indeterminable ( kimcana) [i.e., something unreal]. [bhaviveka] if so, then it is not appropriate even to say that [the statement that a11 dharmas are ] empty of an effable essential nature [is meaningful] b-hilapyotmasunyatva)." Bhaviveka says that in the Yogacaras' view a universal is what is to be denoted by a word. 「n the light of arguments presentedin mHKV66,what is considered here to be a universal sanyapoha. accordingly, bhaviveka brings in here the Yogacaras' view that anyapoha is what is to be denoted by a word. The point is clear. if the Yogacaras argue that since a universal in the form of anyapoha, which they hold to be what is to be denoted by a word, is unreal, what is denoted by a word has no essential nature, they cannot formulate this principle, even if they did, the statement  the japanese ssociationof indian and buddhis studies formulated would be meaningless. 2.1.bhaviveka has stated thatin the Yogacaras' view a universal in the form of anyapoha is what is to be denoted by a word. He goes on to state his own view of what is to be de-noted by a word. MHkv61: vacyam samanyavad vastu tadubhamatihetutah sva tenatmana satnon vuktanabhi lapyatoentity which is qualified by a universal (samanyavad vastu) is what is to be denoted [by a word」, because [the word is] the cause of a cognition in which such an entity appears. Since the universal (tsya) exists as such [ effable] essential nature, it is not reasonable that [the uni-versal] is ineffable." according to bhaviveka, what is to be denoted by a word is an entity qualified by a univer sal (samanyavad vcstu).In his view what is understood from a word is such an entity. itis important to note that, as shall be shown, what bhaviveka considers here to be a universa. is not anyapoha but vijatiyenasunyatva 'emptiness of a dissimilar entity' and that he holds the view because he considers that the wordgo 'cow,' for example, must refer to any cows and not to non-cows. it will be explained in MHKV63how the qualifier universal is treat-ed as what is to be denoted by a word in this view. what is important is thatin bhaviveka's view the universal is not beyond verbalization and hence effable. 2.2.mHkV62states that when he says that an entity qualified by a universal is what is t be denoted by a word, he means the emptiness of a dissimilar entity by the "universal' and hat this emptiness has a claim to be regarded as a universal. MHkV62vjatiyenasunyatvam tulyadhivrttihetutah  smanyat tulyaiatiye samamyam iti miscitam "Emptiness of a dissimilar entity [i.e., being different from a dissimilar entity] is the universal, be-ause lthis emptiness is」 the cause of the occurrence of the same cognitiontuluadhivrttihetu) this emptiness is] determined as a universal' by virtue of similar entities having it in common. According to bhaviveka, it is by virtue of the universal characterized by the emptiness ofa dissimilar entity that different cognitions of the same form cn occur with respect to indi-vidual entities of the same class. 2.3.in bhaviveka's view, if an entity qualified by a universalis denoted by a word, then it naturally follows that the universal is also denoted by a word. MHKv63:nasrayasyagrahe grahyam samkhyovat tadgrahe grahot  tadvat kapycm ato vcstu va-cym cestmprthag hc*〓*cestam prthag naca] h, s, nestamprthag bhavetl1, l2, Ec, cestam prthag bhave SG, ms)" [The universal in the form of emptiness of a dissimilar entity] cannot be  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies grasped when its locus is not grasped. For, just like a number, it is grasped only when its locus is grasped. and, [this being the case,」 itis not accepted that [the universal is ] separate from [the en. ity which has this universal](prthak).accordingly, an entity qualified by the [universal] td vastu) is an object ofa conceptual cognition anda significand [ofa word]." It is interesting that Bhaviveka applies the anvaya-vyatireka method to establish the non-distinction between the universal in question and its holder. according to bhaviveka there does not exist the universal in question independently of the entity which possesses it, so that, when a entity qualified by the universal is denoted by a word, it must be said that the universal is also denoted by the word. 3.now, in order to establish that an entity which is qualified by the universal in the form of emptiness of a dissimilar entity is denoted by a word, bhaviveka must explain about twc points: the first is that the emptiness of a dissimilar entity resides in a11 entities of the same class, in consequence of which the wordgo is used to refer to any cows, the second is that different kinds of emptiness of a dissimilar entity reside in one and the same entity, in con-sequence of which two different words, say, mila blue' and utpal  lotus, ' are used to refer to a single entity, a blue lotus. MHkv64abhedasattvadravyabhyam* ekato 'nekavrtpy**api  tadvinase 'vinasac ca nanyasmin tanmatir n*abhedasattvadravyabhyam]1,l,, ec, abhedasattvadravyabhyam s, sG, ms, abhedadravyasattvabhyamh.**ekato 'nekavrtty]l1,l2, h, s, sG,Ms, ekam anekavrtty ec)" fur-themmore, lthe universal in question」 exists as a single entity in many [individual] entities (ekato nekavrtti) since it exist [in individual entities] as something undifferentiated (abhedosatpva) and since it is not a substance (adravya).in addition, this universal does not perish when a substance which is its locus], perishes. For these reasons, it is not proper to say that the cognition of the uni-versal does not occur in another [substance]" 〓HkV65:anilanutpalabhinnarupenavyavadhanatah*samanadhikaranyam hi dvayor eku. rthavrttitch*anilanutpalabhinna-]h, s, ec, anilanutpalabhinna-]l1,l2, anilanutpalam bhinna- SG, ms)"indeed, [it is established that] two [such universals] have the same locus (samana-dhikaranya) since they can reside in one and the same entity. For they are not excluded from each other avyavadhana).[In the case of a blue lotus, for example, the two universals, being different from non-blue (anilabheda) and being different from non-lotuses (amutpalabhedd), reside in the  lue lotus] since [the blue lotus is ] something which is differentiated from non-blue entities and from non-lotuses." according to bhaviveka, the emptiness of a non-cow which a certain cow possesses is sin-gle, resides in other cows, and does not perish even if the cow perishes. This will explain the first point. Furthermore, emptiness of non-blue and that of anon-lotus do not contradict  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies each other, so that they can reside in one and the same entity. This will explain the second 〓 point. 4.1. From the point of view of bhaviveka who holds that an entity qualified by a universal is denoted by a word, if anyapoha as conceived of by the yogacaras had a claim to be a universal, then it would have to be accepted that anyapoha is denoted by a word. but, in his view, anyapoha cannot be treated as a universal. MHkV66ab: namyapoho 'nyasamanyam nyadharmad* visesavat)*dharmad]l1,l2, h, s, ec, -dharmau sG, ms)" [Thesis:][The universal called] ayapoha [of an entity] is not a universal common to] another entity;, [Reason.] because itis a property differing from entity to entity; [Ex-ample:] like a specific property (visesa).' as cow xexcludes non-x, so also does cowyexclude non-y. cow xis qualified by anyapo. hal and cowyby anyapoha2.in this case, ifanyapohal were the same as anyapoha2, ther the two cows would be identical with each other. but if anvapohal were different fromanyd. poha2, these two anyopohas could not be a universal. This is what bhaviveka intends to say by stating the argument. 4.2.MHKV66cd is to discuss the case in which anyapoha that qualifies an entity is not differentiated fromanyapoha that qualifies another entity. MHkV66cd: nabhavasyavisesatvad dhbhedah kambaladisuAbsence abhava) is not differen-tiated (visesa). consequently, one could not have different cognitions of entities such as a dewlap since such entities are not differentiated from one another].* In bhaviveka's view, anyapoha, as kumarila argues, consists in absence. that is, anyapo-ha amounts to anyubhova absence of others, ' or difference. a dewlap is qualified by anyd. pohal and a tail is qualifed by anyapoha2.anyopohal and anyapoha2 are the difference from non-dewlaps and that fromnon-tails. according to tj, absence has no essential nature (ngo bo nyid medpa,*nihsvabhava) and hence is something unreal.〓 these two anyapo-has are not differentiated from each other in that both are unreal. if they were unreal, then the dewlap and the tail would become the same entity since the dewlap has no difference from the tail and the tail has no difference from the dewlap.4) 43.recall that bhaviveka adopts the anvaya-vyatireka method to establish the non-distinc-tion between a universal and its holder. if a universal is grasped independently ofan entity which is supposedto possess it, it follows that the universal is distinct from the entity. 〓  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies MHkV67:vastvagrahe grahac casya heste* kalpyatavacyate**/taddvarenamyavacyatve tadvo-cyatvadi***hiyate /*neste]l1, h, s,ec, nesta l2, nestya sG, Ms.**kalpyatvavacyate]l1,l2, s, SG,Ms, kalpyatvavacyatve h, ec.***taddvarenanyavacyatve tadvacyatvadi] l1,l2, S, ec, tad-dvarenanyavacyatve tadvacyatadi h, taddvarenanyavacyatvadi SG,Ms)"itis not accepted that this [universal called anyapoha is] an object of a conceptual cognition and a significand of a word, since [the universal] is grasped evenifan entity [supposed to have the universal] is not grasped. if [an entity which is] different (anya) from [the universal] becomes a significand of a word by dint of the universal, then the universal loses the properties of being a significand of a word [and of be-ng an object of a conceptual cognition]." In bhaviveka's view, what is denoted by a word is an entity which is qualified by a univer sal that is not distinct from the entity. Thus it follows that the anyapoha the yogacaras consider to be a universal which is distinct from its qualificand cannot be denoted by a word. In addition, if an entity which is not qualified by the anyapoha were denoted bya word through the amyapoha, then it would follow that the anyopoha is not denoted by the word. 5.In MHKV68bhaviveka concludes that the Yogacaras' theory of emptiness of an effa-ble intrinsic nature' is untenable. MHK V68:tadanyabhinnarupsy vastuno 'nabhilapyata* yukiaivam ato 'yukta yogacara-nayoditih**'nabhilapyata] l1,l2, h, s, ec, 'nabhilapyata sG, Ms.**na yuktaivam ato 'yukta yogacaranayoditih」 h, S. Ec,na yuktyaiva manoyukta yogacaranayaditiL1,na yuktaiva manoyukta yogacaranayad itil2, SG;na yuktaiva manoyukta yogacaranayoditi Ms)"ln this way, it is not un-tenable that an entity which is different from something different from it cannot be denoted by〓 word. accordingly, the assertion of the doctrine of Yogacaras is unfounded.' In bhaviveka's view, it is reasonably established that an entity qualified by a universal is what is to be denoted by a word. The universal consists in emptiness of a dissimilar entity. Both the entity and the universal are real at the conventional level. when such a view is ac-cepted, the Yogacaras" theory of eemptiness of an effable intrinsic nature' cannot be ac-cepted. lt is to be noted that there is a variant reading of MHKV68ab. The tibetan version of MHKV68ab goes as follows. 〓 MHKv68ab (tib)de nigzhan gyingo bo ndes na brjod med nyid mi rigs*sycabhimna-rupatvad vastuno 'nabhilapyata "if the [anyapoha] has an essential nature different from [that of] aentity, in this case it is not reasonable that this [ayapoha] cannot be denoted by a word.? If the Yogacaras argued that anyapoha is distinct froman entity which is supposed to have  The japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies it, it would have to be said that the property anyapoha has an essential nature different from that of the entity, otherwise, no distinction could be made between the two. if the anyo poha, which the yogacaras hold to be what is to be denoted by a word. had an essential na-ture, they couldnot maintain the theory of 'emptiness ofan effable intrinsic nature. 6.the following points have become clear:(1)bhaviveka considers that the theory of apoha is the Yogacaras' linguistic theory to account for their view of emptiness as emptiness of an effable intrinsic nature.' (2)he defines anyapoha as a kind of universal (3)he tries to discredit the apoha theory within the frame of reference such that what is denoted by a word must be an entity qualified by a universal. this leads him to discuss how anyapoha can be related to an entity.(4)what he means by the word vastu entity' is in essence an individual, referred to by the word dravy 'substance' also. This is why, in lenying the property of being a universal to anyopoha, he can treat anyapoha as something like a specific property. (5)he regards anyapoha as "absence of others' or 'difference from others. bhaviveka's arguments against the theory of apoha clearly show that in his view the world in which verbalization takes place must have the conventional reality. lotes:1)See also Tj ad mHkv6[d215b6-2l,23.2for a full account of the invaya-vyatireka method, see g. cardona, 〓oReasoning from anvaya and vyatireka in early dvaita,"in studiesiindihilosopyhmedabad:1981).3)see <ref><canon>T</canon> [<w>217</w>]</ref>. 4)See hattori[19753-4]. (abbreviations)c: m.d. eckel, bhaviveka ad his buddhist opponemts harvard University press, 208).h: p. hoornaert, 〓annotated Translation of nadhyamakahrdayakoriko/turkaivd- 〓5-68," religioad culture(2001)3-47.hattori[1975] study of the chapter on apoha of the nfimamsaslokavarttika"(in japanese),memoirs of the faculpyofletters, kyoto University1:63ch. lindtner, " bhavya's Madhyamakahrdaya (pariccheda Five) Yogacaratattvaviniscayavatara," the adyr librory bulletin9(1995)37-65.lch. Lindtner, 〓adhyamakahrdaymof bhavy(The adyar library and Research centre, 201).MHk: 〓dhyamakahrdayakarika, see Ms, SG,l1,l,h, S, ec. s. a. Saito, " bhaviveka's Theory of Meaning," jibs5-2(04)(24)31).ms. jiang zhongxin, " anskrit tarkajva-sutra Manuscript copy"chinese),〓papersihomour ofdji xianlin the occasioof his 8oth birthdyjiang xi:1991).SG:S.S. bahulkar,"The madhyamak-hrdy-kaika of Bhavaviveka," sambhasa(1994)i-iv,1-49.tj. tarkaivala, d3856,P5256. &lt;Key words&gt; bhaviveka, yogacara, dignaga, samanya, vijatiyenasunyatva, anyapoha, vast (Graduate student, hiroshima university)  
</root>
