<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 〓 ksemendra's version of the dharmarucyavaduna. episodes of Merchants' Adventures and dipankara buddha's prophecy YaMasAKI Kazuho 1.Introduction The bodhisattvovadanakolpalatd v-klp) is a buddhist narrative of 108chapters com-posed by ksemendra (ca.977a.d.)1)The eighty-ninth chapter of this work is devoted to the story of the elder dharmaruci (dharmarucyavadana, dhar-av). dhar-av consists of three episodes:(1)that of the adventures of merchants, (2)that of the dipankara buddha's prophecy; (3)that of three heinous crimes. The first scholar to give much attention to dhar-avinav-klp is silk [],)who pres-ents a critical text and english translation of the third episode (vv.119-188) and shows that the immediate source of the episode is the one preserved in the divyavadana. The ain of this paper is to consider the sources ofepisodes12(vv.1-118). 1.1.list of the versionsof dhar-av The following is a list of the versions of dhar-av: ・divyavadana, chap.18dharmarucyavadan (divy, cowell &amp; neil, 228.1-262.6) ・mahovastu, dipankaravastumvu, Senart, 1.231.17248. apaduna,#486dhammaruci (<ref><canon>T</canon><v>29</v>-<p>431</p>.<c>15</c></ref>) ・zeng yi ahon jing(増一阿含經),vol.11,chap.20 shon chi shipin(善知識品),tr. by qu tan (瞿曇)and Sanghadeva(僧伽提婆)(t#1255972-599c4)[84-38a.d. ・〓en bie gong deun(分別功徳論),vol.415074b9c9) ・jing l yi xiang(經律異相).vol.25,tr. by bao chang(寶唱)(〓〓21219c1-191a7)[a.d dhar-av in the jjing l yi xiang is a word-for-word quotation from the text of dhar-av in the zeng yi ahan jing. thus there is no need to go into details about this version. 2.merchants adventures 2.1.episode structure before proceeding to the central argument, it will be useful to outline the narrative  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies events in the episode of merchants' adventures shownin dhar-avinv-klp. They are a follows:(i)motto. (v.1)(〓)while the buddha makes a sojourn in the jetavana, a party of merchants go to the seashore. (vv.23)(〓)seeing the merchants loading a ship, a pilot wamns them of the dangers of the ocean. (vv.47)(〓) the merchants set sail for  jewel producing island;, on their way back from the island, they happen to see a large fish. (vv.8-19)(v) The fish opens his mouth to swallow the merchants, at the critical moment they utter the name of the buddha for help, the buddha hears their cry and enables the fish to hear the cry by his supemnatural power, the fish gives up swallowing the merchants and disappears into the sea. (vv.2(vi)after completing a voyage, the merchants become arhats. (vv.2-27)(vi) The buddha tells the story about the past lives of the merchants. (vv.28)(vili ) the fish starves to death and his carcass is cast away oa coast by nagas. (vv.29-31)(vili) the fish is bomn in sravasti as a brahman's son named Dharmaruci , as a youth he leaves home and becomes a monk. (vv.32-34)(〓x dharmaruci always feels hunger, a householder who comes to give alms to himis surprised at his enormous appetite and asks the buddha who he is. (vv.35-43)(x)The buddhs makes a prophecy that dharmaruci will become an arhat and takes him to the coast where his carcass is left. (vv.4-4)(xi) dharmaruci feels an aversion to his own carcass, he becomes indifferent to worldly attachment and attains arhatship. (vv.49-60)(〓) The Buddha tells the story about the past lives of the dharmaruci: the story of the construction of the ksemankara buddha's caitya. (vv.-74) The versions ofthe episode of merchants' adventures found in mvu, ap and the Fen bie gong deucontain the following narrative elements: (i)(Mvu2,7-18, 〓en bie gong dev(Mvu2431-21,Fenbie gongde lun 〓b2c3),(v)(mvap4322-5,en bie gog de 4).o the other hand, the version of this episode indivy contains the following: (〓)(228.22- 229.15),(〓)(2291-2302),(〓)(230221),(〓)(23122.2,(v) (232.22-23320),(v)(23320-234.,(vi)(234-16),(〓x)(23416-236.27),(x) (236.27-239.18),(xi)(239.18-240.2,(x)(24017-246.4).it is to be noted that the version in the zeng yi ahan jing merely mentions that dharmaruci is transmigrated into a fish5972-27). we should specifically note with regard to elements(〓 dhar-av in mvu does not mention the jewel-producing island.  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies  dhar-av in mvu gives the leader of merchants the name sthapakarnika which is not found in the other versions. indhar-av in mvu, furthermore. it is the elder purnaka who hears the merchants cry. ・dhar-avinp does not mention either jewel-producing island or the buddha. dhar-av in the fen bie gong de lun mentions the length of the fish: about seven-thousand yoiand 2.2.discrepancies between divy and av-klp The versions indivy and av-klp do not include this description These features strongly suggest that ksemendra consulted the dhar-av preserved in the Divy while composing his own version of merchants' adventures in the av-klp. 2.2.discrepancies between divy and av-klp as shown above, ksemendra's version of the episode of merchants' adventures contains anumber of narrative elements previously exhibited in the dhar-av of the divy. however there are a few discrepancies between the two versions. They are as follows: (a)Ii) Ksemendra's version gives the fish the name timimgilagila imimgila-swallower), while the version of divy the name timitimimgila. (b)In(i), ksemendra's version states that twelve suns rise at the end ofthe universe, seven suns rise in the dhar-av of divy.)(c)in (vi)(ix) and (xii), ksemendra's version gives dharmaruci's father, a householder in Sravasti, and a householder in ksemavati the names sumati, donavrata and dharmasila respectively, while dhar-avindivy does not mention these names. Point (a) shows that ksemendra introduces modifications to the original name so as tc emphasize how big the fish is. point (b) suggests that he adopts the cosmology found in the Puranic literature. in the matsyapurana (bombay ed.)106.12,for example, it is said that the twelve suns burn the universe to nothing at its end. point (c) shows that ksemen-dra invents names for characters in the episode. clearly the names bespeak the personali-ties ofthe characters.4 3.dipankara buddha's prophecy 3.1. listofthe versions ofthe episode of dipankara buddha's Prophecy There are many versions of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy. This episode is widely found in the Pali, tibetan, and chinese canons.  The following versions of the episode will be considered here. ・ls brgya thams karmasataka),(d#3485;井10078798) ・apadana, theri-apadana#28yasodhara s,587.17-589.4) ・〓iu xg beqi jing(修行本起經),tr. by kang neng xiang(康孟詳)(<ref><canon>T</canon>井<p>1844</p><c>b</c><l>16</l>-<p>463</p><c>b</c></ref>  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies ・〓o shuo tai zi yniying benqi jing(佛説太子瑞王本起經),tr. by zhi qian(支謙)(<ref><canon>T</canon>〓<w>1854</w><p>72</p><c>c</c><l>16</l>- <p>473</p><c>b</c><l>11</l></ref>)[222-228a.d.] ・〓i chupu  benqi jing(異出菩薩本起經),tr. by nie dao zhen(道眞)(〓〓1886171- 618a5)[280-313a.d. ・guoqu iziyin guo jing(過去現在因果經),vol.1,tr. by gunabhadra(求那跋陀羅)(t#189 620c23-623a23)[435-443a.d. fo ben xing ji jing(佛本行集經),vol.3, tr. by jnanagupta(那崛多)(<ref><canon>T</canon>井<w>19064</w>1-<p>669</p><c>a</c><l>03</l></ref>) [587-591a.d. ・foben xing jing(佛本行經),vol.5,tr. by bao yun(寶雲)(<ref><canon>T</canon>#<w>1939218</w>-<p>93</p><c>c</c><l>7</l></ref>)[11th century a.d 〓ahoramnakutasutra(大寶積經),vol.54, tr. by xua zang(玄奘)(〓#31031717-319a3) [7th century a.d. ・dachengpzheng fa jing(大乘菩薩藏正法經),vol.39, tr. by dharmapala(法護)(t#316 882bc22)[11th century a.d.] ・sie(四分律),vol.31,tr. by buddhayasas(佛陀耶舎)(〓井142878226-785c22)[410-412 A.D. lt is to be noted that the karmasataka version of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy is a literal tibetan translation of the divy version. accordingly the karmasataka version will be left out of consideration. [197a.d. 3.2.episode structure The episode of dipankara buddha's prophecyinav-klp has the following structure :(i) dipankara buddha appears in the city dipavati. (vv.7-77)(〓)king dipa who rules over dipavati sends a messenger to king vasava to ask the latter to join the former in wel-coming dipankara buddha. (v.78)(〓)king vasava performs a rite with the assistance of a brahman youth named Sumati , the king offers him in retumn five kinds of treasures: a bed, a pitcher, a bowl, five-hundred karsapanas, and his daughter. (vv.79-82)(〓) su mati accepts these treasures with the exception of the king's daughter, other than the daughter returns to dipavati. (vv.83-87)(v) sumati offers the four accepted treasures to his teacher, thereafter, he has strange dreams. (vI) Sumati asks a sage to explain his dreams, the sage suggests that he request dipankara buddha to explain the dreams, sumati and his friend Mati go to dipavati. (vv.9193)(v) Sumati reaches dipavati and hears that dipankara buddha will enter the city; sumati looks for flowers in order to pay homage to dipankara buddha, Sumati comes across king vasava's daughter carning seven lotuses. (vv.94-99)(vi) the daughter gives sumati five lotuses on condition that Sumati prom-ises to become her husband in the distant future. (vv.10104)(〓〓)dipankara buddha.  the japanese assciation of Indian and buddhist studies welcomed by king dipa and king vasava, enters dipavati; miracles happenin the city. (vv. 105-107)(X)Sumati and king vasava's daughter throw the lotuses towards dipankara Buddha, Sumati spreads out his hair to cover a mud puddle in order to keep the dipankara Buddha's feet from being smeared with the mud. (vv.108-112)(〓I)dipankara buddha steps o sumati's hair and prophesies that Sumati will become the buddha named Sakya-muniin the future. (vv.11-115)(〓)mati is annoyed that the dipankara buddha steps on his friend's hair and hurls abuse at dipankara buddha. (v.116)(〓) Sumati and Mati give up worldly life and become monks, after their death, Sumati is rebornin the tusita heaven, while Mati is reborn in hell for having hurled abuse at dipankara buddha. (vv.116-118) a the above-mentioned versions of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy ex-cept ap and Fen bie gong de lun, with minute differences, contain the following narrative elements:(i),(v),(v),(x),(xI).divy version, on the other hand, contains the following:(1)(21(〓)(246-,(〓)(246.1-24714)(〓)(247 25),(v)(2472248,(v)(242,(v)(249217),(v) (24917-4,(〓)2525112)(x)(25122.4),(〓)(252.-7,252.8 253.7),(〓)(252.7-8),(〓)(253.-22).Noteworthy is narrative element (v).in the version of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy in divy and av-klp, it is ter dreams that Sumati has (divy 2472248.,av-klpvv.89-90),while in the version in the guo q i yi gu jing621b2-c1)itis five dreams that Sumati has. This fact further suggests that ksemendra composed his version of the episode of dipankara bud-dha's prophecy on the basis of divy version. 3.3.discrepancies between divy and av-klp Ksemendra's version of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy and divy's have he following discrepancies: (d)i〓), ksemendra gives king vasava's daughter the name sundari, which is not foundindhar-avindivy. it is to be noted that her name is蘇 羅婆提(*suravati?) in the version in the si fe748c1-14).(e)ivi),ksemendra gives the sage the name parndv.91),which is also not foundindhar-avindivy. (f) 〓xi),Ksemendra celebrates the prophecy of dipankara buddha with a showering of flowers (puspavarsa)(v.1-1ab),while the dhar-avindivy describes this celebration at the arrival of dipankara buddhaindipavati (257-9). what is true of point (c) in ksemendra's version of the episode of merchants' adven-  The japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies tures is tnue of points (d) and (e).it is important to note that the version in the guo qu 〓zi yin guo jing 622b15-17)also celebrates the prophecy of dipankara buddha with the flower-shower. this shows that it is likely that ksemendra's version and this Chinese verslon have a common source. 4.Conclusion we have considered the sources of the episode of merchants' adventures and that of di-pankara buddha's prophecy indhar-av ofav-klp. it has been shown that the sources of the two episodes which dhar-av of av-klp contains are foundindivy. Thus it follows that the source of dhar-av of av-klp is divy. but we have to note that there is the possibility that the version of the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy which ksemendra made use of had been altered by the influence of the source of the guo qu ziyin guo jing. in addi-tion, we must also note that the discrepancies between dhar-avindivy and av-klp shows thatin composing the two episodes ksemendra makes minor alterations in order to interest the general reader. Notes *My special thanks are due to dr. david mellins for correcting my english correcting and giving many suggestions. i also wish to express my thanks to profs. kiyoshi okano and kei kataoka for providing me the copies of the manuscripts of av-kip. i gratefully acknowledge helpful discussions with prof. junko matsumura on the episode of dipankara buddha's prophecy.1)S. ch. das &amp; vidyabhusana, eds., "dharmarucyavadana," iavadun kapalata, (calcutta: baptist Missior press,1888),192)jonathan. Silk,"The story of dharmaruci, in the dipapadana and ksemendra's bodhisattvavaddnakalpalata," 〓51(2008)37-185.〓 For the bibliographical reference to the saptasuryyodayasutras, see kiyoshi okano, sarvaraksitas 〓ahasamvartanikatho (Sendai: seminar of indology,1998),313-314)See kiyoshi Okano, "ksemendra's dasakarmaplupyavadana," southalassical studies 2(2007)203. 5)for the detailed discussion of the pali versions, see Minoru Seki, " study on the durenidana," 〓b2(1972)831-835, junko Matsumura, "The sumedhakatha inali literature and its Re-lation to the northemn buddhists textual tradition," journal of the international college 〓st-graduate buddhist studies1(2009)101-133.6)on the karmasataka, see junko libu-chi, "prediction vyakarana) in the karmasataka," bunka6(Sendai: The literary society, Tohoku university, 1997)397. iibuchi supposes that the compiler of the karmasataka bor. rowed the episode of the dipankara buddha's prophecy from dhar-avin divy. (This work was partially supported bya grant-in-aid for JSps fellows) &lt;Key words&gt;dharmarucyavadana, divyavadana, bodhisattvovadanakalpalata, ksemendra Graduate student. hiroshima university/ JSPSResearch Fellow  
</root>
