<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies The concept of rupa and murtatvain the vaisesika School a Study of concept of Matter inancient india MIuRa hirofumi 0. Introduction The concept of matter was one of the most important problems in western thought. in India, it has not been disregarded, though there was no concept exactly corresponding to matter. only few attempts, however, have so far been made at the concept of the matter in ancient india. The vaisesika School, which is one of six indian orthodox schools of philosophies, is known as ancient realism. in this paper, the author intends to examine the theoretical struc-ure of the concept of "matter" in this school, based on the three main texts, the yaisesika-sutraa.d.), the dasapadarthi(勝宗十旬義論4-5c.a.d.),1) and the prasastapada-bhasy.a.d.). The vaisesika system has two different material concepts. one is rupa, the other murta-tva. little attention has been given to this point. we will begin by considering these two concepts. 1.The rupa Basically, the rupa is a word meaning both color and form, and was used to indicate matter in ancient india. in the vaisesika school, the rupa is one of guna (attribute) that is one of six padartha-s (basic categories).〓also in the vaisesika school, the meaning of rupa was the same as its general meaning in ancient india until the time of the vaisesika-sutra. but after the dasapadarthi, the rupa was strictly limited to only one meaning, that of color. The question is the change in this meaning. 1.1.The rupain the vaisesikasutra In the vaisesikasutra, the rupa is defined to the color and form belonging to the dropy (substance), and enabling perception with eyes.'i other words, only dravya with the  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies rupa can be perceived by eyes.lso the rupa enables perception ofmotion of substanc-es.) to take a simple example, sabd (sound) without the rupa cannot be perceived with eyes,〓 though the motion of substances which have the rupa can be perceived with eyes. viewed in this light, the rupa in the vaisesikasutra can be regarded as an important con-cept that enables perception of substance and its motion, and a word that almost indicates matter in the vaisesika school as well as ancient india. 1.2.The rupa in the dasapadarthi and the prasasiapadabhosya also in the dasapadarthi and the prasastapadabhasya, the rupa is one of guna belong ing to the dravya, anda concept of enabling perception with eyes. however, there was n description which relates rupa to the movement in the dasapadorthi and the prasastapadd-bhasya. it was that the term of murtatva began to be used as a term for form at about the same time as the dasapadorthi. in the following the prasastapaddbhosya, moreover, the term of rupa was used only to mean color, and the term of murtatva meant form of the moving substance. to sum up, the change in the meaning of the rupa happened as a result of the murtatva, which was a new concept of form in the vaisesika school. the questior which we must consider nextis the concept of murtatva. 2.The murtatvq The word 'murtatva" is derived from the past passive participle of root of murch' by adding the suffix tvd' meaning solid. and the murtatva is used to mean material form in the vaisesika school after the dasapadorthi. 2.1.The murtatyain the dasapadarthi In the dasapadarthi, the concept of murtatva is used as the murta(有質礙,materia form) in the part of explanation of the motion. the motion is classifled into five types in the dasapadorthi, the one of which is the gamana (going).the gamana is caused by the veg velocity) belonging the murta-draysubstance with material form),the veg does not exist except the travya which has murta. inother words, only the murta-dravy an do the gamana,  and the distinction of movable things and immovable things is the same as the distinction of dravya with murta and dravya without murta.1 it follows from what has been said that the murta or murtatva), in the dasapadarthi, was an important factor of substances which can move.  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 2.2.The muriatvain the prasastapodubhosya also in the prasastapadabhasya, the concept of murtatva is discussed in the relation to motion. The murtatva is a common character of five moving dravya, which are ksiti (earth), jld (water), jyotis (fire), amila (air), and manas (consciousness).11)and exist-ing in the murt-dravya is the one of twelve common characters of the movement.1 Namely, only the murta-droyravya with murtatva, or substances with material form) has mobility, and the concept of murtatva has a close relation to the motion. a11 these things make it clear that the dasapadarthi and the prasastapadabhasya have the congruous views about the concept of the murtatva. both of them consider the murta- 〓v as an important concept relating the motion. 3.conclusion lt should be concluded, from what has been said above, that the change in the usage of rupa occurred simultaneously with introducing the new concept explaining motion of sub-stances, which is the murtatva, in the text of dasapadarthi. The usage of rupa remained as the guna belonging to the dravya, and a concept of en-abling perception by eyes. This usage may be common to throughout the vaisesikasutra, both in the dasapadarthi and the prasastapodabhasya, and was inherited by posterior the Nyaya-vaisesika school. we have, however, the most significant fact that the rupa enabled perception of motion of substances until the vaisesikasutra, but the usage of rupa was ubdued, as was showed by the fact that there was no description that rupa related to movement since the dasapadorthi. 〓n the other hand, the murtatva, which is not discussed in the yaisesikasutra, began to be used simultaneously as an important factor of movement in the dasapadorthi and the prasastapadabhosya. The murtatva means material form, and only the murta-dravysub-tances with material form) can move. and the concept of rupa cames to be used only to mean color since the dasapadorthi. Then, why did not the rupa relate to the motion and did not comes to be used only to mean color? it is for this reason that the problem of movement of the vayu (air) and the iancs consciousness) arose. the movement of the vayu cannot be seen with eyes, be-cause the vayu does not have the rupa. since the manas is minute, the movement of the manas cannot be seen with eyes, either. Therefore, the factor of movement common to the  〓he japanese association of indian and buddhis studies vayu and the manas are needed, and its factor is the murtatvd. Most significantly, the problem of how to conceive and explain motion of substances. which was the very peculiar to vaisesika school, affected the concept of matter itself, and brought the change of usage of the concept of the rupa and the murtatva, which are the material concept, in the vaisesika theory. in the vaisesika system, the concept of matter has a close relation to their original movement theory (notes) 1)Since original Sanskrit texts of the dasapadarthi have been lost in india, we examine a Chinese version translated by xuangzang(玄奘:602-664)of the dasapadorthiin this paper. 2)vSc1.5 rupa-rasa-gandha-sparsah skhyah parimanani prthaktyam smyoga-vibhagat paratva-qparatve buddhyh sukha-duhkhe iccha-dvesu prayatnas c gua p.2,il.17-19). 3)vsc6 mahapy aneka-dravyavattvad rupaccupalabdhih(p.33,1.2). 4)vSc48 rupa-samskara-abhavad vayay amupalabdhih(p.33,1.8). vc9aneka-dravyena dravyena samavayod rupa-visesac c upalabdhihvSc:p.33,1. 12). 5)vsc42smkhyah parimanami prthakpvam smyoga-vibhagu paratva-apararve karmc ca rupi-drapya-samavayac caksusani / (p.33,1l.21-22) vSc4.113aripisv acaksusatvot/p.34,1.3). 6)vsc2..28sab] acaksusattcn na karmap.21,1.15). 7)dp[3:色云何.謂,唯眼所取,一依,名色.[what is the rup that which is per ceived only by eyes and has one [substance] as its locus is the ripa.](p.256,1.1),[40]:現量 者,於至實色等根等合時,有了相生,是名現量.[the direct cognition: that which take: form of direct experience and is produced when perceivable substances, the rupa and sense or-gans and so ocomein contact [ which each other] is direct cognition.」 (p.257,1.2). 〓h[27]trayanam pratyaksatva-rupavattva-dravatvami p.24,1.12),[80tatra rupam caksur-grahyam prthivy-udaka-jvalama-vgtti dravya-upalambhakamnoyana-sahakari suk-l-ady-aneka-prakoram salila-adi-paramansu mipycm parthiva-paramanusv aghi-samyog-vi-rodhi srv-karya-drapyesu karana-guna-purvakam asraya-vinasad eva vinasyati iti (p.104, 〓1.1-5 8)d[4]:作因者,謂,掩擲等生業所生,依附一實,有質礙實所有勢用,是名作因.行 謂勢用.[The cause of action: that which is produced by action caused by hitting, shaking and so on, has one substance as its locus and is the veg velocity) ofthe murta-dray(substances with material form) is cause of action, that is, impression called the vega.j (p.257,11.2-21). 9)dp[]:行業云何.謂,一切有質礙實和合,依一實,合離因,名行業.[what is the gamam (going)?that which is inherent in a11 of the murta-dropysubstances with material form), has one substance as its locus and is the cause of connection and separation is move-  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies The concept of rupa and mirtatva in the vaisesika School (H. MIuRa) ment.] (p.258,il.5-6). 10)dp[85]:如有動作無動作,有質礙無質礙,有勢用無勢用,有彼此軆無彼此〓,應知 亦爾.[lt should be known that the distinction between movable things and immovable things is the same as that between things with murta and things without murta, between things with ve-locity and things without velocity and between things with priority and posteriority and without priority and posteriority.] (p.259,i.1. 11)pbh[23]ksiti-jla-jyotir-anila-manasam kriyovattva-murtatya-paratv-qparatva-vegavatt-vani/p.21.il.21-22). 12)pbh[38]:utksepana-adinam pancanam api karmatva-sambandhah ek-dravyavattvam kysanikatvam murta-drvy'ovyttinvamagunavattvam gurntv-dravatva-proyatnq-samy'ogqjatvan sv-kary-smyog-virodhitvam smyog-vibhog-nirapekya-koranatvam asamavayi-karanat-vam sv-para-asraya-samaveta-karya-arambhakatvam samana- jatiya-anarambhakatvam dra-vy-anarambhakatvamprati-niyata-joti-yoginvam ig-visista-korya-arambhakapvamc vise- 〓hp.290,il.2-8). (abbreviations and bibliography) vSc: muni sri jambuvijayaji (ed.), vaisesikasutra of kanada with the commentary of n-dranand G.s. No.136),baroda: oriental institute, 1982. 〓p keiichi miyamoto (ed.), "the chinese version of the dasapadarthi critical edition," apen-dix of the metaphysics ad epistemology of the earby vaisesikas, pune: bhandarkar oriental Re-search institute,1996. Pbh. dvivedined.), the prasastapad bhoshya with commentaty yoyakandat of iRa, delhi: sri Satguru publications, 1984. bronkhost, J. and Ramseier, y. (ed.) [1994] word index to the prasastapadabhasya, acomplete word index to the printed editions q prasastapadabhosya, delhi: motilal banarsidass publishers private Limited. Mishra. umesha [1936]conceptioatter, acordhing to nyoy-yisesika, delhi (Rep.1987). Mizuno, kogen(水野弘元) [1951]" bukkyo ni okeru shiki (bussitsu) no gainen ni tsuite," vi hakuin kanreki kinen Ronshu. tokyo. iwanami Shoten, Publishers. 『勝宗十旬義論』<ref><canon>大正新脩大藏經</canon>第<v>54</v>卷事彙部(下),外教部no.<w>2138</w></ref>. &lt;Key words) vaisesika, rupa, murtatva, matter, realism (Part-time lecturer, kanagawa Prefectural college of nursing and midwifery, litt.d.  
</root>
