<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies Santaraksita's Interpretation of the sahopalambhaniyam proof Re-examined MatSuOkaHiroko 1.In the pratyaksapariccheda of his pramanaviniscy dharmakirti gives two sorts ot proofs of the non-difference abhedd) between an object of a cognition and the cognition of the object: from the two being necessarily perceived together (sahopalambhaniyama) and from the cognition's object consisting in a cognition amvedana).1In the bahi-rarthapariksa of his tattvasangraha Santaraksita (c725-788)devotes two verses to ex-plaining the sahopalambhamiyama proof. TS bP66-67(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>22030</w></ref>)[j1037b-1567.-9,6147] vatsamvedanamvsyd yy' samvedanam thrnvm/ tasmad avyatiriktamit tato va m vibhiddote  yatha miladhiyah svotma dvitiyo v yathodupch iladhivedanam cedam milakorasya vedanm7 MatsuMoto (1980288)reads this set of verses as follows. "[Major premise:] when a perception (smvedana-upalabdhi) of some [cognition] is necessarily a perception of some [object], that object is not different (opyatirikia) from the cognition, or does not differ (na vibhidyote) from the cognition, just as the self-essence of the cognition of blue [is not different from the cognition of blue」 ,or the second moon [does not differ from the first moon [Minor premise:.] This perception of the cognition of blue (nil-dh) is [necessarily] the percep tion of the form of blue (nilukora).[conclusion][Therefore, the form of blue is not different ol does not differ from the cognition of blue.], according to MatSuMoto (198279),4)Santaraksita here intends to show that by the neg-ative particle q-in the word abhed in the proof dharmakirti means two kinds of negation paryudasa and prasajyapratisedha, so that this word may signify "identity'yatirikia) and "mere negation of difference' na vibhidyate) between the image of blue (nilakora) and the cognition of blue (niladhi).in addition, MatsuMoto considers that the first exam-ple (drstanta), a pair of the cognition of blue and this cognition's own essence, is given to illustrate the identity and the second, a paif of the first moon and the second one appearing  The japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies to an erroneous cognition, is given to illustrate the mere negation of difference. it is obvi-ous that his interpretation is infuenced by those by dharmottara and tibetan scholars, who pay much attention to the question of which negation of the two is preferable for the word abheda mentionedby dharmakirtiin the proofs in question. we must say, however, that the tattvasangrahapanjika by kamalasila (c7-795), who is a direct disciple of Santaraksita, does not support the view of Matsumoto. The aim of this paper is thus to make clear how kamalasnla inteiprets TS bp66-67,on the basis of a newly edited text of TSP, to show that the disjunctive vain santaraksita's argument to prove the non-difference between the image of blue and the cognition of blue is not used to give two interpretations of abheda but to show the mutual non-difference between them. 2.kamalasila comments on kk.66-67as follows. TSPoTS bp66-67[J24-6,23112-15,g6710-17,691.18-2 (a)ysya smvedanam yatsamvedanam/ (b)tad ewa yatsamvedanam yasya samvedanam miyamena nanyat tasmat prathamayacchabdava-yad abhinnam krtam ekantena d dvitiyayacchabdavacyam8 (c) yadva viparyayenobhedah sdhyah/ (d)etad uktam bhavati / yasmad aprthak yatsamvedanamewa tat tasmad abhinnam yatha mla 〓ih svasvabhavat / yatha va taimirikajnanapratibhasidiiya udupah candramah (e) niladhivedanamcedam itipaksadharmopasamharah/ (f) dharmy atra nilakarataddhiyou  yor abhinnatvam sadhyadharmah yathoktah shopalam bhamiyamo hetuh/ (g)idrsa evacuryiye sahopalambhaniyamad ipyodu proy'oge hetartho 'bhipretah. 〓(a) The word yatsamvedanam is [a tatpurusa compound] equivalent to the string ysy samvedan- 〓m cognition of X.' (b)if a cognitionof y is necessarily nothing other than a cognition of X, it is inevitably considered that Y-the referent of the second yd ys)is not different (abhinna) from-the referent of the first yad" yat-), (c) or conversely viparyayena) , it should be established that xis not different from y. (d) the following is meant: if xis never perceived separately fromy, xis not different from y; just as a cognition of blue [is not different from the cognition's] own essence (svatmnsvabha-va),or just as the second moonuddrama), which appears to the cognition of aperson suffering from eye-disease, [is not different from the first one]. (e)by stating niladhivedanam cedmnd this perception of a cognition of blue' a [proving ] property is applied to the subject of the argumentin questionpaksadharmopasamhara). (f)in this argument, a subject property possessor (dharmin) is both the image of blue (nilakora)  The japanese asociation of Indian and buddhist studies Santaraksita's Interpretation of the sahopalambhamivam proof Re-examined (h. Matsuoka)(1 and a cognition of blue, a property to be proved is the non-difference between these two,a logical easonhetu) is 'being necessarily perceived together' (sahopalambhamipama) as described [by Dharmakirti]. (g)anexpression for the logical reason used by the great teacher [dharmakirti] in the formulatior of the argument where the phrase sahopalambhamiyamat "because of being necessarily perceived ogether" and such are employed has this very meaning.' lt is important to note (c).kamalasila paraphrases the phrase tat tato va n vibhidyate in verse oocd as yadva viparyayenabheduh sdhyah. The word viparyaya means "converse nverse.' it is certain that, if viparyoya relation obtained between paryudasa and prasajy-apratisedha, MatSuMoto's interpretation could not be categorically denied. but, by saying viparyayena conversely,' kamalasila intends to say that when there is non-difference be-tween xand Y, the following must hold: x is not different from y, y is not different from X. consider the following statement by kamalasila: TSPoTS bp66-67[J2123,239,G568.7-,b69222-693.1]. (a)n hy atraikenaivopalambha ekopalambhaiy qym artho  bhipretah/ (b)〓in tarhi / jinanaineyayoh parasparam eko evopalambho mprthag iti / y eva hi jnanopalam bhah s eva jneyasyeva jneyasy saeva jnanasyeti yavat/ 〓a) For, here [in the argument in question], [even if the word saha can be taken as synonymous with the word eka the same,'] the following meaning cannot be intended to convey: ekopalambha "the same-perception' in the sense of the perception just by the same entity' (ekenaivopalambhah) takes place. (b) rather, the following meaning can be intended to convey. the perceptionupalambha) of a cognitionnana) and that of an object of the cognition jneya) are mutually (parasparam) identi-a1 (eka) and not separate from each other a prthak).In short, the perception of an object of a cognition is the same as that of the cognition and the perception of the cognition is the same as that of the object of the cognition.' we must note (b),in which by saying parasparam mutually' kamalasila makes the point that when there is non-difference between xand Y, the following both must hold: x is not different from y, y is not different fromx. he states that the perceptionupalam-bha) of a cognition(nana) and that of an object of the cognition (ineya) are mutually (parasparam) identical (eka) and not separate from each other a prthak).〓acognition of x'and a cognition of y"in Santaraksita's argument correspond to the perception ofa cognition' and the perception of an object of the cognition,' respectively. ifthe cognition of x and the cognition of Y are mutually identical, then it must be said that x and y are  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies mutually identical. 3.as I said earlier, MatsuMoto holds that the second example in Santaraksita's argument is given to illustrate abheda as "mere negation of difference.' it is difficult to bring forward evidence to show this. consider the following statement by kamalasila. TSPoTSbp66-67[j2a7-8,231b17-2322,g567.20-24,69.-10 (a)candrattaysy sahopalambhabhimano sti loke / (b) nctayor bhedo sti paramarthatch/ (c) athaca sha sasidvayam upalambhamahaituaktaro bhavamti / (d) evam ihapi jnanad avyatirikiam qpi bahir iva bhasamanam akaram dvitiyam krtva kalpitabhe-danibandhanah sahasabdh prayuktah (e)na hi sarvah sabdo vyavaharo yathavastunivesi / yena sahasabdaprayogamatrena vastuprati-baddhasya lingasyanyatvam syat/ "(a) The world has the belief that two moons are perceived together. (b) but, from the ultimate point of view, there is no difference between the two. (c)[objection:] people say: "we perceive two moons together (saha sasidvayam upalambhama he)." (d) [answer:] even so, in this case also, they use the word saha together' on the basis of the con. ceptually posited difference between the two moons, treating the image of the second moon, which appears to the [erroneous] cognition and which is not different (yatirikia) from the cognition, as if it were an extemnal entity. (e) Indeed, any verbal activity does not enter into a relation with an entity as it really is. otherwise, the logical reason [shopalambhaniyama], which is essentially connected with a real entity, woulc be of quite a different nature simply because the word sahais used." aperson suffering from eye-disease sees a double moon. in this case it is said that there is no difference between two moons. The difference is merely something conceptually posit-ed. letus note (d). kamalasila states that the second image (dvitiyam akaram) of a moon appearing to theerroneous cognition, is not different from this erroneous cognition (nanad avyatiriktam).this statement suggests how it is to be explained that the second moon is not different from the first moon. now suppose that two moon-images appear to the erro-neous cognition. it must be the case that, as the second image of a moon is not different from the cognition, so the first image of a moon is also not different from the cognition. This cognition is single. Thus it follows that the second image of a moon is not different from the first image of a moon, namely that the second moon is not different from the first moovyatirikta). this naturally implies that the description of the relation between the  The japanese asociation of Indian and buddhist studies jantaraksita's Interpretation of the sahopalambhamivama proof Re-examined H. Matsuoka) second and first moons for which the phrase na vibhidtyate is used is equivalent to that for which the wordavyatirikiais employed. 4.we have seen how kamalasila interprets TS bp66-67.on the basis of kamalasila's comments on the set of verses, we may reasonably say the following. it is unlikely that Santaraksita takes the term abhedindharmakirti's sahopalambhamiyama proof in view of the two functions of the negative particle. Santaraksita lays stress on the mutual non-dif-ference between an obiect of a cognition and the cognition of the object: the former is not different from the latter, the latter is not different from the former. The difference is merely a conceptual construct. (notes) 1)pvin35. 2)JPb,rigt, vedanat G. 3)MatsuMoto has rendered yatsamvedanamink. 6a as 'a perceptionmvedana-upalabdhi) of some lcognition」.' but this rendering is inaccurate. it is proper to translate the text for the pervasion as follows. "if a perception of y is necessarily a perception of x, Y is not different from xor x does not differ fromY.' 4)Kajiyaa(19825,60)and iaa199184)agree with matSuMoto. 5)pratikas in the following text are indicated in bold type. 6)em, n.e. gt, y mvedanam j, y samvedanm 7)Jp, ins. /Gb. 8)e, dvitivam v-JPGb. 9)ysmad aprthak yatsamvedanam em1, ysy ysmad aprthak samvedanam em2, gag zhig gamg ls ogs shig mair rigt, y yasmad aprihak samvedanam g, yasmad aprthak samvedanam jpb. 10)jb,pratibhabhasi [ic] g. 11)Jp, kho bb gyis dmigs zhes bya bar t, sasidvayopalambhat saheti g b. 〓 〓 (Literature and abbreviations B. s. sastri's ed. of TS/TSP. varanasi182.〓p bahirarthapariksa.Ge. krsnamacarya's ed. of TS/tSP, baroda1926.iwta99takashi iata, sahopalambhamiyama, stuttgart. j jaisalmer mss of TS/tSP.Kajiyaa1982Yuichi kajiyama,"chugan-shiso no rekishi tc Bunken"[n japanese], in a. hirakawa/y. kAjiyaa/J. takasaki (eds.),kodaio-bukkyo7. Tokyo,1-83.MatSuMoto1980 Shiro MatsuMoto, " sahopalambh-miyama," soto- kenkuu kivo12,265-298(l).〓 patan Mss of S/tSP.pvine. steinkelner's ed. of the prama-uaviniscaa1-2,beijing-vienna07.t tibetan. tS. tattvasangraha Santaraksita).tSp Tattvasangrahapanjika (kamalasila).  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies 2)santaraksita's interpretation of the sahopalambhamiyama proof Re-examined (h. matsuoka) (This work was partially supported by a grant-in-aid for JSPS Fellows.) (key words) santaraksita, kamalasila, tatrvasangraha, tatrvasangrahapaniika, bahirartha-pariksa, sahopalambhaniyama (Graduate student, hiroshima university, JSPS Research Fellow)  
</root>
