<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies Woncheuk圓測obimba本質and pratibimba影像 in his Commentoryon the samdhinirmocan-sutra A. Charles MullEr Background In its standard meaning in yogacara works, bimba, translated into chinese as本質(c. benzhi, j. honzetsu), refers to the bare form of an obiect of sense or of thought, before it has received any interpretation, overlay, or categorization through the cognitive process. Its counterpart is pratibimba影像(c. yingxiang, j. yozo), which is a reflected "image"1 of the bimba, that which we actually "see"" on the surface of consciousness, having been interpreted and transformed by the cognitive process. there was, during the early reception in the west of weishi documents, a widely-promulgated misunderstanding of the term honzetsu, wherein it was often rendered into english as " archetypes," as seen, for example, in daito shuppansha's japanese-english buddhist dictionary(Revised edition,1991) which contains the following entry: honzetsu本質archepype. This term is used by the hosso sect to indicate the true substance a phe-nomenon of which we perceive only the image. Thus, when we see a tree, we don't see the tree it-self (which is the honzetsu) but the image of the tree which is reflected in the sobun相分(cf. shi bun) division of our consciousness This is partly right, in the sense that we do only see an image-of whatever it is that is there. but it is clear that the authors ofthis dictionary held some combination of misunder-standing ofthe meaning ofarchetypes, ' orof the function of biia("seeds") in the dlayavi-inana. after a11, these " seeds," while producing phenomena, are themselves continually be-ing impregnated and reproduced, bringing about a complex condition of incessant combination of change that includes continuity of sameness. we will return to consider possible causes for this kind of interpretation below.  〓he japanese associationof Indian and buddhisstudies woncheuk圓測on bimba本質and pratibimba影像inhis commentory onthe samdhimirmocama-sitra c mulLER)(199) development of the bimb-pratibimba frameworkin the yogacara texts Most of the detailed explanations and applications of the bimba-pratibimba pair-espe cially those that have informed the canonical definitions contained inast asan buddhist lexicons-are derived from kuiji's窺基(632-682)commentaries: especially those or the yogacarabhumi-sastra, ' and his detailed elaborations of the cheng weishi lun.4 thes: works contain extensive discussions of本質and影像from various perspectives. Most importantly, he often treats these notions in the context of their application within the ev-ryday waking consciousness, rather than only in the context of yogic trances. we will1 briefly look at some of kuiii's contributions below The initial appearance of the pair, however, occurs within a well-known passage that is shared almost verbatim between the samdhinirmocana-sutra and the yogdcarabhumi-sas-tra.in this initial reference to the pair of bimba and pratibimba, the meanings of, and re. lationship between the two terms are explained only in a very minimal way, leaving the meaning of bimbaitself almost fully open to speculation. it is only in later Yogacara works (mainly commentarial works) that the concepts come to be defined as we know them to-day. also, the discussion in this passage of the samdhinirmocana-sutra deals strictly with the way images appear on the surface of the consciousness of yogins who are practicing samatha and vipasyana meditation. it does not discuss the case of material objects imping. ing on the consciousness ofregular people in daily waking activity. Some standard interpretations providedby kuiji The pair of bimba andpratibimba became an important component of kuiji's account of the cognitive experience in a numerous ways, and it is primarily in his works that detailed explanations first appear regarding the meaning of bimba. one of the descriptions provided by kuiji, wherein bimba are explained as being produced from seeds" in the dlayavijna-na) is likely the source based on which some early westemn scholars ended up connecting bimba with the western notion of archetypes. one would guess that such scholars had tak-en biia to be something akinplatonic forms, or some other kind of original conceptual template which serves as the model for generating like appearances. however, since Yoga-caric biia are understoodto be continually in flux, created each instant as a combination of a wide range of factors, a reified interpretation such as that of " archetype"" misses the point.  〓he japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studie 200)woncheuk圓測on bimba本質andpratibimba影inhis commentary on the samdhimirmocana-sutra .c. muur Kuiji raises the topic of bimba and pratibimba in his commentaries in a variety of con-texts, many of them which deliberately problematize their relationship with each other, a well as their relationship with the four elements. Their role is examined in the function of a variety of mental states, both yogic and conventional, both human and non-human. There are cases where bimba are said to be produced from seeds, and cases where they are not. 〓n one hand, bimba are seen to be necessary as objective bases, as without them, prati-bimba would have no application whatsoever. on the other hand, for divine beings, the reliance on bimba to cognize objects is not necessary.1 nor are they always required in the cognition of those who are exercising supernatural powers.11) Kuiji's best known usage of本質and影像is seen in his analysis of the objects of cog-nition into three general types, known as the三類境(c. sanlei jing, j. sanrui kyo).12)the pair is also discussed making the distinction of影像being the " perceptual object directly perceived by the consciousness"親所縁(c. qin suoyuon, j. shin shoen), whereas bima-the raw substance本質,is not known directly, and is called the " indirectly perceived ob-iect"疎所縁(c. suoyuon, j. so shoen).these two aspects taken together are understood to constitute the "seen part"相分(c. xiang fen, j. sobun) of consciousness, being the "raw substance seen part"本質相分(c. benh xiangfen, j. honzetsu sobun) and the " reflected image seen part"影像相分(c. yingxiang xiangfen, J. yozo sobun). there are anumber of other ways that the pair fits into kuiii's articulations of cognitive function, but let us now proceed to the discussion of these concepts in woncheuk. bimba本質andpratibimba影像in woncheuk while the discussion of this pair of concepts in east asan buddhist weishi scholarship has been dominated by kuiji's extensive and detailed work, he is not the only one who saw the seminal importance of these categories for their applicationin various epistemological and hermeneutic situations, as woncheuk圓測(613-696),for one, also paid a fair amount of attention to this topic. while there does not seem to be anything in woncheuk's writings on this topic that directly disagrees with the interpretations of kuiji, nonetheless, as in his other writings, woncheuk tends to be an original thinker, and thus utilizes the pair in dif-ferent contexts, and draws on different sources than famous colleague and rival.in his commentary to the samdhinirmocana-sutra,9) woncheuk presents two major discussions involving bimba-pratibimbai one is in connection with the explication of the famous paral-  the japanese association of Indian and buddhist studies lel passage found in the samdhimirmocana-sutra and yogocarabhumi-sastra, wherein prar-ibimba are the obiects of samatha and vipasyana meditation, and where the precise mean ing of bimbais somewhat problematic. The other comes midway through the introductory portion of the commentary, where he is setting up his hermeneutic framework for the com-mentary through the discussion of such matters as the title of the sutra, the possibility for teaching, and so forth. here, we are introduced to a new type of application of bimba and pratibimba: an attempt to employ them in a situation not related to visual objects, as is a1- most always the case, but rather to the explanation of the "essence of the teaching"宗體 (c.zongtl;, J. shutai). while the discussion of bimba-pratibimba in the sutra passage on samatha and vipasyana is extremely valuable for understanding these concepts, due to space constraints, we will here limit our discussion to his usage of the concepts in his in troduction, since this is of greater interestin terms of showing woncheuk's creativity. Applying bimba adpratibimba in the identification of the essence of th Teaching宗體 If this model of the bimba-pratibimba pairis going to be applied as a way of distinguish-ing stages or modes in the process of the apprehension of perceptual objects, how should it work in the case of the other senses or perceptions, and what kind of vocabulary should be used? in most cases, this question may not so readily arise, since the visual model is sc predominant. both bimba and pratibimba fundamentally mean  image." and a11 of the ex-planations and metaphors are done through visual imagery, with the mirror and its refec-tions being the preeminent trope. but what about sound, odor, taste, and tactile sensation? How do we describe these, or try to make them work through the same paradigm? Here, we can see some wisdominxuanzang's choice of the compound word of本質to render bimba, which, unlike its Sanskrit counterpart, has no reference to imagery, but liter-ally means something like "raw substance." we can also understand, perhaps, that finding a term that functioned with equal neutrality among the sensory fields to refer to the " pro-cessed" aspect of sensation/perception would be much more challenging, and perhaps it is for that reason that he opted for the readily understandable equivalent of ereflected image"" 影像for pratibimba. this kind of awareness, however, cannot but problematize our attempts at English translation, if, for example, we needed to find a word that can also adequately express the same kind of modality as " reflected image"" for the processed form of sound or  The japanese association of indian and buddhist studies 202)woncheuk圓測on bimba本質and pratibimba影inhis commentry on the samdhinirmocana-sutra a.c.muLLER) other sensory and perceptual objects.14, woncheuk's discussion of本質/影像in the context of the "buddha's teaching" comes in the middle portion of his introduction to his commentary, where he is establishing his hermeneutical structure. in the section on the explanation of the essence of the teaching, woncheuk enters into an extensive philosophical inquiry attempting to identify exactly what the "essence" of the teaching is. This leads him to a discussion of the "three aggrega-tions" of words,名身(c. mingshen, j. myoshin), phrases句身(c. jushen, j. kushin), and syllables文身(c. wen shen, j. monshin), which further leads to the discussion of the rela-tion of these three to a fourth element-sound音聲(c. yinsheng, j. onsho)-and further, which of these is to be considered as the " essence"" of the teaching. since he enriches the argument by presenting a range of interpretations based on the viewpoints of various schools of lndian philosophy-both buddhist and non-buddhist-the discussion gets rath-er complicated, as some of the more prominent early indian philosophical texts had much to say about the metaphysical status of sound. in the final analysis, however, in the case of the buddhist scriptures, woncheuk takes "words" rather than "sound" as the essence, citing the opinion of his master xuanzang as the final authority. This discussion, which consists of a comparative analysis of the positions of various phi-losophers on the existence or not of "raw substance" and e representations" in the context of he previously discussed four phenomena of sound音聲and the aggregations of words名 身,phrases旬身,and syllables文身,starts off with These four dharmas, according to the Tathagata's own explanation, are called raw substance.' The listener's transformation of these through cognition is called erepresentation.' The distinction be-ween the existence and non-existence of these raw substances and representations is broadly distin uished into four kinds of tenets by the various traditions.! This is a novel and interesting application of the conceptof bimba/pratibimba that is some-what different from the type of explanation we find in kuiji's writings. Yet on the other hand, it might tell us something about the way that woncheuk, and perhaps the other bud-dhist thinkers ofhis period understood the notions of sound, words, phonemes, etc. For it seems that if we were presented with these four seminal indianabhidharmic-Yo-gacaric phenomena of words, phrases, phonemes, and sound, our first reaction would be to regard sound itself as a bimba, and the other three as pratibimba. but does taking a11 four as bimba mean that woncheuk sees words, phrases, and phonemes unifommly as pre-con-  the japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studie woncheuk圓測on bimba本質andprutibimba影inhis commemtary on the samdhimirmocana-siitra .c. mullER)(203 ceptual entities ? such an interpretation is not impossible. it would mean that he under= stands that our thinking consciousness apprehends a11 of these things to a certain level in these distinct yet " unrepresented"" units, and afterwards reflects them as meaningful units. Itmay also be the case that woncheuk is intentionally using the notion of bimba/pratibim-ba here in a looser sense as a hermeneutical device. The four hermeneutic positions that woncheuk sets up to distinguish the approaches of pri-or philosophers are those of: 1.the existence of raw substance and non-existence ofrepresentations有本無影, 2.the existence of representations and non-existence of raw substances有影無本; 3.the existence of both raw substances and representations本影倶有; 4.the existence of neither raw substances nor representations本影倶無. Ina format very close to that which he uses later onin his exegesis of the well-known bim-b-pratibimba discussion in the context of meditation, he summarizes a11 of the arguments of the philosophers who support each of the four positions, and then wraps up the discus- 〓on(as he often does in his commentary), citing xuanzang as the final authority (and on this occasion, dharmapala as well).this discussioncn be summarized as follows. 1.existence of Raw Substance and the non-Existence of Reflections有本無影-wonch-euk says that there are three philosophical streams that support this view.(1)that of the sarvastivadins, for whom a11 buddha-voices are only contaminated. Some also say that words, etc., are definitely of morally indeterminate karmic character. this kind of point is elaborated in detail in the mahavibhosa-sastra. (2)the position taken up by the Mahasamghika, ekavyavaharika一説部,lokottaravadins説出世部,kukkutika 〓胤部,and so forth, who say that a11 world-honored buddhas are transmundane, lack-ing contaminated dharmas. The words of the tathagatas turn the wheel of the dharma, the buddhas, in a single voice, explain a11 the teachings.(3)the position of the ba-husrutiya多聞部説,who take the "five notes" 1 of the buddhas teaching to be trans-mundane. a11 other kinds of voice are the mundane teachings. woncheuk comments that the reason a11 these schools have this misunderstanding is because they don't get the teaching of consciousness-only. ).existence of Reflections and non-Existence of Raw substances有影無本-the sec-ond tenet is that of the existence of representations and the non-existence of raw sub-stances. The nagasena那伽犀那say that the buddha-realization consists only of thus-  the japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studie 204)woncheuk圓測on bimba本質and pratibimba影像inhis commentary on the samdhimirmocana-sutra c. muller) ness and the thusness-cognition, and does not involve coarse attributes such as form, sound, and so forth. according to woncheuk, Sthiramati堅慧論師and Vairasena金 剛軍also support this interpretation. 3.Existence of both Raw substances and Reflections本影倶有-such scholars as can-dragupta月藏and bandhuprabha親光say that a11 tathagatas are endowed with such attributes as the form and sound of the three bodies. The suvarn-prabhasottamg. sutra says. 〓The tathagata is able to turn three kinds of dhamma wheels-the turning [wheel], illuminating [wheel], and the maintaining [wheel]this kind of teach-ing shows that what is witnessed is not the same. in some cases the listener's con-sciousness transforms [what is heard] to appear like another teaching. hence they know that raw substance and representations both exist. 4.existence of neither Raw substances nor reflections本影倶無-coming from the point of view of the absolute truth, bhavaviveka清辯advocates the emptiness of the natures of a11 dharmas. Some assume that dharmapala護法took the stance of the ul-timate truth when he said that in the tathagata's holy teaching, raw substances and representations are both non-existent. This is because in the ultimate truth, there are no words and so forth. Finally, he wraps up with: although the positions are categorized into four like this, the school of the trepitaka of the great Tang (xuanzang) and of dharmapala have two intenpretations. one is from the perspective the teaching of reality, in which there is only raw substance and no representations, this is because raw substance is that which is properly explained by the tathagata. in the second theory both are prop-erly included, this is because both arise according to the power of the tathagata's teaching. (hb 1.126c12-15) From here. this discussion segues into another fascinating discussion, that also deals with the elements of word, phonemes, sound, etc.-the discussion of the possibility of the holy teaching from an entirely different perspective: the question of how to deal with the statement appearing in the lankovatara-sutra and elsewhere that says "during the time between the night i attained supreme perfect enlightenment, until the night i entered final nirvana, i did not explain a single thing. Furthermore, it did not explain itin the past, and will not explain it in the future. not-explaining is the buddha's explanation." (t 670.16.49817-19)that, however, needs to be left as the topic for another paper.  the japanese ociationof Indian and buddhist studies woncheuk圓測on bimba本質and pratibimba影in his commentary on the samdhinirmocana-sutra . mullr)(205) 〓 1)we use the word "image" here with caution, because a full extension of the notion to a11 ensory functions means that it has to be more than simply " image," as will be noted below. 2)merriam-webster:(1)the original pattern or model of which a11 things of the same type ar epresentations or copies.(2)an inherited idea or mode of thought in the psychology of c. g. Jung that is derived from the experience of the race and is present in the unconscious of the individual. Japanese.アーキタイプ(典型,原型,元型)スイスの心理学者カール・ユンク の用いた心理学用語.人間の心の深層にあって遺伝的に伝わり,集合的無意識を作り 上げている心像の基本的な型.(webacdictionary: http://www.alc.co.ip/) 3)the yuqielun fi〓伽論記(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1828</w></ref>). 4)primarily in his cheng weishi lu shui成唯識論述記(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1830</w></ref>),and his cheng weishi lun zhangzhong shuyao成唯識論掌中樞要(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1831</w></ref>). 5)dealt with most recently in japanese scholarship by kato kojiro, who analyzed these pas sages, yielding the convincing report that they are not quite as identical in their full connotation as has been traditionally assumed. See kaTo kojiro,加藤弘二郎."pratibimba in the contex of vijnaptimatra Theory:comparative study of the sravakabhumi and the samdhinirmocang iitra (Chap.vi)「唯識」という文脈で語られる影像".indo tetsugaku bukkyyo kenkyu, vol.9, pp.-65. 6)This situation is of course tnue for many other seminal concepts that are held upas yYogacar: paradigms,as i have recently tried to demonstrate in my forthcoming article that deals with the development of the notion of the two hindrances, entitled eThe contribution of the yogdicarab humi to the systemof the two hindrances," ina edited volume in progress. 7)For example,玄師述三藏云.從頼耶識中名言種子生本質相.(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1828</w>.<p>427</p></ref>) 熏成種子生本質故.(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1831</w>.<p>40</p><c>b</c><l>16</l></ref>) 8)see, for example, <ref><canon>T</canon><w>1831</w>.<p>433</p>-<p>7</p></ref>.勝定果色大種造不.如對法第一末疏.雖有五文 説造不同.説先變爲大種後造色生.竝同繋等文者.有義此説依欲色二界地定果色.以 有所依身故.無色界定果色.從本質大種造.定中無大種.無所依身. 9)若約本質.或無本質法一切名等.同縁一境故.與事等不同.若影像相相似名等.何 事一種.無分別智縁如無影不可相似.不同一.故知有本質者.影像名相似.本質名同 一若無本質者.有爲縁相似名同一.無爲縁境一名同一.此據實縁故不相違(〓 1831.4-11) 10)其上天眼耳見聞下色聲不託本質.(<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1831</w>.<p>4</p><c>a</c><l>26</l></ref>) 11)若定通力所變五塵.非必有本質如生上界縁下界地色.或身在下起天眼耳縁上地色 等又解異熟之心縁境浮淺.非要藉本質.(t18314-23) 12)These are:(1)性境(c. xingiing, j. shokyo)objects as they are in themselves. these are im ages manifested through transformation based on raw substance, and are correct objects of cog-nition. They are manifested fromlaya) seeds.(2)獨影境(c. dying jing, j. dokup ko "image-only objects." objects manifested from a merely subjective view. these are objects that exist purely in the mind and have no relationship to any raw substance. illusions are examples of  the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhist studies 13)the hae simmil gyeong so解深密經疏,containedi hanguk bulgpo jeonseo vol.1, pp.123b-the objects of this category, but this can also include objects that appear in meditation, or obiects perceived by devas.(3)帶質境(c. doizhi jing, j. toizetsu kyo)obiects that derive from raw substance but which are not perceived exactly as they are. despite being grounded in raw sensate appearance, they are, according to the circumstance, not correctly apprehensible, and thus they are the sorts of obiects that we call "mistaken," "misconstrued," or "misidentified." see成唯識 論掌中樞要<ref><canon>T</canon><w>1831</w>.<v>43</v>.<p>60</p><c>a</c><l>20</l></ref>. 478c5. 14)although it is difficult to find an explanation of the concepts of bimba-pratibimbain anon-vi. 〓a1 trope, interestingly, dan lusthaus does use the example of sound to explain the meaning ot hyle in buddhist phenomenology(routledge-curzon, 2002),where he makes the helpful dis-tinction between tone (bimba) and note (pratibimba).(p.15) however, in the present context of woncheuk's discussion, we are not talking about music, and not even exactly about "speech, but the " buddha's teaching." for本質inthis case, perhaps we can still use tone, for the pro-cessed perception, however, it seem that it would be possible that representation could vary in units suchas phoneme, word, and phrase. 15)如是四法,如來自説,名爲本質.聞者識變名之爲影.如是本影有無差別,總約謠宗 有其四旬.(hbj11268-10) 16)These are the so-called suffering, emptiness, impemmanence, no-self, and the quiescence of nirvana-because these are cited from the holy teachings. 17)<ref><canon>T</canon><w>664</w>.<p>1668</p><c>b</c><l>1</l>-<l>11</l></ref>.these three are explained by paramartha and others as the three periods of the teaching三時教. 〓 abbreviations. 〓guk bulgyo jeonseo.韓國佛教全書(the collected works of korean buddhism)(1984). Seoul: dongguk University press. (Electronic text fromdongguk university used as source) 〓isho shinshu dizokvo.大正新脩大藏纒(japanese edition of the buddhist canon)(1924- 35).tokyo daizo kvokai. (Electronic texts from sat used as source (key words)woncheuk圓測,bimba本質,pratibimba影像,kuii窺基 (proiect professor, The university of Tokyo)  
</root>
