<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../cref.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../markup2.css" ?>
<root xml:lang="jp">
the japanese ssociation of Indian and buddhiststudies 〓n the collation of taisho tripitaka. acase oshuo 〓an shouyi jing 02 HuNG hung-lung Introduction The compilation of dai niho kotei shukusotsu di zkyo大日本校訂縮刷大藏經1 (abbreviated as tokyo edition) was originally basedon the version of koryo taeianggyong 高麗大藏經(abbreviated as koryo), then collated with the sog edition, zi fu zang資福 藏(abbreviated as song), the 〓ition, pu ning zang普寧藏(abbreviated as yuan) and the miig edition, bei zang北藏(abbreviated as ming) to finalize the compilations. On the other hand, the compilation of the version of taisho shinshu dizokyo大正新脩 大藏經(abbreviated as Toisho) was also based o koryo, then collated against the song, the yuan, the ming edition, obakuzo黄檗藏(abbreviated as ming),)the old sog ei-tion宮本3)(abbreviated as old-song), the shogo-z0聖語藏4)and the other editions to finalize the compilations. but after compiling the collations, how much creditability can the taisho and tokyo edition achieve ? 〓oshuonbn shouyi jjing T602 The main purpose of this essay is to compare the 2collations found in the first and second volumes of T2fshuo anm shouyi jling佛説大安般守意經5)(hereafter 〓bSYj)itaisho with the corresponding collations foundinokyo edition, to review the issues relating to the collations of taisho. after comparing the collations finished by Taisho and toky edition for -abSYj, we find that: Group a There are a total of1ollations in o which are identical to their counter-parts in the song, the yuam and the ming, but they are different from the ones in the old-song. Group b. on the other hand, if we ignore any collations between koryo and the old-song, and only tally the collations conducted between koyo and any edition of the song,  the japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies the yucn or the ming, we find that the number of these collations are 161 This means that after ignoring the taisho collations with the old song s part, the con. tents of the 161collations intaisho are identical to the counterpart contents that found in Toky edition. combining the 161collations from group b and the1ollations from Group aas mentioned above, there are a total of175collations that are identical between the two editions of taisho and tokyo.in other words, if we remove the collations from the 〓ld-song, out of the 2collations in tisho,175collations are identical to the ones found i okyo edition, which means 85%,almost90%of the collations are consistent with eack other between these two versions. collations in Taisho derived fromtokyoedition As a matter of fact, itis mentionedicmparison researchorshiuzhog zngiing mulu dizhoo kaoshi二十五種藏經目録對照考釋〓that the collations in taisho are de-rived fromokyo edition. This research also supports the credibility of such an argument. If we leave aside the aforementioned175identical collations, there are the other2col-lations which are inconsistent with each other between taisho and tokyo edition. within the 25collations, there are 9 mistaken collations found, where taisho quoted the collations from okyo edition unmodified. This demonstrates that while quoting the collations from Tokyo edition, the editor of taisho did not proofread the collations one by one. however, at the same time, we also fnd that taisho has corrected 8errors in the collations quoted fromtokyo edition. in any event. the editor of taisho quoted the original collations direct-ly from tokyo edition and did not carefully check the errors there. as a result, taisho ad opted9 collation errors which are the original mistakes ofthe tokyo edition. Taisho rectified5collation errors from tokvoedition as mentioned above, taisho also rectified another 8 collation errors that are derived from Tokyo edition. as far as Taisho is concemned, it directly adopted 9collation errors from to-kyo edition but rectified another 8 collation errors, an almost 1 to 1 ratio. This indicates that while quoting the collations fromokyo edition, the editor of taisho only rectified half of the errors, not every one of them. what's more, four correct collations fromtokyo edi-tion were quoted incorrectly by taisho; this is probably caused by negligence during the process of transcribing andproofreading, due to human-error  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhist studies Furthermore, there are three collations itaisho where the versions of the song, the Yuam or the ming are a11 different from the ones in koryo, the master copy of Taisho edi-tion. these three collations are not foundinokyo edition. That is to say, these three colla-tions, no matter they are in koy(the master copy of toky edition), the song, the yuam or the mfing, are a11 identical to each other. this clearly indicates that the versionof koryo used as the master copy of tokyo edition is different from the version of koryo which is used as the master copy of taisho, the former is a partially collated one. The problem of transcribing errors still persists through the process of proofreading among different ver-ions, e.g. the word of"耳"ikoyo is transcribed as "hu互"taisho, and is transcribed as "ya牙"intokvo edition. nine error collations adopted by Taisho from tokyo edition Table 1among the collations adopted by taisho fromokyo edition, there are nine er-rors due to a failure to double-check. The collation textinokyo edition shows "yi tong zuo yi已同作以2The meaning is hat the word yi巳"is parallel with the word eyi以."but no other edition here shows which texts are to be used to proofread with oky edition. but according to the preced-ing contents ofthe collation no.5, the proofread texts will be the yucn and the hfing. ltis obvious that while conducting the collation. the editor of Taisho has referred to the collations fnished by tokvo edtition, but they did not double check if these collations are actually collated with the yua and hing. the editor iust arbitrarily concluded that it has already been collated with the song, the yuam and the hing. This is how this kind of error due to negligence by the editor of tokyo edition. there is no collation for this annota-tion. The collation fnished by taisho has only been collated with the old-song. obvious-y, the editor of taisho found that there was no collation regarding this annotationi- 〓 etition, therefore the editor only collated it with the 〓ld-song. this resulted in the lere "the word echi持"is the same as the word e dai待",mentioned okoeditionis while conducting the collation, the editor of taisho quoted the collation directly from Tokvo edition, plus the collation fnished by the 〓ld-song, but the editor did not make up he omission of failing to refer to the hing by tokyo edition. This demonstrates that the errors found in taisho are due to direct quoting the colla  the japanese ssociationof Indian and buddhiststudies The editor of tokyo edition did not collate this annotation The editor of taisho only collated this annotation with the old-song since no related  ollation is available for reference inokyo edition. The editor of Taisho did not collate this annotation with other editions either. but in fact, this annotation should collate with as mentioned under annotation no.26.in which Tokyoetition illustrated that 'th }word"□" is the same as〓以" defined below.' The editor of taisho onlv collated this an. notation with the 〓ld-song. apparently the song, the yuan and the ming have been late with other editions. but in fact, besides the old-song, the editor should also collate The annotation ilan斂is the same as jian剣"itaisho is a collation against the old lt seems that there is no collation regarding this annotationinokyo edition. 'et there is a sideline on the left side of the word〓□已""and if we trace back. we cat nd that the annotation"已is the same as以.defined below" has already appeared in an-dotation6,the meaning of " defined below" can be applied to annotation no.186. In any case, after finding no collation regarding this annotation in taisho, the editor ailed to collate this annotation with the song. the yuan and the ming. Conclusion after comparing the collations one by one between taisho and tokyo edition, we can find that the accuracy rate of the collations finished by tokyo edition almost reached90%. although taisho not only referred to the collations finished by tokyo edition but also made use of the collations finished by many other versions, it did not correct a11 the origi-nal errors from tokyo edition, it only corrected half of the errors. i.e., the confidence level of the collations finished by taisho is95%.it is not easy for the collations of such a volu-  The japanese ssociation of indian and buddhist studies well, minous taisho to reach%accuracy, but this research does prove that in order to achieve the higher accuracy, reliability of textual criticism, in addition to the version that was adopted, human factors such as collating procedure also plays an important role as Though this research only focused on a single scripture in tisho to arrive at a conclu-sion, and it is still too early to draw any conclusion regarding the overall situation of the collations in taisho, the author still believes that this initial conclusion can serve as an in-dicator to a certain degree. For researchers who utilize chinese material as primary re-search data, in addition to referring to the collations finished in taisho, it would be better to find out the original versions of those materials to collate with. Notes 1)tokyo editionsmall typed),1885. 2)as the contents of obakuzo黄檗藏are parallel with bei zang北藏,so we abbreviate botl editions as the same hi edition.' 3)this is belonging to the library of the imperial household宮内省圖書寮本. 4)this is belonging to the library of the imperial treasure house shoso-in正倉院at nara. 5)<ref><canon>T</canon>no.<w>602</w>, vol.<v>15</v>,pp.<p>163</p><c>c</c>-<p>173</p><c>a</c></ref>. 6)tokyo editionNational diet library of Japan日本國會圖書館),shuku five宿五,pp.6- 73. 7)cai yun-chen蔡運辰,shin-wen-feng press.新文豐出版社,taipei,1983,p.539557. 8)annotation numberl(abbreviated as a. no.1)of <ref><canon>T</canon>.<w>602</w>,p.<p>164</p></ref>. 9)a. No. 3 of<ref><canon>T</canon>.<w>602</w>,p.<p>164</p></ref> 10)a. No.6of <ref><canon>T</canon>.<w>602</w>,p.<p>165</p></ref> 11)a. no. sof t.602,p.166 12)a. No.oft.62,p.167. 13)a. no.10of <ref><canon>T</canon>.<v>62</v>,p.<p>169</p></ref>. 14)a. No. 8of <ref><canon>T</canon>.<w>602</w>,p.<p>170</p></ref>. 15)a. No. 9of <ref><canon>T</canon>.<v>62</v>,p.<p>172</p></ref>. 16)a. no.21of<ref><canon>T</canon>.<v>62</v>,p.<p>172</p></ref>. &lt;Key words&gt; anban Shouyi jing, taisho tripitaka, collations, tokyo edition assistant Prof.. dharma drum buddhist college, taiwan)  
</root>
